<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<journal><operCard><operator>ИПУ РАН|Губко М.В.</operator><date>2023-03-12 18:49:00</date><cntArticle>8</cntArticle></operCard><issn>1819-2440</issn><eissn>1819-2467</eissn><titleid>10618</titleid><journalInfo lang="RUS"><title>Управление большими системами</title><abbrTitle>УБС</abbrTitle><publ>Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</publ><placePubl>Москва</placePubl><address>117997, г. Москва, ул. Профсоюзная, д. 65.</address></journalInfo><journalInfo lang="ENG"><title>Large-scale Systems Control</title><abbrTitle>LSSC</abbrTitle></journalInfo><issue><number>101</number><dateUni>202301</dateUni><pages>1–157</pages><articles><section><secTitle lang="RUS">Системный анализ</secTitle></section><article><pages>6-23</pages><artType>RAR</artType><authors><author num="1"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Краснов</surname><initials>Дмитрий Валентинович</initials><orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName><email>dim93kr@mail.ru</email><address>Москва</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Krasnov</surname><initials>Dmitry</initials><orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName><address>Moscow</address></individInfo></author></authors><artTitles><artTitle lang="RUS">Построение редуцированных наблюдателей состояния для систем с аффинными возмущениями</artTitle><artTitle lang="ENG">Construction of reduced state observers for systems with affine disturbances</artTitle></artTitles><abstracts><abstract lang="RUS">Объектом исследования являются линейные одноканальные системы с аффинными параметрическими и внешними возмущениями, представленные в так называемой треугольной форме «вход – выход». Относительный порядок по управлению равен размерности вектора состояния и не меняется при переходе к канонической форме «вход – выход» в предположении о гладкости внешних возмущений. Известно, что для таких систем только по измерениям выходной переменной можно построить наблюдатель смешанных переменных и восстановить линейные комбинации переменных состояния и внешних воздействий с заданной точностью. Полученных оценок достаточно для синтеза динамической обратной связи, обеспечивающей отслеживание выходной переменной заданного сигнала. В работе рассматривается важный практический случай, когда при некотором наборе датчиков выходная (регулируемая) переменная не измеряется. Нужно построить редуцированный наблюдатель состояния для ее оценивания, чтобы перейти к построению наблюдателя смешанных переменных. Вначале рассматриваются мотивирующие примеры систем второго порядка с различными измерениями и различными каналами действия внешних возмущений. Показано, что при измерении обеих переменных состояния с помощью кусочно-линейных корректирующих воздействий наблюдателя состояния можно восстановить внешние возмущения по их влиянию на систему (т.е. без использования динамического генератора возмущений). Формулируются условия, при которых этот принцип можно также использовать в системе с внешними возмущениями и неполными измерениями для восстановления неизмеряемой переменной состояния. Полученные результаты распространяются на конечномерные одноканальные системы произвольного порядка с аффинными возмущениями, в которых выходная переменная не измеряется. Формализованы условия существования и метод синтеза редуцированного наблюдателя с кусочно-линейным корректирующим воздействием, дающим оценку выходной переменной. Разработанный подход не требует идентификации внешних возмущений и решает задачу наблюдения выходной переменной с любой заданной точностью.</abstract><abstract lang="ENG">The object of study is linear single-channel systems with affine parametric and external disturbances, presented in the so-called triangular form "input-output". The relative degree in control is equal to the dimension of the state vector and does not change upon transition to the canonical form "input-output" under the assumption of smoothness of external disturbances. It is known that for such systems, only by measuring the output variable, it is possible to construct an observer of mixed variables and restore linear combinations of state variables and external influences with a given accuracy. The estimates obtained are sufficient for the synthesis of dynamic feedback, which provides tracking of the output variable of a given signal. The paper considers an important practical case when, for a certain set of sensors, the output (adjustable) variable is not measured. It is necessary to design a reduced state observer for its evaluation in order to proceed to the construction of a mixed variables observer. First, motivating examples of second-order systems with different dimensions and different channels of action of external disturbances are considered. It is shown that when measuring both state variables with the help of piecewise linear corrective actions of the state observer, it is possible to restore external disturbances by their influence on the system (i.e., without using a dynamic disturbance generator). Conditions are formulated under which this principle can also be used in a system with external disturbances and incomplete measurements to restore an unmeasured state variable. The results obtained are extended to finite-dimensional single-channel systems of arbitrary order with affine disturbances, in which the output variable is not measured. The conditions of existence and the method of synthesis of a reduced observer with a piecewise-linear corrective action, which gives an estimate of the output variable, are formalized. The developed approach does not require the identification of external disturbances and solves the problem of observing the output variable with any given accuracy.</abstract></abstracts><text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text><codes><udk>62.50</udk><bbk>32.817</bbk><doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.101.1</doi></codes><keywords><kwdGroup lang="ANY"><keyword>линейные системы</keyword><keyword>возмущения</keyword><keyword>редуцированный наблюдатель состояния</keyword><keyword>кусочно-линейная коррекция</keyword><keyword>linear systems</keyword><keyword>disturbances</keyword><keyword>reduced state observer</keyword><keyword>piecewise-linear correction</keyword></kwdGroup></keywords><references><reference>1. АНТИПОВ А.С., КРАСНОВ Д.В. Синтез системы сле-жения для однозвенного бездатчикового манипулятора при воздействии негладких возмущений // Проблемы управления. – 2022. – №3. – С. 3–15.</reference><reference>2. АНТИПОВ А.С., КРАСНОВА С.А., УТКИН В.А. Синтез инвариантных нелинейных одноканальных систем сле-жения с сигмоидальными обратными связями с обеспе-чением заданной точности слежения // Автоматика и те-лемеханика. – 2022. –№1. – С. 40–66.</reference><reference>3. БУСУРИН В.И., МЕДВЕДЕВ В.М., КАРАБИЦКИЙ А.С. Особенности модульного построения систем контроля и диагностики инерциальных систем управления // Тру-ды МАИ. – 2017. – №92. – С. 19.</reference><reference>4. КОКУНЬКО Ю.Г., КРАСНОВА С.А., УТКИН В.А. Кас-кадный синтез дифференциаторов с кусочно-линейными корректирующими воздействиями // Автоматика и те-лемеханика. – 2021. – №7. – С. 37–68.</reference><reference>5. КРАСНОВ Д.В. Синтез наблюдателя пониженного по-рядка для полноприводной электромеханической систе-мы // Управление большими системами. – 2022. – Вып. 96. – С. 31–48.</reference><reference>6. КРАСНОВ Д.В., АНТИПОВ А.С. Синтез двухконтурного наблюдателя в задаче управления однозвенным манипу-лятором в условиях неопределенности // Проблемы управления. – 2021. – №4. – С. 23–33. </reference><reference>7. КРАСНОВ Д.В., УТКИН А.В. Синтез многофункцио-нальной системы слежения в условиях неопределенно-сти // Управление большими системами. – 2017. – Вып. 69. – С. 29–49.</reference><reference>8. КРАСНОВА С.А. Оценивание внешних возмущений на основе виртуальных динамических моделей // Управле-ние большими системами. – 2018. – Вып. 76. – С. 6–25.</reference><reference>9. КРАСНОВА С.А., УТКИН А.В. Анализ и синтез мини-мально-фазовых нелинейных SISO систем при действии внешних несогласованных возмущений // Проблемы управления. – 2014. – №6. – C. 22–30.</reference><reference>10. МАЛИКОВ А.И. Синтез наблюдателей состояния и не-известных входов для нелинейных липшицевых систем с неопределенными возмущениями // Автоматика и телеме-ханика. –2018. – №3. – С. 21–43.</reference><reference>11. НИКИФОРОВ В.О. Адаптивное и робастное управление с компенсацией возмущений. – СПб.: Наука, 2003. – 282 с.</reference><reference>12. УОНЕМ У.М. Линейные многомерные системы управле-ния. Геометрический подход. – М.: Наука, 1980. – 376 c.</reference><reference>13. УТКИН В.А., УТКИН А.В. Задача слежения в линейных системах с параметрическими неопределенностями при неустойчивой нулевой динамике // Автоматика и телеме-ханика. – 2014. – №9. – С. 62–81.</reference><reference>14. ФОМИЧЕВ В.В., ВЫСОЦКИЙ А.О. Каскадный метод построения наблюдателей для систем с неопределенно-стью // Дифференциальные уравнения. – 2018. – Т. 54, №11. – С. 1533–1539.</reference><reference>15. LEVANT A. Robust exact differentiation via sliding mode technique // Automatica. – 1998. – Vol. 34, Iss. 3. – P. 379–384.</reference><reference>16. LUENBERGER D.B. Observers of multivariable systems // IEEE Trans. on Automatic Control. – 1966. – Vol. 11, No. 2. – P. 190–197.</reference><reference>17. SPONG M., HUTCHINSON S., VIDYASAGAR M. Robot Modeling and Control. – New York: Wiley, 2005. – 496 p.</reference></references><files><furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23081</furl><file>UBS10101.pdf</file></files><dates><dateReceived>10.12.2022.</dateReceived></dates></article><section><secTitle lang="RUS">Математическая теория управления</secTitle></section><article><pages>24-38</pages><artType>RAR</artType><authors><author num="1"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Берлин</surname><initials>Леонид Михайлович</initials><orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName><email>berlin.lm@phystech.edu</email><address>Москва</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Berlin</surname><initials>Leonid</initials><orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName><address>Moscow</address></individInfo></author><author num="2"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Галяев</surname><initials>Андрей Алексеевич</initials><orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName><email>galaev@ipu.ru</email><address>Москва</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Galyaev</surname><initials>Andrey</initials><orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName><address>Moscow</address></individInfo></author><author num="3"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Кравцова</surname><initials>Софья Константиновна</initials><orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName><email>kravtsovasofja@mail.ru</email><address>Москва</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Kravtsova</surname><initials>Sofia</initials><orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName><address>Moscow</address></individInfo></author></authors><artTitles><artTitle lang="RUS">О классе двух переключений управления в задаче быстродействия двух несинхронных осцилляторов</artTitle><artTitle lang="ENG">About two-switching control class in the time-optimal control problem of two non-synchronous oscillators</artTitle></artTitles><abstracts><abstract lang="RUS">Рассматривается задача быстродействия в системе, состоящей из двух несинхронных осцилляторов. Исследуемая постановка имеет ряд отличительных особенностей, таких как, например, то, что каждый из осцилляторов системы управляется единым ограниченным скалярным управлением, целью которого является разгон первого осциллятора из состояния покоя в заданное положение. В терминальный момент фазовые координаты второго осциллятора снова становятся равными нулю. Оптимальное управление в данной задаче имеет релейный вид, поэтому ключевыми являются решения с различным количеством переключений управления. Базовым является случай с тремя переключениями, так как в данном классе управления достаточно использовать решение системы уравнений динамики. Для большего количества неизвестных моментов переключения известны необходимые условия оптимальности, позволяющие рассматривать произвольные классы управления. При различных вырождениях указанных классов происходит изменение количества переключений управления. Интерес представляет класс двух переключений, для значений параметров которого выписаны функциональные зависимости. Проведено математическое моделирование для иллюстрации полученных аналитических результатов.</abstract><abstract lang="ENG">The time-optimal control problem in a system consisting of two non-synchronous oscillators is considered. The studied formulation has a number of distinctive features, such as, for example, that each of the oscillators is controlled by a common bounded scalar control and the goal is to accelerate the first oscillator from rest to a given position in the shortest time. At the terminal moment the phase coordinates of the second oscillator become zero again. The optimal control is a relay mode, so solutions with different numbers of control switchings are the key. The basic one is the three-switching control class and for a larger number of unknown switching moments the necessary optimality conditions are known. The two-switching control class obtained by degeneracies is of interest, where functional dependences are written out for the values of interval durations. Mathematical modeling was carried out to illustrate the obtained analytical results.</abstract></abstracts><text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text><codes><udk>517.9</udk><bbk>32.96</bbk><doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.101.2</doi></codes><keywords><kwdGroup lang="ANY"><keyword>принцип максимума Понтрягина</keyword><keyword>релейное управление</keyword><keyword>осцилляторы</keyword><keyword>Pontryagin's maximum principle</keyword><keyword>relay control</keyword><keyword>oscillators</keyword></kwdGroup></keywords><references><reference>1. БЕРЛИН Л.М., ГАЛЯЕВ А.А., ЛЫСЕНКО П.В. Геометриче-ский подход к задаче оптимального скалярного управления дву-мя несинхронными осцилляторами // Итоги науки и техники. Со-временная математика и ее приложения. Тематические обзоры. –2022. – Т. 215. – С. 40–51.</reference><reference>2. БЕРЛИН Л.М., ГАЛЯЕВ А.А. Условия экстремума при ограни-ченном скалярном управлении двумя несинхронными осциллято-рами в задаче быстродействия // Доклады Российской академиинаук. Математика, информатика, процессы управления. – 2022. –Т. 505, №1. – С. 86–91.</reference><reference>3. БОЛТЯНСКИЙ В.Г. Математические методы оптимальногоуправления. – М.: Наука, 1969. – 408 c.</reference><reference>4. КАЮМОВ О.Р. Оптимальное по быстродействию перемещениеплатформы с осцилляторами // Прикладная математика и меха-ника. – 2021. – Т. 85, №6. – С. 699–718.</reference><reference>5. ЧЕРНОУСЬКО Ф.Л., АКУЛЕНКО Л.Д., СОКОЛОВ Б.Н. Управле-ние колебаниями. – М.: Наука, 1980. – 384 c.</reference><reference>6. ANDRESEN B., SALAMON P., HOFFMANN K.H., TSIRLIN A.M.Optimal processes for controllable oscillators // Automation andRemote Control – 2018. – Vol. 79. – P. 2103–2113.</reference><reference>7. BERLIN L.M., GALYAEV A.A., LYSENKO P.V. Time-optimalcontrol problem of two non-synchronous oscillators // Mathematics –2022. – Vol. 10, No. 19. – P. 3552.</reference><reference>8. FEDOROV A.K., OVSEEVICH A.I. Asymptotic control theory fora system of linear oscillators // Mosc. Math. J. – 2016. – Vol. 16. –P. 561–598.</reference><reference>9. PESCH H.J., PLAIL M. The Maximum Principle of optimal control:A history of ingenious ideas and missed opportunities // ControlCybern. – 2009. – Vol. 38. – P. 973–995.</reference><reference>10. SALOBUTINA E.O. Regimes of more and more frequent switchingsin the optimal control problem of oscillations of n oscillators // J.Math. Sci. – 2008. – Vol. 151. – P. 3603–3610.</reference><reference>11. ZHAO Y., CHEN G.H. Two oscillators in a dissipative bath // Phys.A: Stat. Mech. Appl. – 2003. – Vol. 317. – P. 13–40.</reference></references><files><furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23082</furl><file>UBS10102.pdf</file></files><dates><dateReceived>17.01.2023.</dateReceived></dates></article><section><secTitle lang="RUS">Анализ и синтез систем управления</secTitle></section><article><pages>39-63</pages><artType>RAR</artType><authors><author num="1"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Жуков</surname><initials>Пётр Игоревич</initials><orgName>Старооскольский технологический институт им. А.А. Угарова (филиал) НИТУ «МИСиС»</orgName><email>Zhukov.petr86@yandex.ru</email><address>Старый Оскол</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Zhukov</surname><initials>Petr</initials><orgName>STI NUST “MISIS”</orgName><address>Stary Oskol</address></individInfo></author><author num="2"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Фомин</surname><initials>Андрей Вячеславович</initials><orgName>Старооскольский технологический институт им. А.А. Угарова (филиал) НИТУ «МИСиС»</orgName><email>verner444@yandex.ru</email><address>Старый Оскол</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Fomin</surname><initials>Andrey</initials><orgName>STI NUST “MISIS”</orgName><address>Stary Oskol</address></individInfo></author><author num="3"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Глущенко</surname><initials>Антон Игоревич</initials><orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName><email>aiglush@ipu.ru</email><address>Москва</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Glushchenko</surname><initials>Anton</initials><orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName><address>Moscow</address></individInfo></author></authors><artTitles><artTitle lang="RUS">Алгоритмическая устойчивость и сложность процесса неявной адаптации сеточной модели нестационарной теплопроводности к нагреваемому веществу</artTitle><artTitle lang="ENG">Algorithmic stability and complexity of implicit adaptation of nonstationary thermal conductivity mesh model to heated substance</artTitle></artTitles><abstracts><abstract lang="RUS">Рассматривается процесс адаптации численной модели нестационарной теплопроводности, реализованной при помощи методов конечных разностей. Для классического представления данных моделей в большинстве приложений и задач уже доказана алгоритмическая устойчивость, но в данном случае рассматривается задача, связанная с параметрической адаптацией уравнения нестационарной теплопроводности к нагреваемому веществу, выполненной при помощи решения смежной вариационной задачи. Основа данного подхода предполагает замену теплофизических параметров рассматриваемого уравнения на свободно настраиваемые параметры и их коррекцию («обучение модели») методом стохастического градиента. Чтобы избежать попадания в области неустойчивости при «обучении», необходимы ограничения на введенные настраиваемые параметры. В данной работе такие ограничения получены на основании доказанных условий устойчивости классической конечно-разностной модели нестационарной теплопроводности. В результате численного эксперимента было установлено, что предлагаемые ограничения позволяют в среднем увеличить количество устойчивых начальных условий на 14%, увеличить количество попаданий в устойчивые траектории на 61%. Также было проведено аналитическое сравнение порядков роста алгоритмической сложности классической и модифицированной модели. В результате расчетов было установлено, что обе модели имеют порядок роста О(n4), что было подтверждено численным экспериментом.</abstract><abstract lang="ENG">This paper deals with the process of adaptation of a numerical model of nonstationary thermal conductivity implemented with the help of finite difference methods. The algorithmic stability has already been proved for the classical representation of these models in most applications and problems, but in this case we consider a problem related to the parametric adaptation of the equation of nonstationary heat conduction to the heated substance implemented by solving of the related variational problem. The basis of this approach implies replacement of thermophysical parameters of the equation in question by freely adjustable parameters and their adaptation ("model training") by a stochastic gradient method. Optimization of algorithmic equations that do not have an analytical form is associated with unstable initial conditions and "training" trajectories. To avoid falling into these regions we need to impose restrictions on the adjustable parameters. In this paper, such constraints are derived on the basis of proven stability conditions for the classical finite-difference model of non-stationary thermal conductivity. As a result of the numerical experiments, it is shown that the proposed constraints allow one to increase, on average, the number of stable initial conditions by 13%, as well as the number of experiments when stable trajectories are achieved - by 61%. In addition to this result, an analytical comparison of the growth orders of algorithmic complexity of the classical model and the modified one is also made. As a result of the calculations, it is found that both models have a growth order of O(n4), which is confirmed by numerical experiments.</abstract></abstracts><text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text><codes><udk>519.63</udk><bbk>22.193</bbk><doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.101.3</doi></codes><keywords><kwdGroup lang="ANY"><keyword>сеточная модель</keyword><keyword>нестационарная теплопроводность</keyword><keyword>адаптация</keyword><keyword>градиентный метод</keyword><keyword>алгоритмическая сложность</keyword><keyword>вычислительная устойчивость</keyword><keyword>mesh model</keyword><keyword>nonstationary thermal conductivity</keyword><keyword>adaptation</keyword><keyword>gradient descent method</keyword><keyword>algorithmic complexity</keyword><keyword>computational stability</keyword></kwdGroup></keywords><references><reference>1. БУЛАНОВ С.Г. Анализ устойчивости систем линейных дифференциальных уравнений на основе преобразования разностных схем // Мехатроника, автоматизация, управ-ление. – 2019. – Т. 20, №9. – С. 542–549.</reference><reference>2. ВЕРЖБИЦКИЙ В.М. Основы численных методов. – Москва-Берлин: Директ-Медиа, 2021. – 849 с. </reference><reference>3. ДЕГТЯРЁВ С.Л. Об устойчивости разностных схем с переменными весами для одномерного уравнения тепло-проводности // Журнал вычислительной математики и математической физики. – 1994. – Т. 34, №8–9. – С. 1316–1322.</reference><reference>4. ДЕГТЯРЕВ С.Л. Устойчивость локально неявных раз-ностных схем для двумерного нестационарного уравне-ния теплопроводности // Препринты ИПМ им. МВ Кел-дыша. – 1994. – №76. – С. 1–24.</reference><reference>5. ЖУКОВ П.И., ФОМИН А.В., ГЛУЩЕНКО А.И. Неявная адаптация сеточной модели нестационарной тепло-проводности к нагреваемому веществу // Управление большими системами. – 2022. – Вып. 100. – С. 78–106.</reference><reference>6. ЖУКОВ П.И., ГЛУЩЕНКО А.И., ФОМИН А.В. Модель для прогнозирования температуры заготовки по ре-троспекции ее нагрева на основе бустинга структуры // Вестник Новосибирского государственного университе-та. Серия: Информационные технологии. – 2020. – Т. 18, №4. – С. 11–27.</reference><reference>7. МАТУС П.П. Критерий устойчивости разностных схем для нелинейных дифференциальных задач // Дифферен-циальные уравнения. – 2021. – Т. 57, №6. – С. 821–829.</reference><reference>8. ОЖЕРЕЛКОВА Л.М., САВИН Е.С. Температурная зави-симость нестационарной теплопроводности твердых тел // Russian Technological Journal. – 2019. – Т. 7, №2. – С. 49–60.</reference><reference>9. ПАРСУНКИН Б.Н., АНДРЕЕВ С.М., МУХИНА Е.Ю. Экстремально-оптимизирующее автоматизированное управление нагревом непрерывнолитых заготовок в пе-чах проходного типа // Вестник Череповецкого государ-ственного университета. – 2021. – №5 (104). – С. 22–34.</reference><reference>10. ФРОЛОВ А.Ю., ДРУЖИНИНА О.В. Устойчивость раз-ностных схем численного решения обобщенной системы уравнений Максвелла в задачах моделирования Z-пинчей // Электромагнитные волны и электронные системы. – 2020. – Т. 25, №3. – С. 5–13.</reference><reference>11. BARBASOVA T.A., FILIMONOVA A.A., ZAKHA-ROV A.V. Energy-saving oriented approach based on model predictive control system // IEEE Int. Russian Auto-mation Conference. – IEEE, 2019. – P. 243-252.</reference><reference>12. BELYAEV A.M., IVANOV I.N., BELYAEV E.D. Digital Technologies in Russian Metallurgy // Institute of Scientific Communications Conference. – Springer, Cham, 2021. – P. 1817–1824.</reference><reference>13. FENG Y., WU M., CHEN L., CHEN X., CAO W., DU S., PEDRYCZ W. Hybrid intelligent control based on condition identification for combustion process in heating furnace of compact strip production // IEEE Trans. on Industrial Elec-tronics. – 2021. – Vol.69, No. 3. – P. 2790–2800</reference><reference>14. HADJISKI M., DELIISKI N. Advanced Process Control of Distributed Parameter Plants by Integration First Principle Modeling and Case-Based Reasoning: Part 1: Framework of DPP Control with Initial Uncertainty // Int. Conf. Auto-matics and Informatics – 2020 (ICAI–2020). – IEEE, 2020. – P. 1–6.</reference><reference>15. HARVEY N. J., LIAW C., PLAN Y., RANDHAWA S Tight analyses for non-smooth stochastic gradient descent // Con-ference on Learning Theory. – PMLR, 2019. – P. 1579–1613.</reference><reference>16. SCHULTE M. Steel Production Efficiency Improvements by Digitalization // REWAS 2022: Developing Tomorrow’s Technical Cycles. – 2022. – Vol. 1. – P. 487–488.</reference><reference>17. SHCHERBAKOV M.V., GLOTOV A.V., CHEREMIS-INOV S.V. Proactive and predictive maintenance of cyber-physical systems // Cyber-Physical Systems: Advances in Design &amp; Modelling. – Springer, Cham, 2020. – P. 263-278.</reference><reference>18. VASILYEVA N., FEDOROVA E., KOLESNIKOV A. Big data as a tool for building a predictive model of mill roll wear // Symmetry. – 2021. – Vol. 13, No. 5. – P. 859–870.</reference><reference>19. YU B., HU P., SAPUTRA A. A., GU Y. The scaled bounda-ry finite element method based on the hybrid quadtree mesh for solving transient heat conduction problems // Applied Mathematical Modelling. – 2021. – Vol. 89. – P. 541–571.</reference><reference>20. ZANOLI S. M., BARBONI L., COCCHIONI F., PEPE C. Advanced process control aimed at energy efficiency im-provement in process industries. // IEEE Int. Conf. on Indus-trial Technology (ICIT–2018). – IEEE, 2018. – P. 57–62.</reference><reference>21. ZANOLI S. M., PEPE C., MOSCOLONI E., ASTOLFI G. Data Analysis and Modelling of Billets Features in Steel In-dustry // Sensors. – 2022. – Vol. 22, No. 19. – P. 7333.</reference></references><files><furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23083</furl><file>UBS10103.pdf</file></files><dates><dateReceived>01.12.2022.</dateReceived></dates></article><section><secTitle lang="RUS">Управление в социально-экономических системах</secTitle></section><article><pages>64-85</pages><artType>RAR</artType><authors><author num="1"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Гераськин</surname><initials>Михаил Иванович</initials><orgName>Самарский национальный исследовательский университет имени академика С. П. Королёва</orgName><email>innovation@ssau.ru</email><address>Самара</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Geraskin</surname><initials>Mikhail</initials><orgName>Samara National Research University named after Academician S.P. Korolev</orgName><address>Samara</address></individInfo></author><author num="2"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Иванова</surname><initials>Мария Владимировна</initials><orgName>Самарский национальный исследовательский университет имени академика С. П. Королёва</orgName><email>ivanova.maria.ami@gmail.com</email><address>Самара</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Ivanova</surname><initials>Maria</initials><orgName>Samara National Research University named after Academician S.P. Korolev</orgName><address>Samara</address></individInfo></author></authors><artTitles><artTitle lang="RUS">Моделирование взаимодействий институтов рынка жилья на основе степенных, экспоненциальных и логарифмических функций издержек</artTitle><artTitle lang="ENG">Modeling interactions of institutions of housing markets based on power, exponential and log cost functions</artTitle></artTitles><abstracts><abstract lang="RUS">Представлена система условий оптимальности агентов рынка жилья (риелтора, банка и страховщика) при степенных, экспоненциальных и логарифмических функциях издержек, соответствующих различным типам эффекта масштаба. Представлены результаты численных экспериментов, демонстрирующие характер взаимозависимостей цен на этом рынке при различных видах функций. В отличие от исследования системы «риелтор – банк – страховщик» на основе линейных функций издержек данная работа представляет следующие выводы: во-первых, в случае, когда все агенты имеют вогнутые функции издержек, цена недвижимости, процентная ставка по ипотечному кредиту и тариф страхования ниже, чем в случае, когда агенты имеют выпуклые функции издержек; во-вторых, рост ставки внутрисистемной комиссии приводит к росту цены того агента, который платит комиссию, и снижению цены того агента, который ее получает; в-третьих, увеличение ставки комиссии ведет к более резкому снижению цены агента в том случае, когда он имеет выпуклую функцию издержек, а контрагент – вогнутую, чем в противном случае. При сравнении эффективности применения разных типов функций издержек было выявлено, что логарифмические и экспоненциальные функции дают большую точность, чем степенные.</abstract><abstract lang="ENG">The article presents a system of optimality conditions for housing market agents (realtor, bank and insurer) with power, exponential and logarithmic cost functions corresponding to different types of economies of scale. The results of numerical experiments are presented, demonstrating the nature of price interdependencies in these markets for various types of functions. In contrast to the study of the "realtor – bank – insurer" system based on linear cost functions, this work presents the following conclusions: firstly, in the case when all agents have concave cost functions, then the real estate price, mortgage interest rate and insurance tariff lower than in the case when agents have convex cost functions; secondly, an increase in the intrasystem commission rate leads to an increase in the price of the agent who pays the commission, and a decrease in the price of the agent who receives it; thirdly, an increase in the commission rate leads to a sharper decrease in the price of an agent, in the case when he has a convex cost function, while the counterparty has a concave one, than otherwise. When comparing the effectiveness of using different types of cost functions, it was found that logarithmic and exponential functions provide greater accuracy than power functions.</abstract></abstracts><text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text><codes><udk>330.4</udk><bbk>65.05</bbk><doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.101.4</doi></codes><keywords><kwdGroup lang="ANY"><keyword>оптимальная стратегия</keyword><keyword>риелтор</keyword><keyword>банк</keyword><keyword>страховщик</keyword><keyword>optimal strategy</keyword><keyword>realtor</keyword><keyword>bank</keyword><keyword>insurer</keyword></kwdGroup></keywords><references><reference>1. ЗАМЯТИНА А.Ю. Построение модели отраслевой функции издержек естественной монополии ОАО «РЖД» // JSRP. – 2014. – №14(18). – С. 25–30.</reference><reference>2. КОСОРУКОВ О.А., СВИРИДОВА О.А. Модель миними-зации издержек в системах управления запасами // Вестник РЭА им. Г.В. Плеханова. – 2009. – №6. – С. 52–58.</reference><reference>3. КУРИЛЁНОК К., КУРИЛЁНОК Е. Новые Методы эко-номического анализа // Наука и инновации. –2019. – №12(202). – С. 61–66.</reference><reference>4. Медиа-информационная группа «Страхование сегодня». Динамика рынка. – Url: http://www.insur-info.ru/statistics/ (дата обращения: 23.01.2021).</reference><reference>5. ОАО «РЕСО-ГАРАНТИЯ», Отчетность по МСФО. – URL: https://www.reso.ru/shareholders/finance/msfo/ (дата обращения: 19.01.2021).</reference><reference>6. Отчетность по МСФО. ГК ПИК. – URL: https://pik-group.ru/about/news-and-reports/reports/financial-results (дата обращения: 19.01.2021).</reference><reference>7. ПЛЕЩЕНКО В.И. Оптимизация издержек промышлен-ных предприятий при работе с альтернативными по-ставщиками // Экономический анализ: теория и практи-ка. – 2011. – №25. – С. 47–50.</reference><reference>8. Рейтинговое агентство «РИА РЕЙТИНГ». Рэнкинг страховых компаний по итогам 2014 года. – URL: http://riarating.ru/insurance_companies_rankings/20150319/610649976.html (дата обращения: 23.01.2021).</reference><reference>9. Росриэлт недвижимость, цены на недвижимость в Рос-сии. – URL: https://rosrealt.ru/cena (дата обращения: 19.01.2021).</reference><reference>10. Сбербанк, отчетность по МСФО. – URL: https://www.sberbank.com/ru/investor-relations/reports-and-publications/ifrs (дата обращения: 19.01.2021).</reference><reference>11. Центральный Банк, статистика. URL: https://www.cbr.ru/statistics/table/?tableid=4-1 (дата обращения: 19.01.2021). </reference><reference>12. Центральный Банк, статистика. – URL: https://www.cbr.ru/statistics/insurance/report_individual_ins/?unid-bquery.posted=true&amp;unidbquery.dttype=1&amp;unidbquery.to=2020 (дата обращения: 19.01.2021). </reference><reference>13. CALOMIRIS C.W., JAREMSKI M. Deposit insurance: theo-ries and facts // Annual Review of Financial Economics. – 2016. – Vol. 8, No. 1. – P. 97–120.</reference><reference>14. CARBAUGH R. Contemporary economics: an applications approach // Cengage Learning. – 2006. – P. 35. </reference><reference>15. GERASKIN M. Pricing analysis of interconnected markets of housing, mortgage lending and insurance // Kybernetes. – 2020. – Vol. 50, No. 5. – Р. 1212–1249.</reference><reference>16. JONES K. Fha-insured home loans: an overview // The Housing Finance System in the United States. –2013. – P. 44–58.</reference><reference>17. PARK K.A. Temporary loan limits as a natural experiment in federal housing administration insurance // Housing Poli-cy Debate. – 2017. – Vol. 27, No. 3. – P. 449–466.</reference><reference>18. TIROLE J. The theory of industrial organization. – Cam-bridge: MIT Press, 1988. – 496 p.</reference><reference>19. WALTERS A.A. Production and cost functions: and econo-metric survey // Econometrica. – 1963. – No. 31(1). – Р. 23–44.</reference></references><files><furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23084</furl><file>UBS10104.pdf</file></files><dates><dateReceived>01.12.2022.</dateReceived></dates></article><section><secTitle lang="RUS">Управление техническими системами и технологическими процессами</secTitle></section><article><pages>86-96</pages><artType>RAR</artType><authors><author num="1"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Третьякова</surname><initials>Екатерина Алексеевна</initials><orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName><email>ekaterina_tretikova@mail.ru</email><address>Москва</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Tretyakova</surname><initials>Ekaterina</initials><orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName><address>Moscow</address></individInfo></author></authors><artTitles><artTitle lang="RUS">Моделирование гидроудара в аксиально-плунжерном насосе</artTitle><artTitle lang="ENG">Simulation of a water hammer in an axial piston pump</artTitle></artTitles><abstracts><abstract lang="RUS">Представлен подход к моделированию аксиально-плунжерного насоса компакт-серии с наклонным блоком и выполнен гидродинамический расчет. Были изучены существующие модели аксиально-плунжерного насоса, в ходе чего обнаружен скачок расхода в момент гидроудара, однако «величина удара» была неизвестна. При моделировании вводились допущения, связанные со свойствами рабочей жидкости и геометрией плунжера, также не учитывались температурные изменения. В процессе моделирования были выделены четыре этапа. Первый этап включает в себя создание объёма жидкости – жидкостную модель по твердотельной модели насоса. На втором этапе была создана сетка. Третий этап посвящён созданию макросов для движения выделенных ранее составляющих насоса. На четвёртом этапе все подготовленные части модели выгружаются во Fluent 18.1 и производится установка параметров расчёта. Адекватность полученной модели была оценена при помощи сравнения смоделированного полного расхода насоса с величиной теоретического расхода, рассчитанной аналитически. В ходе моделирования была вычислена амплитуда скачка давления во время гидроудара на рабочем режиме насоса при максимальном давлении нагнетания. Был предложен метод по его снижению. Внесены изменения в конструкцию плунжера. Проведен расчет на прочность измененной конструкции.</abstract><abstract lang="ENG">The paper presents an approach to modeling an axial piston pump compact series with an inclined block and performed a hydrodynamic calculation. Existing models of the axial piston pump were studied, during which a jump in flow was found at the time of water hammer, but the "shock magnitude" was unknown. During modeling, assumptions related to the properties of the working fluid and the geometry of the plunger were introduced, and temperature changes were also not taken into account. Four stages were identified in the modeling process. The first stage involves the creation of a fluid volume - a fluid model from a solid model of the pump. In the second step, a mesh was created. The third stage is devoted to creating macros for the movement of the previously selected pump components. At the fourth stage, all prepared parts of the model are uploaded to Fluent 18.1 and the calculation parameters are set. The adequacy of the resulting model was assessed by comparing the simulated total pump flow with the theoretical flow calculated analytically. Upon the simulation, the amplitude of the pressure jump was calculated during the water hammer in the operating mode of the pump at the maximum discharge pressure. A method was proposed to reduce it. Changes have been made to the design of the plunger. The strength of the modified structure was calculated.</abstract></abstracts><text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text><codes><udk>62-12</udk><bbk>31.16</bbk><doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.101.5</doi></codes><keywords><kwdGroup lang="ANY"><keyword>аксиально-плунжерный насос</keyword><keyword>гидродинамический расчёт</keyword><keyword>модель</keyword><keyword>плунжер</keyword><keyword>сетка</keyword><keyword>удар</keyword><keyword>клапан</keyword><keyword>axial piston pump</keyword><keyword>hydrodynamic calculation</keyword><keyword>model</keyword><keyword>plunger</keyword><keyword>mesh</keyword><keyword>water hummer</keyword><keyword>valve</keyword></kwdGroup></keywords><references><reference>1. БЕЛОВ Н.А., НИКИТИН О.Ф. Профилирование проточ-ной части нагнетательного канала аксиально-поршневого насоса // МГТУ им. Н.Э. Баумана, Москва, 2019. – 53 с.</reference><reference>2. НИКОЛЕНКО И.В., РЫЖАКОВ А.Н. Математическое моделирование рабочего процесса в гидроприводе на основе регулируемых акссиально-поршневых гидрома-шин // Наука и образование. МГТУ им. Баумана. – 2015. – №9 – C. 17–31.</reference><reference>3. ПУЗАНОВ А.В. Гидромеханический анализ ходовой ча-сти аксиально-поршневой гидромашины // Вестник Брянского государственного технического университета. – 2016. – №4. – C.161–169.</reference><reference>4. ПУЗАНОВ А.В., ЕРШОВ Е.А. Моделирование индика-торной диаграммы аксиально-плунжерной гидромаши-ны // Вестник Брянского государственного технического университета. – 2017. – №3(56) – C. 29–35.</reference><reference>5. РОДИОНОВ Л.В. и др. Методические указания для кур-сового проекта «Проектирование объемного насоса» метод. указания. – Самара: Изд-во Самар. гос. аэрокосм. ун-та, 2011. – C. 32.</reference><reference>6. BERTA G.L., CASOLI P, VACCA A. Simulation model of axial piston pumps inclusive of cavitation // Proc. of Fluid Power Systems and Technology Division (FPSTD) ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress and Exposi-tion, 2015.</reference><reference>7.  BIN ZHANG, JIEN MA, HAOCEN HONG, HUAYONG YANG, YOUTONG FANG Analysis of the flow dynamics characteristics of an axial piston pump based on the compu-tational fluid dynamics method // Journal of Aeronautics. Engineering Applications of Computational Fluid Mechan-ics. – 2017. – Vol. 11. – P. 86–95.</reference><reference>8. EDGE K.A., DARLING J. Cylinder pressure transients in oil hydraulic pump with sliding plate valves. – School of Engineering, University of Bath, 2016. – 45 р.</reference><reference>9. GUAN CHANGBIN, JIAO ZONGXIA, HE SHOUZHAN Theoretical study of flow ripple for an aviation axial-piston pump with damping holes in valve // Journal of Aeronautics. School of Automation Science and Engineering, Beihang University, Beijing, China, 2013. – 182 p.</reference><reference>10. IVANTYSYNOVA M. The Piston Cylinder Assembly in Pis-ton Machines // A Long Journey of Discovery Maha Fluid Power Research Center, Purdue University, USA, 2013. – 25 p.</reference></references><files><furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23085</furl><file>UBS10105.pdf</file></files><dates><dateReceived>27.11.2022.</dateReceived></dates></article><article><pages>97-122</pages><artType>RAR</artType><authors><author num="1"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Яковлев</surname><initials>Илья Андреевич</initials><orgName>ФГБОУ ВО Уфимский государственный авиационный технический университет</orgName><email>ilya-yakovlev-1999@bk.ru</email><address>Уфа</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Yakovlev</surname><initials>Ilya</initials><orgName>Ufa State Aviation Technical University</orgName><address>Ufa</address></individInfo></author><author num="2"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Елизарова</surname><initials>Анастасия Валерьевна</initials><orgName>ФГБОУ ВО Уфимский государственный авиационный технический университет</orgName><email>elizarovaanastasia@gmail.com</email><address>Уфа</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Elizarova</surname><initials>Anastasia</initials><orgName>Ufa State Aviation Technical University</orgName><address>Ufa</address></individInfo></author><author num="3"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Саитова</surname><initials>Гузель Асхатовна</initials><orgName>ФГБОУ ВО Уфимский государственный авиационный технический университет</orgName><email>saitova@bk.ru</email><address>Уфа</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Saitova</surname><initials>Guzel</initials><orgName>Ufa State Aviation Technical University</orgName><address>Ufa</address></individInfo></author></authors><artTitles><artTitle lang="RUS">Определение архитектуры нейронной сети в задаче прогнозирования состояния заряда аккумулятора</artTitle><artTitle lang="ENG">Determining the architecture of a neural network in the problem of estimating the state of the battery charge</artTitle></artTitles><abstracts><abstract lang="RUS">Рассматривается задача прогнозирования состояния заряда аккумулятора, на основе нейронных сетей. Были исследованы два типа рекуррентных нелинейных авторегрессионных нейронных сетей в задаче прогнозирования состояния заряда аккумулятора в процессе его использования. Основным критерием качества прогнозирования выступала среднеквадратичная ошибка. По результатам исследования была выбрана оптимальная структура нейронной сети.</abstract><abstract lang="ENG">The problem of estimating the state of charge of the battery, based on neural networks, is considered. Two types of recurrent nonlinear autoregressive neural networks were investigated in the problem of estimating the state of charge of a battery during its use. The main criterion for the quality of forecasting was the mean square error. According to the results of the study, the optimal structure of the neural network was chosen.</abstract></abstracts><text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text><codes><udk>681.5</udk><bbk>30.2-5-05</bbk><doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.101.6</doi></codes><keywords><kwdGroup lang="ANY"><keyword>химический источник тока</keyword><keyword>нейросетевое моделирование</keyword><keyword>литий-ионный аккумулятор</keyword><keyword>прогнозирование</keyword><keyword>уровень разряда аккумулятора</keyword><keyword>chemical current source</keyword><keyword>neural network modeling</keyword><keyword>lithium-ion battery</keyword><keyword>battery discharge level prediction</keyword></kwdGroup></keywords><references><reference>1. ГАЛУШКИН Н.Е., ГАЛУШКИНА Н.Н. Анализ эмпири-ческих зависимостей, описывающих разряд щелочных аккумуляторов // Электрохимическая энергетика. – 2005. – Т. 5, №1. – С. 43–50.</reference><reference>2. ГЕЙДАРОВ П.Ш. Сравнительный анализ результатов обучений нейронной сети с вычисленными весовыми зна-чениями и с генерацией весовых значений случайным об-разом // Автоматика и телемеханика. – 2020. – №7. – С. 56–78. Англ.: GEIDAROV P. Comparative analysis of the results of training a neural network with calculated weights and with random generation of the weights // Auto-mation and Remote Control. – 2020. – Vol. 81:7. – P. 1211–1229.</reference><reference>3. ЕРИН С. Литиевые аккумуляторы: от сырья до готовых химических источников тока // Технологии в электрон-ной промышленности. – 2014. – №3. – С. 70–73.</reference><reference>4. САИТОВА Г.А., ЕЛИЗАРОВА А.В. Нейросетевая мо-дель для оценки состояния заряженности литий-ионного аккумулятора // Перспективные информацион-ные технологии (ПИТ–2021) [Электронный ресурс]: тру-ды Международной научно-технической конференции / Под ред. С.А. Прохорова. – Электрон. текстовые и граф. дан.– Самара: Изд-во Самарского научного центра РАН, 2021. – С. 288–293.</reference><reference>5. ХАЙКИН С. Нейронные сети. Полный курс. Второе из-дание: перевод с англ. – М: Издательский дом «Виль-ямс», 2006. – 1104 с.</reference><reference>6. ЧУДИНОВ Е.А., ТКАЧУК С.А., ШИШКО В.С. Техноло-гические основы производства литий-ионного аккуму-лятора // Электрохимическая энергетика. – 2015. – Т. 15, №2. – С. 84–92.</reference><reference>7. CHANG W.Y. The state of charge estimating methods for battery: A review // International Scholarly Research Notices. – 2013. – Vol. 2013. – 8 p.</reference><reference>8. LI S. et al. State-of-charge estimation of lithium-ion batteries in the battery degradation process based on recurrent neu-ral network // Energies. – 2021. – Vol. 14, No. 2. – P. 306.</reference><reference>9. TANG X. et al. Li-ion battery parameter estimation for state of charge // IEEE American Control Conference (ACC-2011). – IEEE, 2011. – P. 941–946.</reference><reference>10. TIAN J. et al. Flexible battery state of health and state of charge estimation using partial charging data and deep learning // Energy Storage Materials. – 2022. – Vol. 51. – P. 372–381.</reference><reference>11. VIDAL C. et al. Machine learning applied to electrified ve-hicle battery state of charge and state of health estimation: State-of-the-art // IEEE Access. – 2020. – Vol. 8. – P. 52796–52814.</reference><reference>12. WANG K. et al. State of charge estimation of composite en-ergy storage systems with supercapacitors and lithium bat-teries // Complexity. – 2021. – Vol. 2021.</reference><reference>13. WANG L. et al. State of charge estimation for LiFePO4 bat-tery via dual extended kalman filter and charging voltage curve // Electrochimica Acta. – 2019. – Vol. 296. – P. 1009–1017.</reference><reference>14. WANG Q. et al. Power battery state of charge estimation based on extended Kalman filter // Journal of Renewable and Sustainable Energy. – 2019. – Vol. 11, No. 1. – P. 014302.</reference><reference>15. WANG Y., CHEN Z. A framework for state-of-charge and remaining discharge time prediction using unscented parti-cle filter // Applied Energy. – 2020. – Vol. 260. – P. 114324.</reference><reference>16. WEI Z. et al. Load current and state-of-charge coestimation for current sensor-free lithium-ion battery // IEEE Trans. on Power Electronics. – 2021. – Vol. 36, No. 10. – P. 10970–10975.</reference><reference>17. XI Z. et al. Learning of battery model bias for effective state of charge estimation of lithium-ion batteries // IEEE Trans. on Vehicular Technology. – 2019. – Vol. 68, No. 9. – P. 8613–8628.</reference><reference>18. XIA Z., QAHOUQ J.A. A. State-of-charge balancing of lith-ium-ion batteries with state-of-health awareness capability // IEEE Trans. on Industry Applications. – 2020. – Vol. 57, No. 1. – P. 673–684.</reference><reference>19. XIONG R. et al. A set membership theory based parameter and state of charge co-estimation method for all-climate bat-teries // Journal of Cleaner Production. – 2020. – Vol. 249. – P. 119380.</reference><reference>20. XIONG X. et al. A novel practical state of charge estimation method: an adaptive improved ampere‐hour method based on composite correction factor // Int. Journal of Energy Re-search. – 2020. – Vol. 44, No. 14. – P. 11385–11404.</reference><reference>21. XU Y. et al. Online identification of battery model parame-ters and joint state of charge and state of health estimation using dual particle filter algorithms // Int. Journal of Energy Research. – 2022. – Vol. 46, No. 14. – P. 19615–19652.</reference><reference>22. XUAN D.J. et al. Real-time estimation of state-of-charge in lithium-ion batteries using improved central difference trans-form method // Journal of Cleaner Production. – 2020. – Vol. 252. – P. 119787.</reference><reference>23. YANG B., WANG Y., ZHAN Y. Lithium Battery State-of-Charge Estimation Based on a Bayesian Optimization Bidi-rectional Long Short-Term Memory Neural Network // Ener-gies. – 2022. – Vol. 15, No. 13. – P. 4670.</reference><reference>24. YANG F. et al. State-of-charge estimation of lithium-ion bat-teries via long short-term memory network // IEEE Access. – 2019. – Vol. 7. – P. 53792–53799.</reference><reference>25. YANG F. et al. State-of-charge estimation of lithium-ion bat-teries using LSTM and UKF // Energy. – 2020. – Vol. 201. – P. 117664.</reference><reference>26. ZHANG K. et al. State of charge estimation for lithium bat-tery based on adaptively weighting cubature particle filter // IEEE Access. – 2019. – Vol. 7. – P. 166657–166666.</reference><reference>27. ZHANG R. et al. State of the art of lithium-ion battery SOC estimation for electrical vehicles // Energies. – 2018. – Vol. 11, No. 7. – P. 1820.</reference></references><files><furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23086</furl><file>UBS10106.pdf</file></files><dates><dateReceived>11.08.2022.</dateReceived></dates></article><section><secTitle lang="RUS">Управление подвижными объектами и навигация</secTitle></section><article><pages>123-139</pages><artType>RAR</artType><authors><author num="1"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Кокунько</surname><initials>Юлия Георгиевна</initials><orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName><email>juliakokunko@gmail.com</email><address>Москва</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Kokunko</surname><initials>Julia</initials><orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName><address>Moscow</address></individInfo></author></authors><artTitles><artTitle lang="RUS">Синтез генератора задающих воздействий для системы управления мобильным роботом</artTitle><artTitle lang="ENG">Design of a reference actions generator for a mobile robot control system</artTitle></artTitles><abstracts><abstract lang="RUS">При планировании пути следования автономного колесного робота возникают такие проблемы, как обеспечение безопасности движения, гладкости и ограниченности кривизны пути и скорости ее изменения с учетом проектных ограничений робота как механического объекта управления. Совместное решение этих проблем может привести к громоздким аналитическим расчетам, нереализуемым в реальном времени. В данной работе предлагается упростить и автоматизировать генерацию плоских путей для колесного робота, совмещающую решение указанных проблем. На первом этапе строится примитивный путь в виде плоской ломаной, отрезки которой соединяют опорные точки маршрута и обеспечивают безопасное выполнение рабочего сценария. На втором этапе решается проблема сглаживания сочленений ломаной без использования геометрических расчетов. Для этого предлагается использовать динамический генератор с использованием уравнений движения центра масс колесной платформы. При синтезе корректирующих воздействий генератора, имитирующих управляющие воздействия робота, используется метод декомпозиции и S-образные гладкие и ограниченные нелинейные обратные связи, что позволяет выполнить проектные ограничения робота на скорость, ускорение и управляющие моменты. Поэтому выходные переменные генератора, имитирующие координаты центра масс робота, будут порождать сглаженный естественным образом путь с допустимой кривизной при отслеживании координат опорного негладкого маршрута. Разработанные алгоритмы сглаживания не требуют сложных геометрических построений и специальных вычислительных ресурсов, их можно использовать и на этапе планирования, и в реальном времени на бортовом компьютере.</abstract><abstract lang="ENG">Planning the path of an autonomous wheeled robot can pose problems such as ensuring motion safety, smoothness and bounded curvature of the path and its rate of change, considering the design constraints of the robot as a mechanical control object. The joint solution of these problems can lead to cumbersome analytical calculations that are not realizable in real-time. In this paper, we propose to simplify and automate the generation of planar paths for a wheeled robot, which will solve both of these problems. At the first stage, a primitive path is constructed in the form of a flat polyline. The second stage solves the problem of smoothing the articulation of the polyline. Instead of geometric calculations, a dynamic generator is designed as a copy of the equations of motion of the robot. The synthesis of the generator's correcting actions, which simulate the robot's control actions, is based on the decomposition method and S-shaped smooth and constrained nonlinear feedbacks. This ensures that the design constraints of the robot on velocity, acceleration and control torques are met, and the output variables of the generator will generate a naturally smoothed path with acceptable curvature when tracking the coordinates of the reference nonsmooth trajectory.</abstract></abstracts><text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text><codes><udk>62.50</udk><bbk>32.817</bbk><doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.101.7</doi></codes><keywords><kwdGroup lang="ANY"><keyword>колесный робот</keyword><keyword>реализуемая траектория</keyword><keyword>динамический генератор</keyword><keyword>проектные ограничения</keyword><keyword>сигма-функция</keyword><keyword>wheeled robot</keyword><keyword>realizable trajectory</keyword><keyword>dynamic oscillator</keyword><keyword>design constraints</keyword><keyword>sigma function</keyword></kwdGroup></keywords><references><reference>1. АНТИПОВ А.С., КРАСНОВА С.А., УТКИН В.А. Синтез инвари-антных нелинейных одноканальных систем слежения с сигмои-дальными обратными связями с обеспечением заданной точности слежения // Автоматика и телемеханика. – 2022. – №1. – С. 40–66.</reference><reference>2. КОЧЕТКОВ С.А., УТКИН В.А. Метод декомпозиции в задачах управления мобильными роботами // Автоматика и телемехани-ка. – 2011. – №10. – С. 86–103.</reference><reference>3. КРАСНОВ Д.В., УТКИН А.В. Синтез многофункциональной си-стемы слежения в условиях неопределенности // Управление большими системами. – 2017. – Вып. 69. – С. 29–49.</reference><reference>4. КРАСНОВА С.А., УТКИН А.В. Анализ и синтез минимально-фазовых нелинейных SISO-систем при действии внешних несогла-сованных возмущений // Проблемы управления. – 2014. – №6. – С. 22–30.</reference><reference>5. ПЕСТЕРЕВ А.В. Синтез стабилизирующего управления в задаче следования колесного робота вдоль заданной кривой // Автомати-ка и телемеханика. – 2012. – №7. – С. 25–39.</reference><reference>6. ПЕСТЕРЕВ А.В., РАПОПОРТ Л.Б., ТКАЧЕВ С.Б. Каноническое представление нестационарной задачи путевой стабилизации // Известия РАН. Теория и системы управления. – 2015. – Т. 54, №4. – С. 160–176.</reference><reference>7. BAUTISTA G.D., PEREZ J., MILANÉS V., NASHASHIB F. A review of motion planning techniques for automated vehicles // IEEE T-ITS. – 17(4) – P. 1–11.</reference><reference>8. BELINSKAYA Y. Application of the covering method for trajectories design for car-like robot // Proc. of the 14th Int. Conf. Management of Large-Scale System Development (MLSD–2021), 27–29 September 2021, Moscow, Russia.</reference><reference>9. BELINSKAYA YU.S., CHETVERIKOV V.N. Covering method for point-to-point control of constrained flat system // IFAC-Papers OnLine. – 2015. – Vol. 48(11). – P. 924–929.</reference><reference>10. BUSURIN V.I., YIN NAING WIN Microoptoelectromechanical ring angular velocity transducer based on the optical tunnel effect for control system of mobile objects // J Phys: Conf Ser. – 1333:052002.</reference><reference>11. FAROUKI R.T. Pythagorean Hodograph Curves. – Springer, 2008.</reference><reference>12. KANO H., FUJIOKA H. B-Spline trajectory planning with curvature constraint // Proc. Annual American Control Conference (ACC). – 2018. – P. 1963–1968.</reference><reference>13. KOCHETKOV S.A. Mobile robot trajectory control under influence of unknown perturbation // Mathematics in Engineering, Science and Aerospace. – 2019. – No. 10(4). – P. 725–732.</reference><reference>14. KOKUNKO YU., KRASNOVA S. Synthesis of a tracking system with restrictions on UAV state variables // Mathematics in Engineering, Science and Aerospace. – 2019. – No. 10(4). – P. 695–705.</reference><reference>15. LAVALLE S.M. Planning algorithms. – Cambridge University Press, 2006.</reference><reference>16. MERCY T., VAN PARYS R., PIPELEERS G. Spline-based motion planning for autonomous guided vehicles in a dynamic environment // IEEE TCST. – 2017. – Vol. 26(6). – P. 2182 –2189.</reference><reference>17. MINGUEZ J., LAMIRAUX F., LAUMOND J.P. Motion planning and obstacle avoidance // In: Springer Handbook of Robotics, Springer In-ternational Publishing. – 2008. – P. 1177–1202.</reference><reference>18. SAKCSAK B., BASCETTA L., FERRETTI G., PRANDINI M. Sam-pling-based optimal kinodinamic planning with motion primitives // Autonomous Robots. – 2019. – Vol. 43(7). – P. 1715–1732.</reference><reference>19. SAMSON C. Control of chained systems. Application to path follow-ing and time varying point – stabilization of mobile robots // IEEE Trans Automat Control. – 1995. – Vol. 40(1). – P. 64–77.</reference><reference>20. WEBB D.J., VAN DER BERG J. Kinodynamic RRT*: asymptotically optimal motion planning for robots with linear // Proc. of the IEEE Int. Conf. on Robotics and Automation – 2013 (ICRA–2013), May 6–10, 2013, Karlsruhe, Germany. – P. 5039–5046.</reference><reference>21. ZHOU CH., HUANG B., FRÄNTI P. A review of motion planning al-gorithms for intelligent robots // Journal of Intelligent Manufacturing. – 2022. – No. 33. – P. 387–424.</reference></references><files><furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23087</furl><file>UBS10107.pdf</file></files><dates><dateReceived>30.11.2022.</dateReceived></dates></article><section><secTitle lang="RUS">Технические и программные средства управления</secTitle></section><article><pages>140-157</pages><artType>RAR</artType><authors><author num="1"><individInfo lang="RUS"><surname>Тутуров</surname><initials>Алексей Александрович</initials><orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName><email>tuturov@mail.ru</email><address>Москва</address></individInfo><individInfo lang="ENG"><surname>Tuturov</surname><initials>Aleksey</initials><orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName><address>Moscow</address></individInfo></author></authors><artTitles><artTitle lang="RUS">Графический интерфейс системы поддержки принятия решений для управления космическим аппаратом</artTitle><artTitle lang="ENG">Development of a project of a graphic interface as an element of a decision support system for the duty shift of space vehicle control</artTitle></artTitles><abstracts><abstract lang="RUS">Описаны специфика работы специалистов дежурной смены и роль отображения информации о процессах, протекающих в космическом комплексе, на принятие решений по управлению космическими аппаратами в составе орбитальной группировки дистанционного зондирования Земли. Поставлена задача разработки графического интерфейса как элемента системы поддержки принятия решений для дежурной смены управления космическими аппаратами, состоящей из специалистов предприятий космического комплекса. Предложены принципы разделения служебной информации, которой оперируют специалисты дежурной смены, по категориям на основе природы её источников, а также механизм отображения данной информации в режиме реального времени с помощью графического интерфейса с целью уменьшить затраты времени на идентификацию ситуации нештатного функционирования наземного и/или бортового программно-технического обеспечения в условиях ограниченного времени проведения сеанса связи с космическим аппаратом. Ключевой особенностью предложенного графического интерфейса является «вектор состояния космического аппарата» – способ отображения данных телеметрии элементов подсистем космического аппарата, необходимых для регистрации нештатной ситуации на борту космического аппарата, и поиска стратегии купирования/ликвидации последствий обеспечения её функциональной устойчивости как способности сохранять и/или восстанавливать возложенные на неё функции.</abstract><abstract lang="ENG">The specifics of the work of duty shift specialists and the role of means of displaying information about the processes occurring in the space complex on decision-making on the control of spacecraft as part of the Earth's remote sensing orbital constellation are described. The task was set to develop a graphical interface project as an element of a decision support system for the on-duty shift of spacecraft control, consisting of specialists from space complex enterprises. The principles of separating service information, which are operated by shift shift specialists, into categories based on the nature of its sources, as well as a mechanism for displaying this information in real time using a graphical interface, in order to reduce the time spent on identifying the situation of abnormal operation of the ground and/or on-board software and hardware in the conditions of a limited time of a communication session with the spacecraft. The key feature of the proposed graphical interface is the "spacecraft state vector" - a method for displaying telemetry data of the elements of the spacecraft subsystems necessary to register an emergency situation on board the spacecraft and search for a strategy to stop / eliminate its consequences by ensuring functional stability - the ability of the system to save and / or restore the functions assigned to it.</abstract></abstracts><text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text><codes><udk>629.78 + 004.5 + 007.5</udk><bbk>32.81</bbk><doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.101.8</doi></codes><keywords><kwdGroup lang="ANY"><keyword>космический аппарат</keyword><keyword>космический комплекс</keyword><keyword>нештатная ситуация</keyword><keyword>диагностика</keyword><keyword>система поддержки принятия решений</keyword><keyword>интерфейс</keyword><keyword>spacecraft</keyword><keyword>space complex</keyword><keyword>emergency situation</keyword><keyword>diagnostics</keyword><keyword>decision support system</keyword><keyword>interface</keyword></kwdGroup></keywords><references><reference>1. АБРАМОВ Н.С., ТАЛАЛАЕВ А.А., ФРАЛЕНКО В.П. Интеллектуальный анализ телеметрической информа-ции для диагностики оборудования космического аппа-рата // Информационные технологии и вычислительные системы. – 2016. – №1. – С. 64–75.</reference><reference>2. ГОНЧАРОВ А.К., ЧЕРНОВ А.А. Планирование сеансов приёма информации с космических аппаратов орби-тальной группировки при ограниченном количестве при-ёмных комплексов // Космонавтика и ракетостроение. – 2014. – №1. – С. 180–189.</reference><reference>3. КОРОЛЕВ А.Н. Функциональная устойчивость навига-ционно-информационных систем // Известия высших учебных заведений. Приборостроение. – 2018. – Т. 61, №7. – С. 559–565.</reference><reference>4. КОТЯШОВ Е.В., КУВАЕВ О.Л., КУДИНОВ М.Г., ЧЕР-НЯВСКИЙ В.А. Информационно-расчетная модель пла-нирования применения орбитальных группировок косми-ческих аппаратов // Труды Военно-космической акаде-мии им. А.Ф. Можайского. – 2017. – №657. – С. 15–22.</reference><reference>5. YURKEVITCH E.V., STEPANOVSKAYA I.A. Controlling the security of the airport airspace using the digital twin // Journal of Physics: Conference Series. – London: Institute of Physics and IOP Publishing Limited. – 2021. – Vol.1864. –P. 012128 (1–6).</reference><reference>6. YURKEVITCH E.V., STEPANOVSKAYA I.A., KRYU-KOVA L.N. Mechanisms of information support for the digi-tal transformation of space complexes based on the concept of socio-cyber-physical self-organization // Lecture Notes in Networks and Systems. – Cham: Springer. – 2022. – Vol. 330. – P. 629-637.</reference><reference>7. YURKEVITCH E.V., KRYUKOVA L.N. Model design as a new socio-cyber-physical systems creating mechanism // Journal of Physics: Conference Series. – London: IOP Pub-lishing Limited. – 2021. – Vol. 1864. – P. 012089 (1–6).</reference></references><files><furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23088</furl><file>UBS10108.pdf</file></files><dates><dateReceived>05.12.2022.</dateReceived></dates></article></articles></issue></journal>
