<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<journal>
  <operCard>
    <operator>ИПУ РАН|Губко М.В.</operator>
    <date>2023-06-22 12:37:21</date>
    <cntArticle>6</cntArticle>
  </operCard>
  <issn>1819-2440</issn>
  <eissn>1819-2467</eissn>
  <titleid>10618</titleid>
  <journalInfo lang="RUS">
    <title>Управление большими системами</title>
    <abbrTitle>УБС</abbrTitle>
    <publ>Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</publ>
    <placePubl>Москва</placePubl>
    <address>117997, г. Москва, ул. Профсоюзная, д. 65.</address>
  </journalInfo>
  <journalInfo lang="ENG">
    <title>Large-scale Systems Control</title>
    <abbrTitle>LSSC</abbrTitle>
  </journalInfo>
  <issue>
    <number>102</number>
    <dateUni>202303</dateUni>
    <pages>1–113</pages>
    <articles>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Системный анализ</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>5-14</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Щеголев</surname>
              <initials>Александр Алексеевич</initials>
              <orgName>Национальный исследовательский университет "Высшая~школа экономики"</orgName>
              <email>ashchegolev@hse.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Shchegolev</surname>
              <initials>Aleksandr</initials>
              <orgName>HSE University</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">О центральной предельной теореме для однородных нелинейных цепей Маркова в дискретном времени</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">On the central limit theorem for homogeneous discrete-time nonlinear markov chains</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Класс нелинейных марковских процессов характеризуется наличием зависимости текущего состояния процесса от текущего распределения процесса в дополнение к зависимости от предыдущего состояния процесса. Благодаря этой особенности данные процессы характеризуются сложным предельным поведением и эргодическими свойствами, для которых привычных критериев для марковских процессов недостаточно. Будучи разновидностью нелинейных марковских процессов, нелинейные цепи Маркова унаследовали эти особенности. В~работе исследованы условия для выполнения центральной предельной теоремы для однородных нелинейных цепей Маркова в дискретном времени с~конечным дискретным фазовым пространством. Также приведен краткий обзор известных результатов об эргодических свойствах нелинейных цепей Маркова. Полученный результат дополняет существующие результаты в данной области и может быть полезен для дальнейших приложений в статистике.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">The class of nonlinear Markov processes is characterized by the dependence of the current state of the process on its current distribution in addition to the dependence on the previous state. Due to this feature, these processes are characterized by complex limit behavior and ergodic properties, for which the usual criteria for Markov processes are not sufficient. Being a subclass of nonlinear Markov processes, nonlinear Markov chains have inherited these features. In this paper, conditions for the fulfillment of the central limit theorem for homogeneous nonlinear Markov chains in discrete time and with a discrete finite state space are studied. Also, a brief review of known results on the ergodic properties of nonlinear Markov chains is included. The obtained result complements the existing results in this area and may be useful for further applications in statistics.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>519.2</udk>
          <bbk>22.171</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.102.1</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>нелинейные марковские цепи центральная предельная теорема</keyword>
            <keyword>экспоненциальная скорость сходимости</keyword>
            <keyword>nonlinear Markov chains</keyword>
            <keyword>central limit theorem</keyword>
            <keyword>exponential rate of convergence</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>БУТКОВСКИЙ О.А. Об эргодических свойствах нелиней-ных марковских цепей и стохастических уравнений Мак-кина–Власова // Теория вероятностей и ее применения. –2013. –Т. 58, №4. – С. 782–794.</reference>
          <reference>ВЛАСОВ А.А. О вибрационных свойствах электронного га-за // Журнал экспериментальной и теоретической физики. –1938. –Т. 8, №3. – С. 291–318.</reference>
          <reference>ИБРАГИМОВ И.А., ЛИННИК Ю.В. Независимые и стаци-онарно связанные величины. — М.: Изд-во «Наукa», Гл. ред.физ.-мат. лит-ры, 1965.</reference>
          <reference>ЩЕГОЛЕВ А.А. Об оценках скорости сходимости одно-родных нелинейных цепей Маркова в дискретном време-ни // Управление большими системами. – 2021. – Вып. 90. –С. 36–48.</reference>
          <reference>KOLOKOLTSOV V.N. Nonlinear Markov processes andkinetic equations // Cambridge Tracts in Mathematics. –Cambridge University Press, Cambridge – 2010. – Vol. 182.</reference>
          <reference>MCKEAN H.P. A class of Markov processes associated withnonlinear parabolic equations // Proc. of the National Academyof Sciences of the United States of America. – 1966. – Vol. 56. –P. 1907–1911.</reference>
          <reference>MUZYCHKA S.A., VANINSKY K.L. A class of nonlinearrandom walks related to the Ornstein–Uhlenbeck process //Markov Process. Related Fields. – 2011. – Vol. 17, No. 2. –P. 277–304.</reference>
          <reference>NEUMANN B. Nonlinear Markov chains with finite statespace: Invariant distributions and long-term behaviour //Journal of Applied Probability. – 2022. – P. 1–15.</reference>
          <reference>SABUROV M. Ergodicity of nonlinear Markov operators onthe finite dimensional space // Nonlinear Analysis: Theory,Methods &amp; Applications. – 2015. – Vol. 143. – P. 105–119.</reference>
          <reference>SHCHEGOLEV A.A. A new rate of convergence estimatefor homogeneous discrete-time nonlinear Markov chains //Random Operators and Stochastic Equations. – 2022. – Vol. 30,No. 3. – P. 205–213.</reference>
          <reference>SZNITMAN A.-S. Topics in propagation of chaos // ´Ecoled’ ´ Eté de Probabilités de Saint-Flour XIX.—1989. – LectureNotes in Math. – 1991. – Vol. 1464. – P. 165–251.</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23091</furl>
          <file>UBS10201.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived> 23.12.2022.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Математическая теория управления</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>15-43</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Зверкина</surname>
              <initials>Галина Александровна</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>zverkina@gmail.com</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Zverkina</surname>
              <initials>Galina</initials>
              <orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Неравенство лордена и скорость сходимости распределения одной обобщённой системы массового обслуживания эрланга – севастьянова</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Lorden's inequality and the rate of convergence of the distribution of one generalized erlang -- sevast'yanov queuing system</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Во многих прикладных задачах теории надежности и массового обслуживания очень важно не только доказывать существование стационарного распределения, но и уметь оценивать скорость сходимости распределения к  стационарному. Стандартные методы получения таких оценок предполагают, что времена обслуживания (ремонта или работы) экспонециальны, входящий поток -- пуассоновский и все формирующие процесс обслуживания (надёжности) случайные величины (сл.в.) независимы. Результаты для таких простейших случаев хорошо известны. Отказ от предположений независимости и экспоненциальности этих сл.в. приводит к довольно сложным случайным процессам, которые очень трудно изучать с помощью стандартных процедур. Для таких процессов нужно использовать более сложную технику. Для этого потребуется некоторое обобщение (и доказательство) ряда известных результатов. Один из таких результатов -- обобщённое неравенство Лордена, используемое в данной статье. "Классическое" неравенство Лордена касается "классических" процессов восстановления. В работе используется обобщение этого неравенства для случая "слабо зависимых" и имеющих в некотором смысле "близкие" распределения интервалов между моментами восстановления. Такое обобщение позволяет изучать скорость сходимости для широкого класса сложных процессов в ТМО и в смежных дисциплинах. В данной работе изучается одна обобщённая система массового обслуживания Эрланга -- Севастьянова.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">It is more important to estimate the rate of convergence to a stationary distribution rather than only to prove the existence one in many applied problems of reliability and queuing theory. This can be done via standard methods, but only under assumptions about an exponential distribution of service time, independent intervals between recovery times, etc. Results for such simplest cases are well-known. Rejection of these assumptions results to rather complex stochastic processes that cannot be studied using standard algorithms. A more sophisticated approach is needed for such processes. That requires generalizations and proofs of some classical results for a more general case. One of them is the generalized Lorden's inequality proved in this paper. We propose the generalized version of this inequality for the case of dependent and arbitrarily distributed intervals between recovery times. This generalization allows to find upper bounds for the rate of convergence for a wide class of complicated processes arising in the theory of reliability. The rate of convergence for a two-component process has been obtained via the generalized Lorden's inequality  in this paper.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>519.21</udk>
          <bbk>22.171</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.102.2</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>регенерирующие марковские процессы</keyword>
            <keyword>метод склеивания</keyword>
            <keyword>метрика полной вариации</keyword>
            <keyword>обобщённая система Эрланга -- Севастьянова</keyword>
            <keyword>скорость сходимости</keyword>
            <keyword>regenerative Markov processes</keyword>
            <keyword>coupling method</keyword>
            <keyword>total variation metric</keyword>
            <keyword>generalized Erlang-Sevastyanov system</keyword>
            <keyword>rate of convergence</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>АНИЧКИН С.А. Склеивание процессов восстановления иего применение // Проблемы устойчивости стохастическихмоделей. Труды семинара. – 1984. – М.: ВНИИСИ. –C. 4–24.</reference>
          <reference>БОРИСОВ И.С. Методы одного вероятностного про-странства для марковских процессов // Тр. Ин-та матема-тики. – 1982. – Т. 1. – С. 4–18.</reference>
          <reference>БОРОВКОВ А.А. Обобщенные процессы восстановления. –М.: Российская академия наук, 2020. – 453 с.</reference>
          <reference>СЕВАСТЬЯНОВ Б.А. Формулы Эрланга в телефонии припроизвольном законе распределения длительности разгово-ра // Труды Третьего Всесоюзного математического съезда,Москва, июнь–июль 1956. – 1959. –Т. 4. – М.: Изд-во АНСССР. – C. 121–135.</reference>
          <reference>СЕВАСТЬЯНОВ Б.А. Эргодическая теорема для марков-ских процессов и ее приложение к телефонным системамс отказами // Теория вероятн. и ее примен. – 1957. – Т. 2,вып. 1. – С. 106–116.</reference>
          <reference>ШЕЛЕПОВА А.Д., САХАНЕНКО А.И. Об асимптотике ве-роятности невыхода неоднородного обобщенного процессавосстановления за невозрастающую границу // Сиб. элек-трон. матем. изв. – 2021. – Т. 18:2. – С. 1667—1688.</reference>
          <reference>AFANASYEVA L.G., TKACHENKO A.V. On theConvergence Rate for Queueing and Reliability ModelsDescribed by Regenerative Processes // Journal ofMathematical Sciences. – October 2016. – Vol. 218, Issue 2. –P. 119–36.</reference>
          <reference>ASMUSSEN S. Applied probability and queues. – Springer,New York, 2003.</reference>
          <reference>CHANG J. T. Inequalities for the Overshoot // The Annals ofApplied Probability. – 1994. – Vol. 4(4). – P. 1223.</reference>
          <reference>DOEBLIN W. Exposé de la théorie des cha ˆ ines simplesconstantes de Markov à un nombre fini d’états // Rev. Math.de l’Union Interbalkanique. – 1938. – Vol.2. – P. 77–105.</reference>
          <reference>ERLANG A. K. Solution of some problems in the theory ofprobabilities of significance in automatic telephone exchanges //Elektroteknikeren. – 1917. – Vol. 13 – P. 5–13 (in Danish);Engl. transl.: P.O. Elect. Eng. Journal. – 1918. – Vol. 10. –P. 189–197; Reprinted as: WEB-based edition bypermission from the Danish Acad. Techn. Sci. athttp://oldwww.com.dtu.dk/teletraffic/Erlang.html.</reference>
          <reference>FERREIRA M.A., ANDRADE M. The M|G|∞ queuebusy period distribution exponentiality // Journal of appliedmathematics. – 2011. – Vol. 4, No. 3. – P. 249–260.</reference>
          <reference>FORTET R. Calcul des probabilités. – CNRS, Paris, 1950.</reference>
          <reference>GRIFFEATH D. A maximal coupling for Markov chains // undZeitschrift für Wahrscheinlichkeitstheorie Verwandte Gebiete. –1975. – Vol. 31, Iss. 2. – P. 95–106.</reference>
          <reference>KALASHNIKOV V.V. Mathematical Methods in QueuingTheory. – Kluwer Academic Publishers, Amsterdam, 1994.</reference>
          <reference>KALIMULINA E., ZVERKINA G. On some generalization ofLorden’s inequality for renewal processes // arXiv.org. Cornell:Cornell university library. – 2019. – 1910.03381v1. – P. 1–5.</reference>
          <reference>KATO K. Coupling Lemma and Its Application to TheSecurity Analysis of Quantum Key Distribution // TamagawaUniversity Quantum ICT Research Institute Bulletin. – 2014. –Vol.4, No.1, – P. 23-30.</reference>
          <reference>LORDEN G. On Excess over the Boundary // The Annals ofMathematical Statistics. – 1970. – Vol. 41(2). – P. 520–527.</reference>
          <reference>PECHINKIN A.V. On an invariant queueing system // Math.Operationsforsch. Statist. Ser. Optim. – 1983. – Vol. 14(3). –P. 433–444.</reference>
          <reference>PECHINKIN A.V., SOLOVYEV A.D., YASHKOV S.F. Asystem with servicing discipline whereby the order of minimumremaining length is serviced first // Eng. Cybern. – 1979. –Vol. 17(5). – P. 38–45.</reference>
          <reference>SMITH W. L. Renewal theory and its ramifications // J. Roy.Statist. Soc. – 1958. – Ser. B, Vol. 20:2. – P. 243–302.</reference>
          <reference>STADJE W. The busy period of the queueing system M|G|∞ //Journal of Applied Probability. – 1985. – Vol. 22. – P. 697–704.</reference>
          <reference>STOYAN D. Qualitative Eigenschaften und Abschtzungenstochastischer Modelle. – Berlin, 1977.</reference>
          <reference>TAK ´ ACS L. Introduction to the Theory of Queues. – OxfordUniversity Press, 1962.</reference>
          <reference>VAN DOORN E.A., ZEIFMAN A.I. On the speed ofconvergence to stationarity of the Erlang loss system //Queueing Systems. – 2009. – Vol. 63. – P. 241–252.</reference>
          <reference>VERETENNIKOV A.YU. On rate of convergence to thestationary distribution in queueing systems with one servingdevice // Automation and Remote Control. – Vol. 74, Iss. 10. –P. 1620–1629. (2013).</reference>
          <reference>VERETENNIKOV A.YU. On the rate of mixing andconvergence to a stationary distribution in Erlang-type systemsin continuous time // Problems Inf. Transmiss. –2010. – Vol.46(4). – P. 382–389.</reference>
          <reference>VERETENNIKOV A.YU. The ergodicity of service systemswith an infinite number of servomechanisms // Математиче-ские заметки. – 1977. – Vol. 22(4). – P. 804–808.</reference>
          <reference>VERETENNIKOV A., BUTKOVSKY O. A. On asymptoticsfor Vaserstein coupling of Markov chains // Stochastic Processesand their Applications. – 2013. – Vol. 123(9). – P. 3518–3541.</reference>
          <reference>VERETENNIKOV A.YU., ZVERKINA G.A. Simple proof ofDynkin’s formula for single-server systems and polynomialconvergence rates // Markov Proc. Rel. Fileds. – 2014. –Vol. 20, Iss. 3. – P. 479–504; arXiv:1306.2359 [math.PR](2013).</reference>
          <reference>ZVERKINA G. On strong bounds of rate of convergence forregenerative processes // Communications in Computer andInformation Science. – 2016. – Vol. 678. – P. 381–393.</reference>
          <reference>ZVERKINA G. Lorden’s inequality and coupling methodfor backward renewal process // Proc. of XX Int. Conf. onDistributed Computer and Communication Networks: Control,Computation, Communications (DCCN-2017, Moscow),2017. – P. 484–491.</reference>
          <reference>ZVERKINA G. On strong bounds of rate of convergence forregenerative processes // Communications in Computer andInformation Science – 2016. – Vol. 678. – P. 381–393.</reference>
          <reference>ZVERKINA G. About some extended Erlang-Sevast’yanovqueueing system and its convergence rate (English and Russianversions) // https:∖∖arxiv.org/abs/1805.04915; Фундаменталь-ная и прикладная математика. – 2018. – No. 22, Iss. 3. –P. 57–82.</reference>
          <reference>ZVERKINA G., KALIMULINA E. On generalized intensityfunction and its application to the backward renewal timeestimation for renewal processes // Proc. of the 5th Int. Conf.on Stochastic Methods (ICSM-5, 2020). – 2020. – М.: Изд-воРУДН. – P. 306–310.</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23092</furl>
          <file>UBS10202.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>14.11.2022</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Анализ и синтез систем управления</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>44-57</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Фуртат</surname>
              <initials>Игорь Борисович</initials>
              <orgName>Институт проблем машиноведения РАН</orgName>
              <email>cainenash@mail.ru</email>
              <address>Санкт-Петербург</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Furtat</surname>
              <initials>Igor</initials>
              <orgName>Institute of Problems of Mechanical Engineering RAS</orgName>
              <address>St.Peterburg</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Гущин</surname>
              <initials>Павел Александрович</initials>
              <orgName>Институт проблем машиноведения РАН</orgName>
              <email>guschin.p@mail.ru</email>
              <address>Санкт-Петербург</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Gushchin</surname>
              <initials>Pavel</initials>
              <orgName>Institute of Problems of Mechanical Engineering RAS</orgName>
              <address>St.Peterburg</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="3">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Нгуен</surname>
              <initials>Ба Хю</initials>
              <orgName>Институт проблем машиноведения РАН</orgName>
              <email>leningrat206@gmail.com</email>
              <address>Санкт-Петербург</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <initials>Ba Huy</initials>
              <orgName>Institute of Problems of Mechanical Engineering RAS</orgName>
              <address>St.Peterburg</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="4">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Колесник</surname>
              <initials>Никита Сергеевич</initials>
              <orgName>Институт проблем машиноведения РАН</orgName>
              <email>nik.kolesnik.1998@mail.ru</email>
              <address>Санкт-Петербург</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Kolesnik</surname>
              <initials>Nikita</initials>
              <orgName>Institute of Problems of Mechanical Engineering RAS</orgName>
              <address>St.Peterburg</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Адаптивное управление с гарантией заданного качества регулирования</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Adaptive control with a guarantee of a given performance</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Приведена модификация классического алгоритма адаптивного управления по выходу с целью гарантии нахождения выходного сигнала в заданном разработчиком множестве в любой момент времени. В отличие от классических схем адаптивного управления, где нельзя повлиять на качество переходного процесса, качество регулирования в установившемся режиме и время переходного процесса, здесь для решения данных проблем предлагается дополнить классическую процедуру адаптивного управления нелинейным законом управления. Нелинейный закон управления базируется на взаимообратном преобразовании выходной переменной так, чтобы задача с ограничениями свелась к задаче без ограничений. Для преобразованной системы без ограничений можно применять любые существующие схемы адаптивного управления для ее стабилизации. Причем в новых координатах не требуется гарантировать заданное качество переходных процессов в любой момент времени и не важна величина предельной ошибки. Это связано с тем, что обратные преобразования всегда будут гарантировать нахождение исходных сигналов в заданных разработчиком ограничениях. Решена задача для объектов с единичной относительной степенью дабы избежать громоздких выводов. Однако все полученные результаты могут быть непосредственно распространены на объекты с произвольной относительной степенью. Приведен пример, иллюстрирующий эффективность предложенного метода и подтверждающий теоретические выводы.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">The paper presents a modification of the classical output adaptive control algorithm in order to guarantee that the output signal belongs to a given set specified by the developer at any time. Unlike classical adaptive control schemes, where it is impossible to influence control performances, including transient and steady-state performance, it is proposed here to supplement the classical adaptive control procedure with a nonlinear control law to solve these problems. The nonlinear control law is based on the special coordinate transformation of the output variable so that the problem with constraints is reduced to the problem without constraints. For a transformed system without constraints, any existing adaptive control schemes can be applied to stabilize it. Moreover, in new coordinates, it is not required to guarantee the specified performance of transient processes at any time, and the value of the marginal error is not important. This is due to the fact that inverse transformations will always guarantee that the original signals are within the limits specified by the developer. The problem for plants with a relative degree one is solved in order to avoid cumbersome conclusions. However, all the results obtained can be directly extended to plants with an arbitrary relative degree. An example is given that illustrates the effectiveness of the proposed method and confirms the theoretical conclusions.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>519.7</udk>
          <bbk>Ж 50</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.102.3</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>динамическая система</keyword>
            <keyword>адаптивное управление</keyword>
            <keyword>нелинейное управление</keyword>
            <keyword>замена координат</keyword>
            <keyword>устойчивость</keyword>
            <keyword>управление</keyword>
            <keyword>dynamical system</keyword>
            <keyword>change of coordinates</keyword>
            <keyword>stability</keyword>
            <keyword>control</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>ЕРЕМИН Е.Л. Алгоритм адаптивной системы управле-ния с явно-эталонной моделью для строго мниимально-фазового объекта // Информатика и системы управления. –2004. – №2, Т. 8. – С. 157–166.</reference>
          <reference>МИРОШНИК И.В., НИКИФОРОВ В.О., ФРАДКОВ А.Л.Нелинейное и адаптивное управление сложными динами-ческими системами. – СПб.: Наука, 2000.</reference>
          <reference>ФРАДКОВ А.Л. Кибернетическая физика: принципы и при-меры. – СПб.: Наука, 2003.</reference>
          <reference>ФУРТАТ И.Б., ГУЩИН П.А. Управление динамическимиобъектами с гарантией нахождения регулируемого сигна-ла в заданном множестве // Автоматика и телемеханика. –2021. – №4. – С. 121–139.</reference>
          <reference>ХАЛИЛ Х.К. Нелинейные системы. – М.-Ижевск: НИЦ «Ре-гулярная и хаотическая динамика», Институт компьютер-ных исследований, 2009.</reference>
          <reference>ANDERSON B.D.O. Adaptive systems, lack of persistency ofexcitation and bursting phenomena // Automatica. – 1985. –Vol. 21, No. 3. – P. 247–258.</reference>
          <reference>ANNASWAMY A.M., SKANTZE F.P., LOH A.-P. Adaptivecontrol of continuous time systems with convex/concaveparametrization // Automatica. – 1998. – Vol. 34, No. 1. –P. 33–49.</reference>
          <reference>ARSLAN G., BASAR T. Disturbance attenuating controllerdesign for strict-feedback systems with structurally unknowndynamics // Automatica. – 2001. – Vol. 37, No. 8. –P. 1175–1188.</reference>
          <reference>CAMPION G., BASTIN G. Analysis of an adaptive controllerfor manipulators: Robustness versus flexibility // Systems &amp;Control Letters. – 1989. – Vol. 12, No. 3. – P. 251–258.</reference>
          <reference>CHOPRA N., SPONG M.W. Output Synchronization ofNonlinear Systems with Relative Degree One // RecentAdvances in Learning and Control. – Springer, London, 2008. –Vol. 371. – P. 51–64.</reference>
          <reference>FARZA M., M’SAAD M., MAATOUG T., KAMOUN M.Adaptive observers for nonlinearly parameterized class ofnonlinear systems // Automatica. – 2009. – Vol. 45, No. 10. –P. 2292–2299.</reference>
          <reference>FURTAT I.B. Robust Synchronization of the StructuralUncertainty Nonlinear Network with Delay and Disturbances //IFAC Proc. Volumes (IFAC-PapersOnline), 11th IFAC Int.Workshop on Adaptation and Learning in Control and SignalProcessing, ALCOSP–2013. – 2013. – P. 227–232.</reference>
          <reference>FURTAT I., GUSHCHIN P. Nonlinear feedback controlproviding plant output in given set // Int. Journal of Control. –2021. – DOI: https://doi.org/10.1080/00207179.2020.1861336.</reference>
          <reference>GOODWIN G.C., MAYNE D.Q. A parameter estimationperspective of continuous time model reference adaptivecontrol // Automatica. – 1987. – Vol. 23, No. 1. – P. 57–70.</reference>
          <reference>HASHIM Z.S., IBRAHEEM I.K. A relative degree onemodified active disturbance rejection control for four-tanklevel control system // Int. Review of Applied Sciences andEngineering. – 2021. – No. 2, Vol. 8. – P. 157–166.</reference>
          <reference>IOANNOU P.A., SUN J. Robust Adaptive Control. – CourierCorporation, 2012.</reference>
          <reference>NARENDRA K.S., ANNASWAMY A.M. Stable AdaptiveSystems. – Courier Corporation, 2012.</reference>
          <reference>POLYCARPOU M.M., IOANNOU P.A. A robust adaptivenonlinear control design // Automatica. – 1996. – Vol. 32,No. 3. – P. 423–427.</reference>
          <reference>RIFAI K.E., YOUCEF-TOUMI K. Robust Adaptive Control ofSwithched system. – InTech, Switched Systems, 2009.</reference>
          <reference>TAO G. Multivariable adaptive control: A survey //Automatica. – 2014. –Vol. 50, No. 11. – P.2737–2764.</reference>
          <reference>ZHAO G., CHEN G., MI J. Overcoming a FundamentalLimitation of Linear Systems with Generalized First OrderReset Element // Proc. of the 37th Chinese Control Conference(CCC). – 2018. – DOI: 10.23919/ChiCC.2018.8483381.</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23093</furl>
          <file>UBS10203.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived> 06.12.2022.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <article>
        <pages>58-75</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Фуртат</surname>
              <initials>Игорь Борисович</initials>
              <orgName>Институт проблем машиноведения РАН</orgName>
              <email>cainenash@mail.ru</email>
              <address>Санкт-Петербург</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Furtat</surname>
              <initials>Igor</initials>
              <orgName>Institute of Problems of Mechanical Engineering RAS</orgName>
              <address>St.Peterburg</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Гущин</surname>
              <initials>Павел Александрович</initials>
              <orgName>Институт проблем машиноведения РАН</orgName>
              <email>guschin.p@mail.ru</email>
              <address>Санкт-Петербург</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Gushchin</surname>
              <initials>Pavel</initials>
              <orgName>Institute of Problems of Mechanical Engineering RAS</orgName>
              <address>St.Peterburg</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="3">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Копысова</surname>
              <initials>Есения Алексеевна</initials>
              <orgName>Институт проблем машиноведения РАН</orgName>
              <email>esyako@ya.ru</email>
              <address>Санкт-Петербург</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Kopisova</surname>
              <initials>Esenia</initials>
              <orgName>Institute of Problems of Mechanical Engineering RAS</orgName>
              <address>St.Peterburg</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Нелинейные законы управления, построенные на базе линейных с использованием нечетных функций</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Nonlinear control laws based on linear ones using odd functions</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Исследуются нелинейные законы управления, полученные из линейного путем двух типов замен с использованием нечетных функций. Первая замена состоит в пропускании каждой компоненты вектора состояния через нелинейную функцию,  вторая замена -- в пропускании всего линейного закона управления через нелинейную функцию. Для исследования таких систем предлагается представить нелинейные функции в виде линейных с нелинейным угловым коэффициентом. Такое представление позволит использовать аппарат линейных матричных неравенств (ЛМН) для исследования устойчивости замкнутых систем. Найдены области устойчивости и области для начальных условий, полученные в результате многошаговой процедуры поиска решений с использованием ЛМН. Показано, что использование предложенных нелинейных законов управления позволяет уменьшить установившуюся ошибку по сравнению с линейным. Приведены многочисленные моделирования, иллюстрирующие теоретические выводы.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">The paper investigates nonlinear control laws obtained from linear one by two types of coordinate change by using odd functions. The first coordinate change consists in passing each component of the state vector through a nonlinear function, the second coordinate change is in passing the entire linear control law through a nonlinear function. To study such systems, it is proposed to represent nonlinear functions as linear ones with a nonlinear slope. Such a representation will allow using the methods of linear matrix inequalities (LMI) to study the stability of the closed-loop systems. The stability domains and the domains for the initial conditions are found, obtained as a result of a multi-step solution search procedure using LMI. It is shown that the use of the proposed nonlinear control laws makes it possible to reduce the steady-state error compared to the linear one. The simulations illustrate the theoretical conclusions.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>519.7</udk>
          <bbk>Ж 50</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.102.4</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>динамическая система</keyword>
            <keyword>нелинейный закон управления</keyword>
            <keyword>линейные матричные неравенства</keyword>
            <keyword>dynamical system</keyword>
            <keyword>nonlinear control law</keyword>
            <keyword>linear matrix inequalities</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>АНДРИЕВСКИЙ Б.Р., ФРАДКОВ А.Л. Избранные главытеории автоматического управления с примерами на языкеMATLAB. – СПб.: Наука, 2000.</reference>
          <reference>АНТИПОВ А.С., КРАСНОВА С.А., УТКИН В.А. Синтезинвариантных нелинейных одноканальных систем слеже-ния с сигмоидальными обратными связями с обеспечениемзаданной точности слежения Большие отклонения в линей-ных системах при ненулевых начальных условиях // Автома-тика и телемеханика.</reference>
          <reference>КРАСНОВА С.А., АНТИПОВ А.С. Иерархический син-тез сигмоидальных обобщенных моментов манипуляторав условиях неопределенности // Проблемы управления. –2016. – № 4. – С. 10–21.</reference>
          <reference>КРАСНОВА С.А., УТКИН В.А. Каскадный синтез наблю-дателей состояния динамических систем. – М.: Наука,2006.</reference>
          <reference>КРАСНОВА С.А., УТКИН А.В. Сигма-функция в задачахсинтеза наблюдателей состояний и возмущений // Пробле-мы управления. – 2015. – № 5. – С. 27–36.</reference>
          <reference>ХАЛИЛ Х.К. Нелинейные системы. – М-Ижевск: НИЦ «Ре-гулярная и хаотическая динамика», Институт компьютер-ных исследований, 2009.</reference>
          <reference>BOYD S., GHAOUI L.E., FERON E., BALAKRISHNAN V.Linear Matrix Inequalities in System and Control Theory. –Philadelphia, PA: SIAM, 1994.</reference>
          <reference>FRIDMAN E. Introduction to Time-Delay Systems: Analysisand Control. – Springer, International Publishing, 2014.</reference>
          <reference>NEKHOROSHIKH A.N., EFIMOV D., POLYAKOV A.,PERRUQUETTI W., FURTAT I.B., FRIDMAN E. On output-based accelerated stabilization of a chain of integrators:Implicit Lyapunov-Krasovskii functional approach // IFAC-PapersOnLine. – 2020. – Vol. 53, no. 2. – P. 5982–5987.</reference>
          <reference>NEKHOROSHIKH, A.N., EFIMOV, D., POLYAKOV, A.,PERRUQUETTI, W., FURTAT, I.B. On finite-time stabilizationof a class of nonlinear time-delay systems: Implicit Lyapunov-Razumikhin approach // Proc. IEEE Conf. on Decision andControl, 2020. – P. 1975–1980.</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23094</furl>
          <file>UBS10204.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>06.12.2022.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Сетевые модели в управлении</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>76-98</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Тырсин</surname>
              <initials>Александр Николаевич</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Научно-инженерный центр «Надежность и ресурс больших систем и машин» УрО РАН, Екатеринбург; ФГБУН Институт экономики УрО РАН</orgName>
              <email>at2001@yandex.ru</email>
              <address>Екатеринбург</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Tyrsin</surname>
              <initials>Alexander</initials>
              <orgName>Science and Engineering Center “Reliability and Resource of Large Systems and Machines”, Ural Branch of RAS, Yekaterinburg, Institute of Economics</orgName>
              <address>Ural Branch of RAS</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Кащеев</surname>
              <initials>Станислав Евгеньевич</initials>
              <orgName>Южно-Уральский государственный университет</orgName>
              <email>kashcheevs@susu.ru</email>
              <address>Челябинск</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Kashcheev</surname>
              <initials>Stanislav</initials>
              <orgName>South-Ural State University</orgName>
              <address>Chelyabinsk</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Индикаторы риска каскадных сбоев взаимосвязанных сетевых структур</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Risk indicators of cascading failures in interconnected network structures</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Поведение реальных систем часто обладает стохастичностью, а связи между их элементами можно адекватно описывать как корреляционные. В последние годы наблюдаются тенденции увеличения и усложнения современных сетей при росте их зависимости друг от друга. Мы наблюдаем, как несколько сетей объединяются в одну взаимозависимую сетевую структуру. Это приводит к возрастанию рисков того, что отказ узлов в одной сети может привести к отказу зависимых узлов в других сетях. В результате таких отказов могут возникать катастрофические каскадные сбои в таких взаимосвязанных сетевых структурах. С учетом масштабности таких структур, часто являющихся критическими инфраструктурами, данная проблема становится весьма актуальной. В статье введена скалярная мера взаимосвязи между несколькими произвольно распределенными непрерывными случайными векторами. Она позволяет оценить тесноту взаимосвязи между различными подсистемами (сетями) в сетевых структурах. Применительно к гауссовым модельным сетевым структурам проведено исследование влияния тесноты взаимосвязи между подсистемами на риск возникновения каскадных сбоев. В качестве величины риска использовалась вероятность таких сбоев. В качестве индикатора риска возникновения каскадных сбоев в сетевой структуре предложено использовать коэффициент корреляционной взаимосвязи между ее подсистемами. А для снижения риска возникновения каскадных сбоев в сетевой структуре следует уменьшать тесноту корреляции между наиболее взаимосвязанными элементами подсистем.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">The behavior of real systems is often stochastic, and the connections between their elements can be adequately described as correlations. In recent years, there have been trends of increasing and complicating modern networks with the growth of their dependence on each other. We observe how several networks are combined into one interdependent network structure. This leads to an increase in the risks that the failure of nodes in one network may lead to the failure of dependent nodes in other networks. As a result of such failures, catastrophic cascade failures can occur in such interconnected network structures. Given the scale of such structures, which are often critical infrastructures, this problem becomes very relevant. The article introduces a scalar measure of the relationship between several arbitrarily distributed continuous random vectors. It allows you to assess the closeness of the relationship between different subsystems (networks) in network structures. Applied to Gaussian model network structures, the influence of the closeness of the relationship between subsystems on the risk of cascading failures has been studied. The probability of such failures was used as the risk value. As an indicator of the risk of cascading failures in the network structure, it is proposed to use the coefficient of correlation between its subsystems. And to reduce the risk of cascading failures in the network structure, it is necessary to reduce the tightness of correlation between the most interconnected elements of subsystems.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>519.237.5 + 330.131.7</udk>
          <bbk>22.172 + 65.2/4</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.102.5</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>сетевая структура</keyword>
            <keyword>модель</keyword>
            <keyword>риск</keyword>
            <keyword>взаимосвязь</keyword>
            <keyword>каскадный сбой</keyword>
            <keyword>система</keyword>
            <keyword>network structure</keyword>
            <keyword>model</keyword>
            <keyword>risk</keyword>
            <keyword>interconnection</keyword>
            <keyword>cascading failure</keyword>
            <keyword>system</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>АЛЕКСЕЕВ В.В., СОЛОЖЕНЦЕВ Е.Д. Логико-вероятностный подход к управлению риском и эффек-тивностью в структурно-сложных системах // Инфор-мационно-управляющие системы. – 2009. – №6(43). – С. 67–71.</reference>
          <reference>АШНИНА Ю.А. БОРИСОВ А.В., БОРИСОВА Н.И. Раз-витие инфраструктуры современного города: социаль-ные и экономические аспекты // NovaInfo. – 2015. – №39. – С. 177–183.</reference>
          <reference>БУЛАТОВ В.В. Введение в математические методы моделирования сложных систем. – М.: ОнтоПринт, 2018. – 338 с.</reference>
          <reference>МИХАЙЛОВ Г.А., ВОЙТИШЕК А.В. Численное стати-стическое моделирование. Методы Монте-Карло. – М.: Издательский центр «Академия», 2006. – 368 с.</reference>
          <reference>НОВИКОВ Д.А. Сетевые структуры и организационные системы. – М.: ИПУ РАН, 2003. – 102 с.</reference>
          <reference>Современный философский словарь: 2-е изд. / Под общ. ред. В.Е. Кемерова. – М.: ПАНПРИНТ, 1998. – 1064 с.</reference>
          <reference>ТЫРСИН А.Н. Мера совместной корреляционной зави-симости многомерных случайных величин // Заводская лаборатория. Диагностика материалов. – 2014. – Т. 80, №1. – С. 76–80.</reference>
          <reference>ТЫРСИН А.Н. Скалярная мера взаимосвязи между не-сколькими случайными векторами // Заводская лабора-тория. Диагностика материалов. – 2022. – Т. 88, №3. – С. 73–80.</reference>
          <reference>ФИХТЕНГОЛЬЦ Г.М. Курс дифференциального и инте-грального исчисления. В 3 т. Т.1. – 8-е изд. – М.: ФИЗ-МАТЛИТ, 2003. – 680 с.</reference>
          <reference>ХАРДЛЕ В. Прикладная непараметрическая регрессия: Пер. с англ. – М.: Мир, 1993. – 349 с.</reference>
          <reference>BEHRENSDORF J., BROGGI M., BEER M. Reliability Analysis of Networks Interconnected with Copulas // ASCE-ASME. Journal of Risk and Uncertainty in Engineering Sys-tems, Part B Mechanical Engineering. – 2019. – Vol.5. – P. 041006-9.</reference>
          <reference>BULDYREV S.V., PARSHANI R., PAUL G., STAN-LEY H.E., HAVLIN SH. Catastrophic cascade of failures in interdependent networks // Nature. – 2010. – Vol. 464. – P. 1025–1028.</reference>
          <reference>CHERUBINI U., LUCIANO E., VECCHIATO W. Copula Methods in Finance. – Wiley, Chichester, UK, 2004.</reference>
          <reference>ENGLE R.F. Anticipating Correlations. A New Paradigm for Risk Management. – Princeton University Press, 2009.</reference>
          <reference>GOODWIN B.K., HUNGERFORD A. Copula-Based Models of Systemic Risk in us Agriculture: Implications for Crop In-surance and Reinsurance Contracts // American Journal of Agricultural Economics. – 2014. – Vol. 97, No 3. – P. 879–896.</reference>
          <reference>GORBAN A.N., TYUKINA T.A., POKIDYSHEVA L.I., SMIRNOVA E.V. Dynamic and thermodynamic models of adaptation // Physics of Life Reviews. – 2021. – Vol. 37. – P.17–64.</reference>
          <reference>JOE H. Dependence Modeling with Copulas. – Chapman and Hall/CRC, New York, 2014.</reference>
          <reference>LAPRIE J.C., KANOUN K., KANICHE M. Modeling inter-dependencies between the electricity and information infra-structures // SAFECOMP-2007. – 2007. – Vol. 4680. – P. 54–67.</reference>
          <reference>PENA D., RODRIGUEZ J. Descriptive Measures of Multi-variate Scatter and Linear Dependence // Journal of Multi-variate Analysis. – 2003. – Vol. 85, No 2. – P. 361–374.</reference>
          <reference>RAM M., SINGH S.B. Analysis of Reliability Characteristics of a Complex Engineering System under Copula // Journal of Reliability and Statistical Studies. – 2009. – Vol. 2, No 1. – P. 91–102.</reference>
          <reference>RINALDI S., PEERENBOOM J., KELLY T. Identifying, un-derstanding, and analyzing critical infrastructure interde-pendencies // IEEE Control Systems Magazine. – 2001. – Vol. 21. – P. 11–25.</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23095</furl>
          <file>UBS10205.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>12.10.2022.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Надежность и диагностика средств и систем управления</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>99-113</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Задиран</surname>
              <initials>Константин Сергеевич</initials>
              <orgName>Волгоградский государственный технический университет</orgName>
              <email>konstantin.zadiran@gmail.com</email>
              <address>Волгоград</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Zadiran</surname>
              <initials>Konstantin</initials>
              <orgName>Volgograd state technical university</orgName>
              <address>Volgograd</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Щербаков</surname>
              <initials>Максим Владимирович</initials>
              <orgName>Волгоградский государственный технический университет</orgName>
              <email>maxim.shcherbakov@vstu.ru</email>
              <address>Волгоград</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Shcherbakov</surname>
              <initials>Maxim</initials>
              <orgName>Volgograd state technical university</orgName>
              <address>Volgograd</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="3">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Сай</surname>
              <initials>Ван Квонг</initials>
              <orgName>Волгоградский государственный технический университет</orgName>
              <email>svcuonghvktqs@gmail.com</email>
              <address>Волгоград</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Sai</surname>
              <initials>Cuong</initials>
              <orgName>Volgograd state technical university</orgName>
              <address>Volgograd</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Прогнозирование остаточного ресурса оборудования в условиях малой выборки данных</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Forecasting of the remaining useful life in conditions of small data sample</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Предлагается метод прогнозирования остаточного ресурса оборудования, использующий глубокое обучение и применимый в случаях с малым количеством информации об отказах в данных, где существующие классические методы могут не давать требуемой точности. Процесс поддержания оборудования в рабочем состоянии – один из наиболее важных процессов в эксплуатации оборудования. При этом процесс технического обслуживания зачастую страдает от недостаточной эффективности. Поэтому были разработаны методы прогнозирования, на основе которых была построена концепция проактивного управления процессом техобслуживания, позволяющая оптимизировать структуру и затраты управления оборудованием на протяжении жизненного цикла. Однако данные методы могут показывать недостаточную точность, если для их обучения недостаточно данных, например, в связи с редкостью возникновения отказов в оборудовании. Для решения этой проблемы предлагается новый метод прогнозирования, в основе которого лежит алгоритм, основанный на глубоком обучении и который может улучшить точность прогнозирования. В данном методе произведена замена непрерывного прогнозирования остаточного ресурса оборудования на всем интервале на систему генерации сигналов, содержащих рассчитанный прогноз.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">In the article a method for forecasting the residual life of equipment using deep learning is proposed. The method is applicable in cases with a small amount of information about data failures, where existing classical methods may not provide the required accuracy. The process of maintaining the equipment in working condition is one of the most important processes in the operation of the equipment. At the same time, the maintenance process often suffers from inefficiency. Therefore, forecasting methods were developed, on the basis of which the concept of proactive maintenance process management was built, which allows optimizing the structure and costs of equipment management throughout the life cycle. However, these methods may show insufficient accuracy if there is not enough data to train them, for example, due to the rarity of equipment failures. To solve this problem, a new prediction method based on deep learning is proposed that can improve the prediction accuracy. In this method, the continuous prediction of the remaining service life over the entire interval is replaced by a model for generating signals containing the calculated prediction.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>004.9</udk>
          <bbk>32.972</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.102.6</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>машинное обучение</keyword>
            <keyword>остаточный ресурс</keyword>
            <keyword>проактивное техническое обслуживание</keyword>
            <keyword>machine learning</keyword>
            <keyword>remaining useful life</keyword>
            <keyword>proactive maintenance</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>ГУНИНА И.А., ШКАРУПЕТА Е.В., РЕШЕТОВ В.В. Прорывное технологическое развитие промышленных комплексов в условиях цифровой трансформации // Ин-новационные кластеры цифровой экономики: теория и практика. – 2018. – С. 535–554.</reference>
          <reference>КУПРИЯНОВСКИЙ В.П., НАМИОТ Д.Е., ДРОЖЖИ-НОВ В.И., КУПРИЯНОВСКАЯ Ю.В., ИВАНОВ М.О. Интернет вещей на промышленных предприятиях // International Journal of Open Information Technologies. – 2016. – №12. – С. 156–161. </reference>
          <reference>ЛЫСЕНКО С.В., ТЕН Э.В. Об оценке остаточного ре-сурса башенных кранов // Проблемы современной науки и образования. – 2016. – №1. – С. 98–102.</reference>
          <reference>САЙ ВАН КВОНГ, ЩЕРБАКОВ М.В. Метод прогнози-рования остаточного ресурса на основе обработки данных многообъектных сложных систем // Прикаспий-ский журнал: управление и высокие технологии. – 2019. – №1(45). – C. 33–44.</reference>
          <reference>ШИЛОВА Е.В., ДЬЯКОВ А.Р. О феномене четвертой промышленной революции и его влиянии на экономику и управление // Вестник Прикамского социального инсти-тута. – 2018. – №3(81). – С. 86–95.</reference>
          <reference>A Grammar Of Data Manipulation – Dplur. – URL: https://dplyr.tidyverse.org (дата обращения: 03.04.2022). </reference>
          <reference>CERNUDA C. On the relevance of preprocessing in predic-tive maintenance for dynamic systems // In: Lughofer E., Sayed-Mouchaweh M. (Eds.). Predictive Maintenance in Dynamic Systems. Cham, Springer. – 2019. – P. 53–93.</reference>
          <reference>CHENG J.C., CHEN W., CHEN K., WANG Q. Data-driven predictive maintenance planning framework for MEP com-ponents based on BIM and IoT using machine learning al-gorithms // Automation in Construction. – 2020. – Vol. 112. – P. 1– 21.</reference>
          <reference>CHE-SHENG H., JEHN-RUEY J. Remaining useful life esti-mation using long short-term memory deep learning // IEEE Int. Conf. on Applied System Invention (ICASI–2018), Chi-ba, Japan. – 2018. – P. 58–61.</reference>
          <reference>CRAN – Packages. – URL: https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ (дата обращения: 03.04.2022). </reference>
          <reference>Forecast Package – RDocumentation. – URL: https://www.rdocumentation.org/packages/forecast (дата обраще-ния: 03.04.2022).</reference>
          <reference>GOEBEL K., SAHA B., SAXENA A., CELAYA J.R., CHRISTOPHERSEN J.P. Prognostics in battery health man-agement // IEEE Instrumentation &amp; Measurement Magazine. – 2008. – Vol. 8. – P. 33–40. </reference>
          <reference>HUANG Z.Y., XU Z.G., WANG W.H., SUN Y.X. Remain-ing usefullife prediction for a nonlinear heterogeneous Wie-ner process model withan adaptive drift // IEEE Trans. Rel. – June, 2015. – Vol. 64, No. 2. – P. 687–700. </reference>
          <reference>Identify and replace outliers in time series. – URL: https://pkg.robjhyndman.com/forecast/reference/tsoutliers.html (дата обращения: 03.04.2022).</reference>
          <reference>LEI Y., LI N., GONTARZ S., LIN J, RADKOWSKI S., DYBALA J. A Model-Based Method for Remaining Useful Life Prediction of Machinery // IEEE Trans. on Reliability. – 2017. – Vol. 65. – P. 1314–1326.</reference>
          <reference>LI X., DING Q., SUN J. Remaining useful life estimation in prognostics using deep convolution neural networks // Re-liab. Eng. Syst. Saf. – 2018. – Vol. 172. – P. 1–11. </reference>
          <reference>LIU J., WANG W., MA F., YANG Y.B., YANG C.S. A da-ta-model-fusionprognostic framework for dynamic system state forecasting // Eng. Appl.Artif. Intell. – June, 2012. – Vol. 25, No. 4. – P. 814–823. </reference>
          <reference>PATIL S., PATIL A., HANDIKHERKAR V., DESAI S., PHALLE V. M., KAZI F. S. Remaining Useful Life (RUL) Prediction of Rolling Element Bearing Using Random Forest and Gradient Boosting Technique // ASME 2018 Interna-tional Mechanical Engineering Congress and Exposition. – 2018. – P. 1–7.</reference>
          <reference>RAN Y., ZHOU X., LIN P., WEN Y., DENG R. A Survey of Predictive Maintenance: Systems, Purposes and Approaches // IEEE communications Surveys &amp; Tutorials. – 2019. – P. 1–36.</reference>
          <reference>SHCHERBAKOV M.V. A Survey of Forecast Error Measures // World Applied Sciences Journal (WASJ). – 2013. – No. 24. – P. 171–176. </reference>
          <reference>XIONGZI C., JINSONG Y., DIYIN T. YINGXUN W. Re-maining useful life prognostic estimation for aircraft subsys-tems or components: A review // 10th IEEE Int. Conf. on Electronic Measurement &amp; Instruments (ICEMI). – 2011. – Vol. 2. – P. 94.</reference>
          <reference>YAN M., WANG X., WANG B., CHANG M., MUHAM-MAD I. Bearing remaining useful life prediction using sup-port vector machine and hybrid degradation tracking model // ISA Trans. – 2020. – Vol. 98. – P. 471–482.</reference>
          <reference>YU J. Remaining useful life prediction for lithium-ion batter-ies using a quantum particle swarm optimization-based par-ticle filter // Quality Engineering. – 2017. – Vol 29. – P. 536–546. </reference>
          <reference>ZHANG Z., SI X., HU C., LEY Y. Degradation data analy-sis and remaining useful life estimation: A review on Wiener-process-based methods // European Journal of Operational Research. – 2018. – Vol. 271(3). – P. 775–796.</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23096</furl>
          <file>UBS10206.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>20.07.2022.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
    </articles>
  </issue>
</journal>
