<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<journal>
  <operCard>
    <operator>ИПУ РАН|Губко М.В.</operator>
    <date>2023-10-03 15:35:05</date>
    <cntArticle>5</cntArticle>
  </operCard>
  <issn>1819-2440</issn>
  <eissn>1819-2467</eissn>
  <titleid>10618</titleid>
  <journalInfo lang="RUS">
    <title>Управление большими системами</title>
    <abbrTitle>УБС</abbrTitle>
    <publ>Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</publ>
    <placePubl>Москва</placePubl>
    <address>117997, г. Москва, ул. Профсоюзная, д. 65.</address>
  </journalInfo>
  <journalInfo lang="ENG">
    <title>Large-scale Systems Control</title>
    <abbrTitle>LSSC</abbrTitle>
  </journalInfo>
  <issue>
    <number>104</number>
    <dateUni>202307</dateUni>
    <pages>1–134</pages>
    <articles>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Системный анализ</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>5-35</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Касаткин</surname>
              <initials>Андрей Алексеевич</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУ «НИЦ «Институт имени Н.Е. Жуковского»</orgName>
              <email>kasatkinaa@nrczh.ru</email>
              <address/>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Kasatkin</surname>
              <initials>Andrey</initials>
              <orgName>National Research Center “Zhukovskiy Institute”</orgName>
              <address>Zhukovskiy</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Методы моделирования и оптимизации уровня автономности технического обслуживания и ремонта парка авиационной техники гражданского назначения</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">methods for modelling and optimization of the level of autonomy of maintenance, overhaul and repair of the civil aircrfat fleet</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Организация технического обслуживания и ремонта парка воздушных судов принципиально отличается для воздушных судов разных классов. Зачастую техническое обслуживание и ремонт рассматриваются лишь как часть полных эксплуатационных расходов, однако для воздушных судов, обладающих малыми дальностью и скоростью полета, перегон судна на специализированные ремонтные предприятия или предприятия-производители может быть причиной значительных временных издержек. В статье рассматривается проблема организации технического обслуживания и ремонта парка воздушных судов местных воздушных линий в отдаленных и малонаселенных регионах. Рассматриваются различные подходы к технической эксплуатации парка воздушных судов: эксплуатация по регламенту и по фактическому состоянию, проведение технического обслуживания и ремонта в соответствии с РТЭ и переход к более автономному проведению технического обслуживания и ремонта. Старение высоконагруженной техники, обуславливающее увеличение потока отказов техники с ростом наработки, в данной работе не рассматривается. Проводится моделирование выполнения пассажироперевозок в регионе с учетом технического обслуживания и ремонта парка воздушных судов. Рассчитываются экономические характеристики пассажироперевозок.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">The organization of maintenance, repair and overhaul of the aircraft fleet is fundamentally different for different classes of aircraft. Frequently, maintenance and repairs are considered only as part of the total operating costs, but for aircraft with short range and speed, transferring the aircraft to specialized repair facilities or manufacturing facilities can cause significant time costs. The article deals with the problem of organizing maintenance and repair of the aircraft fleet of local airlines in remote and sparsely populated regions. Various approaches to the technical maintenance of the aircraft fleet are considered: operation according to the regulations and according to the actual state, maintenance and repair in accordance with the maintenance manual and the transition to a more autonomous maintenance and repair. The obsolescence of highly loaded equipment, which causes an increase in the arrival rate of equipment failures with an increase in operating time, is not considered in this paper. Simulation of the performance of passenger transportation in the region is carried out, taking into account the maintenance and repair of the aircraft fleet. The economic characteristics of passenger transportation are calculated.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>021.8 + 025.1</udk>
          <bbk>78.34</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.104.1</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>техническое обслуживание и ремонт авиационной техники</keyword>
            <keyword>местные воздушные линии</keyword>
            <keyword>авиатранспортная система</keyword>
            <keyword>aircraft maintenance</keyword>
            <keyword>repair and overhaul; local air lines; air transport system</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>ГОРШКОВА И.В., КЛОЧКОВ В.В. Экономический ана-лиз перспектив развития воздушного транспорта в ма-лонаселенных регионах России // Проблемы прогнозиро-вания. – 2011. – №6. – С. 36–52.</reference>
          <reference>ДАЛЕЦКИЙ С.В., ДЕРКАЧ О.Я., ПЕТРОВ А.Н. Эффек-тивность технической эксплуатации самолетов граж-данской авиации. – М.: «Воздушный транспорт», 2002.</reference>
          <reference>ДАЛЕЦКИЙ Е.С. Оценка эффективности эксплуатации изделий авиатехники при эксплуатации до безопасного отказа // Научный вестник ГосНИИ ГА. – 2008. – №130. – С. 180–187.</reference>
          <reference>ЕГОШИН С.Ф. Влияние особенностей моделирования пассажирских потоков на выбор оптимального воздуш-ного судна местных воздушных линий // Научный вестник ГосНИИ ГА. – 2021. – №35. – С. 68–79.</reference>
          <reference>КЛОЧКОВ В.В., РОЖДЕСТВЕНСКАЯ С.М., ФРИД-ЛЯНД А.А. Обоснование приоритетных направлений развития авиационной техники для местных воздушных линий // Научный вестник ГосНИИ ГА. – 2018. – № 20(331). – С. 93–102.</reference>
          <reference>ФОМИНА И.В., ШЕВЕЛЕВА А.А. Повышение авиацион-ной доступности территорий европейского и при-уральского севера России // Материалы международной-научно-практи¬ческой конференции «Транспорт России: проблемы и перспективы – 2018», Санкт-Петербург, 13-14 ноября 2018 г. – С. 81–83.</reference>
          <reference>Межгосударственный авиационный комитет. Состоя-ние безопасности полетов в гражданской авиации госу-дарств-участников соглашения о гражданской авиации и об использовании воздушного пространства в 2016 г. [Электронный ресурс]. – 2017. – URL: https://mak-iac.org/upload/iblock/552/bp-16-2.pdf (дата обращения: 05.12.2022).</reference>
          <reference>Межгосударственный авиационный комитет. Состоя-ние безопасности полетов в гражданской авиации госу-дарств-участников соглашения о гражданской авиации и об использовании воздушного пространства в 2017 г. [Электронный ресурс]. – 2018. – URL: https://mak-iac.org/upload/iblock/4b6/bp-17-2.pdf (дата обращения: 05.12.2022).</reference>
          <reference>Межгосударственный авиационный комитет. Состоя-ние безопасности полетов в гражданской авиации госу-дарств-участников соглашения о гражданской авиации и об использовании воздушного пространства в 2018 г. [Электронный ресурс]. – 2019. – URL: https://mak-iac.org/upload/iblock/03e/bp-18-2.pdf (дата обращения: 05.12.2022).</reference>
          <reference>Межгосударственный авиационный комитет. Состоя-ние безопасности полетов в гражданской авиации госу-дарств-участников соглашения о гражданской авиации и об использовании воздушного пространства в 2020 г. [Электронный ресурс]. – 2021. – URL: https://mak-iac.org/upload/iblock/1c1/bp-20-2.pdf (дата обращения: 05.12.2022).</reference>
          <reference>Межгосударственный авиационный комитет. Состоя-ние безопасности полетов в гражданской авиации госу-дарств-участников соглашения о гражданской авиации и об использовании воздушного пространства в 2021 г. [Электронный ресурс]. – 2022. – URL: https://mak-iac.org/upload/iblock/448/cvhy5ylxegg5sghcxr6icz0irccnj2ge/bp-21.pdf (дата обращения: 05.12.2022).</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23149</furl>
          <file>UBS10401.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>09.03.2023.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Анализ и синтез систем управления</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>36-72</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Богданов</surname>
              <initials>Станислав Дмитриевич</initials>
              <orgName>Сколковский институт науки и технологий</orgName>
              <email>s.bogdanov@skoltech.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Bogdanov</surname>
              <initials>Stanislav</initials>
              <orgName>Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Парсегов</surname>
              <initials>Сергей Эрнестович</initials>
              <orgName>Сколковский институт науки и технологий, ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>s.e.parsegov@gmail.com</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Parsegov</surname>
              <initials>Sergei</initials>
              <orgName>Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology, V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="3">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Пугач</surname>
              <initials>Михаил Александрович</initials>
              <orgName>Сколковский институт науки и технологий</orgName>
              <email>m.pugach@skoltech.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Pugach</surname>
              <initials>Mikhail</initials>
              <orgName>Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Ванадиевые проточные аккумуляторы: модели динамики и измерений</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Vanadium redox flow batteries: models of dynamics and measurements</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Статья знакомит читателей с ванадиевыми проточными аккумуляторами, принципами их работы и моделями в пространстве состояний. Ванадиевые проточные аккумуляторы (ВПА) -- перспективная технология стационарных накопителей электрической энергии, имеющая ряд преимуществ перед традиционными накопителями на основе литий-ионных батарей. Одна из особенностей ВПА -- наличие гидравлической системы с насосами, обеспечивающими непрерывную подачу электролита из резервуаров, где он хранится, в стек, где происходят электрохимические реакции. Это влечёт за собой необходимость построения динамических моделей таких систем, которые используются для задач мониторинга и управления. В статье приводятся основные модели динамики ванадиевых аккумуляторов с сосредоточенными параметрами, модели доступных измерений, анализируются их особенности. Кроме того, предлагаются новые модели, позволяющие более точно описывать изменение концентраций в процессе длительной работы ВПА.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">This article introduces readers to vanadium redox flow batteries, their operating principles, and state-space models. Vanadium redox flow batteries (VRFBs) are a promising technology for stationary storage of electric energy, which has a number of advantages over traditional storage batteries based on lithium-ion batteries. One of the features of VRFBs is a hydraulic system with pumps that provide a continuous supply of electrolyte from the tanks where it is stored to the stacks where the electrochemical reactions take place. This entails the need to build dynamic models of such systems, which are used for monitoring and control tasks. The article presents the basic models of vanadium battery dynamics with concentrated parameters, along with models of available measurements, and analyzes their features. In addition, new models are proposed that allow a more accurate and convenient description of the change in concentrations during VRFB operation.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>681.5</udk>
          <bbk>31.251</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.104.2</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>ванадиевые проточные аккумуляторы</keyword>
            <keyword>динамические модели</keyword>
            <keyword>валидация моделей</keyword>
            <keyword>vanadium redox flow batteries</keyword>
            <keyword>dynamical models</keyword>
            <keyword>model validation</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>AARON D., TANG Z., PAPANDREW A., ZAWODZINSKI T.Polarization curve analysis of all-vanadium redox flowbatteries // Journal Of Applied Electrochemistry. – 2011. –Vol. 41. – P. 1175–1182.</reference>
          <reference>BAROTE L., MARINESCU C. A new control method forVRB SOC estimation in stand-alone wind energy systems //Int. Conf. On Clean Electrical Power, (ICCEP-2009). – 2009. –P. 253–257.</reference>
          <reference>BARTON J., BRUSHETT F. A one-dimensional stack modelfor redox flow battery analysis and operation // Batteries. –2019. – Vol. 5.</reference>
          <reference>BHATTACHARJEE A., ROY A., BANERJEE N., PATRA S.,SAHA H. Precision dynamic equivalent circuit model of aVanadium Redox Flow Battery and determination of circuitparameters for its optimal performance in renewable energyapplications // Journal Of Power Sources. – 2018. – Vol. 396. –P. 506–518.</reference>
          <reference>BOGDANOV S., PUGACH M., PARSEGOV S., VLASOV V.,IBANEZ F., STEVENSON K., VOROBEV P. Dynamicmodeling of vanadium redox flow batteries: Practicalapproaches, their applications and limitations // Journal OfEnergy Storage. – 2023. – Vol. 57, 106191.</reference>
          <reference>CHAHWAN J., ABBEY C., JOOS G. VRB modelling forthe study of output terminal voltages, internal losses andperformance // IEEE Canada Electrical Power Conference(EPC-2007). – 2007. – P. 387–392.</reference>
          <reference>CHANG W. The State of Charge Estimating Methods forBattery: A Review // ISRN Applied Mathematics. – 2013. –P. 1–7.</reference>
          <reference>CHEN Y., XU Z., WANG C., BAO J., KOEPPEL B., YAN L.,GAO P., WANG W. Analytical modeling for redox flow batterydesign // Journal Of Power Sources. – 2021. – Vol. 482. –P. 228817.</reference>
          <reference>CLEMENTE A., CECILIA A., COSTA-CASTELLO R.Online state of charge estimation for a vanadium redox flowbattery with unequal flow rates // Journal Of Energy Storage. –2023. – Vol. 60. – P. 106503.</reference>
          <reference>CLEMENTE A., COSTA-CASTELLO R. Redox flowbatteries: A literature review oriented to automatic control //Energies. – 2020. – Vol. 13. – P. 1–31.</reference>
          <reference>CLEMENTE A., MONTIEL M., BARRERAS F., LOZANO A.,COSTA-CASTELLO R. Vanadium Redox Flow Battery State ofCharge Estimation Using a Concentration Model and a SlidingMode Observer // IEEE Access. – 2021. – Vol. 9. –P. 72368–72376.</reference>
          <reference>COLTHORPE A. China’s largest solar-plus-flow batteryproject will be accompanied by vrfb gigafactory [Элек-тронный ресурс] // Energy Storage News. – URL:https://www.energy-storage.news/chinas-largest-solar-plus-flow-battery-project-will-be-accompanied-by-vrfb-gigafactory(дата обращения: 04.04.2022).</reference>
          <reference>CORCUERA S., SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M. State-of-ChargeMonitoring and Electrolyte Rebalancing Methods for theVanadium Redox Flow Battery // European ChemicalBulletin. – 2012. – Vol. 1. – P. 511–519.</reference>
          <reference>JIENKULSAWAD P., JIRABOVORNWISUT T., CHEN Y.,ARPORNWICHANOP A. Improving the Performance of anAll-Vanadium Redox Flow Battery under Imbalance Conditions:Online Dynamic Optimization Approach // ACS SustainableChemistry And Engineering. – 2020. – Vol. 8. – P. 13610–13622.</reference>
          <reference>KAZACOS M., CHENG M., SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M.Vanadium redox cell electrolyte optimization studies // JournalOf Applied Electrochemistry. – 1990. – Vol. 20. – P. 463–467.</reference>
          <reference>KHAKI B., DAS P. An equivalent circuit model for VanadiumRedox Batteries via hybrid extended Kalman filter and Particlefilter methods // Journal Of Energy Storage. – 2021. – Vol. 39. –P. 102587.</reference>
          <reference>KNEHR K., AGAR E., DENNISON C., KALIDINDI A.,KUMBUR E. A Transient Vanadium Flow Battery ModelIncorporating Vanadium Crossover and Water Transportthrough the Membrane // Journal Of The ElectrochemicalSociety. – 2012. – Vol. 159. – P. A1446–A1459.</reference>
          <reference>KONIG S., SURIYAH M., LEIBFRIED T. Validating andimproving a zero-dimensional stack voltage model of theVanadium Redox Flow Battery // Journal Of Power Sources. –2018. – Vol. 378. – P. 10–18.</reference>
          <reference>LI B., LUO Q., WEI X., NIE Z., THOMSEN E., CHEN B.,SPRENKLE V., WANG W. Capacity decay mechanism ofmicroporous separator-based all-vanadium redox flow batteriesand its recovery // ChemSusChem. – 2014. – Vol. 7. –P. 577–584.</reference>
          <reference>MOHAMED M., AHMAD H., SEMAN M., RAZALI S.,NAJIB M. Electrical circuit model of a vanadium redox flowbattery using extended Kalman filter // Journal Of PowerSources. – 2013. – Vol. 239. – P. 284–293.</reference>
          <reference>MUNOZ C., DEWAGE H., YUFIT V., BRANDON N. A UnitCell Model of a Regenerative Hydrogen-Vanadium Fuel Cell //Journal Of The Electrochemical Society. – 2017. – Vol. 164. –P. F1717–F1732.</reference>
          <reference>NGAMSAI K., ARPORNWICHANOP A. Measuring the stateof charge of the electrolyte solution in a vanadium redox flowbattery using a four-pole cell device // Journal Of PowerSources. – 2015. – Vol. 298. – P. 150–157.</reference>
          <reference>OH K., WON S., JU H. A comparative study of speciesmigration and diffusion mechanisms in all-vanadium redoxflow batteries // Electrochimica Acta. – 2015. – Vol. 181. –P. 238–247.</reference>
          <reference>PUGACH M., KONDRATENKO M., BRIOLA S., BISCHI A.Zero dimensional dynamic model of vanadium redox flowbattery cell incorporating all modes of vanadium ionscrossover // Applied Energy. – 2018. – Vol. 226. – P. 560–569.</reference>
          <reference>PULESTON T., CECILIA A., COSTA-CASTELLO R.,SERRA M. Vanadium redox flow batteries real-time Stateof Charge and State of Health estimation under electrolyteimbalance condition // Journal Of Energy Storage. – 2023. –Vol. 68. – P. 107666.</reference>
          <reference>SEAMAN A., DAO T., MCPHEE J. A survey of mathematics-based equivalent-circuit and electrochemical battery models forhybrid and electric vehicle simulation // Journal Of PowerSources. – 2014. – Vol. 256. – P. 410–423.</reference>
          <reference>SEEPANA M., SAMUDRALA S., SURESH P., VOORADI R.Unit Cell Modelling and Simulation of All Vanadium RedoxFlow Battery // Chemical Product And Process Modeling. –2018. – Vol. 13. – P. 1-13.</reference>
          <reference>SHAH A., TANGIRALA R., SINGH R., WILLS R., WALSH F.A Dynamic Unit Cell Model for the All-Vanadium FlowBattery // Journal Of The Electrochemical Society. – 2011. –Vol. 158. – P. A671.</reference>
          <reference>SHI Y., WEI Z., LIU H., ZHAO J. Dynamic modeling oflong-term operations of vanadium/air redox flow battery withdifferent membranes // Journal Of Energy Storage. – 2022. –Vol. 50. – P. 104171.</reference>
          <reference>SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M., CHAKRABARTI M.,HAJIMOLANA S., MJALLI F., SALEEM M. Progressin flow battery research and development // Journal Of TheElectrochemical Society. – 2011. – Vol. 158. – P. R55.</reference>
          <reference>SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M., GOH L. Modeling of vanadium iondiffusion across the ion exchange membrane in the vanadiumredox battery // Journal Of Membrane Science. – 2012. –Vol. 399. – P. 43–48.</reference>
          <reference>SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M., KAZACOS M. State of chargemonitoring methods for vanadium redox flow battery control //Journal Of Power Sources. – 2011. – Vol. 196. – P. 8822–8827.</reference>
          <reference>TANG A., BAO J., SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M. Dynamicmodelling of the effects of ion diffusion and side reactions onthe capacity loss for vanadium redox flow battery // Journal OfPower Sources. – 2011. – Vol. 196. – P. 10737–10747.</reference>
          <reference>TANG A., BAO J., SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M. Thermalmodelling of battery configuration and self-discharge reactionsin vanadium redox flow battery // Journal Of Power Sources. –2012. – Vol. 216. – P. 489–501.</reference>
          <reference>TANG A., BAO J., SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M. Studies onpressure losses and flow rate optimization in vanadium redoxflow battery // Journal Of Power Sources. – 2014. – Vol. 248. –P. 154–162.</reference>
          <reference>TANG A., MCCANN J., BAO J., SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M.Investigation of the effect of shunt current on battery efficiencyand stack temperature in vanadium redox flow battery //Journal Of Power Sources. – 2013. – Vol. 242. – P. 349–356.</reference>
          <reference>TROVO A., MARINI G., SUTTO A., ALOTTO P.,GIOMO M., MORO F., GUARNIERI M. Standby thermalmodel of a vanadium redox flow battery stack with crossoverand shunt-current effects // Applied Energy. – 2019. –Vol. 240. – P. 893–906.</reference>
          <reference>TROVO A., SACCARDO A., GIOMO M., GUARNIERI M.Thermal modeling of industrial-scale vanadium redox flowbatteries in high-current operations // Journal Of PowerSources. – 2019. – Vol. 424. – P. 204–214.</reference>
          <reference>VYNNYCKY M. Analysis of a model for the operation of avanadium redox battery // Energy. – 2011. – Vol. 36. – P. 2242–2256.</reference>
          <reference>WANDSCHNEIDER F., ROHM S., FISCHER P.,PINKWART K., TUBKE J., NIRSCHL H. A multi-stacksimulation of shunt currents in vanadium redox flow batteries //Journal Of Power Sources. – 2014. – Vol. 261. – P. 64–74.</reference>
          <reference>WANG H., POURMOUSAVI S., SOONG W., ZHANG X.,ERTUGRUL N. Battery and energy management systemfor vanadium redox flow battery: A critical review andrecommendations // Journal Of Energy Storage. – 2023. –Vol. 58.</reference>
          <reference>WANG Q., QU Z., JIANG Z., YANG W. Numerical study onvanadium redox flow battery performance with non-uniformlycompressed electrode and serpentine flow field // AppliedEnergy. – 2018. – Vol. 220. – P. 106–116.</reference>
          <reference>WANG T., FU J., ZHENG M., YU Z. Dynamic control strategyfor the electrolyte flow rate of vanadium redox flow batteries //Applied Energy. – 2018. – Vol. 227. – P. 613–623.</reference>
          <reference>WEAVER J. World’s largest battery: 200MW/800MWhvanadium flow battery —site work ongoing // Electrek. – 2017</reference>
          <reference>WEI Z., JET K., WAI N., MARIANA T., SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M. Adaptive estimation of state of charge andcapacity with online identi fi ed battery model for vanadiumredox fl ow battery // Journal Of Power Sources. – 2016. –Vol. 332. – P. 389–398.</reference>
          <reference>WU X., YUAN X., WANG Z., LIU J., HU Y., DENG Q.,YIN X., ZHOU Q., ZHOU W., WU Y. Electrochemicalperformance of 5 kW all-vanadium redox flow battery stack witha flow frame of multi-distribution channels // Journal Of SolidState Electrochemistry. – 2017. – Vol. 21. – P. 429–435.</reference>
          <reference>XIONG B., YANG Y., TANG J., LI Y., WEI Z., SU Y.,ZHANG Q. An Enhanced Equivalent Circuit Model ofVanadium Redox Flow Battery Energy Storage SystemsConsidering Thermal Effects // IEEE Access. – 2019. – Vol. 7. –P. 162297–162308.</reference>
          <reference>XIONG B., ZHAO J., SU Y., WEI Z., SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M. State of Charge Estimation of Vanadium RedoxFlow Battery Based on Sliding Mode Observer and DynamicModel Including Capacity Fading Factor // IEEE Trans. OnSustainable Energy. – 2017. – Vol. 8. – P. 1658–1667.</reference>
          <reference>XU Q., ZHAO T., LEUNG P. Numerical investigations of flowfield designs for vanadium redox flow batteries // AppliedEnergy. – 2013. – Vol. 105. – P. 47–56.</reference>
          <reference>YANG X., YE Q., CHENG P., ZHAO T. Effects of the electricfield on ion crossover in vanadium redox flow batteries //Applied Energy. – 2015. – Vol. 145. – P. 306–319.</reference>
          <reference>YIN C., GAO Y., XIE G., LI T., TANG H. Three dimensionalmulti-physical modeling study of interdigitated flow field inporous electrode for vanadium redox flow battery // JournalOf Power Sources. – 2019. – Vol. 438. – P. 227023.</reference>
          <reference>YOU X., YE Q., CHENG P. The Dependence of MassTransfer Coefficient on the Electrolyte Velocity in Carbon FeltElectrodes: Determination and Validation // Journal Of TheElectrochemical Society. – 2017. – Vol. 164. – P. E3386–E3394.</reference>
          <reference>ZHANG B., LEI Y., BAI B., XU A., ZHAO T. A two-dimensional mathematical model for vanadium redox flowbattery stacks incorporating nonuniform electrolyte distributionin the flow frame // Applied Thermal Engineering. – 2019. –Vol. 151. – P. 495–505.</reference>
          <reference>ZHANG Y., ZHAO J., WANG P., SKYLLAS-KAZACOS M.,XIONG B., BADRINARAYANAN R. A comprehensiveequivalent circuit model of all-vanadium redox flow battery forpower system analysis // Journal Of Power Sources. – 2015. –Vol. 290. – P. 14–24.</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23150</furl>
          <file>UBS10402.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>20.06.2023.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Управление в социально-экономических системах</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>73-99</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Власенко</surname>
              <initials>Андрей Олегович</initials>
              <orgName>ООО «Межотраслевой аналитический центр»</orgName>
              <email>andrey.vlasenko84@gmail.com</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Vlasenko</surname>
              <initials>Andrey</initials>
              <orgName>Intersectoral analytical center</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Сухарев</surname>
              <initials>Алексей Александрович</initials>
              <orgName>Национальный исследовательский университет «Высшая школа экономики»</orgName>
              <email>alx.sukharev@gmail.com</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Sukharev</surname>
              <initials>Alexey</initials>
              <orgName>National Research University Higher School of Economics</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="3">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Урюпин</surname>
              <initials>Илья Вадимович</initials>
              <orgName>Федеральное государственное учреждение «Федеральный исследовательский центр «Информатика и управление» РАН»</orgName>
              <email>uryupin93@yandex.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Uryupin</surname>
              <initials>Ilia</initials>
              <orgName>Federal Research Center "Computer Science and Control" of the Russian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Оценка качества функционирования авиатранспортной системы как инструмент формирования требований к перспективной авиационной технике</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Developing the air transportation system quality assessment tools to define the main requirements for future aircraft</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Предложены новые метрики «качества» авиатранспортной системы – физической и экономической доступности авиаперевозки для пассажира, применение которых в стратегическом планировании для постановки согласованной системы целей и задач долгосрочного развития гражданской авиационной деятельности и научно-технологического развития авиастроения позволит гармонизировать интересы ее ключевых стейкхолдеров – государства, конечных пользователей авиатранспорта, эксплуатантов, производителей гражданской авиатехники и организаций авиационной науки. Описана методика получения точечной и интегральной оценок качества авиатранспортной системы для пассажира по выбранной мере преодоления пространства, математическая модель и алгоритм их вычисления. Реализация методики продемонстрирована на базе разработанного программного комплекса, оперирующего доступной для сбора или приобретения статистической информацией. Возможности применения метрик к задаче формирования требований к перспективной авиатехнике показаны на примере количественной оценки влияния на качество авиатранспортной системы замены региональных самолетов с газотурбинными двигателями на «более электрические» самолеты вдвое меньшей вместимости.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">The aim of this article is to define and to describe the calculation methodology for both on-point and general quantitative indicators of air transportation system quality for a passenger. The indicators can be based on any of the three common measures of path-passing (time, cost, and distance). The pair of values that is proposed to be used as indicators is (1) a guaranteed value of the selected measure of path-passing defined for (2) a share of the population inside the air transportation system. As an application example the article describes the use of program module based on the proposed methodology to assess the potential benefits from the substitution of a Russia-based fleet of gas turbine powered regional aircraft with a fleet of “more electric” aircraft that have a twice less passenger capacity. The proposed indicators may be used as either optimization criteria or a boundary condition while developing the requirements for future civil aircraft.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>656.7</udk>
          <bbk>39.58</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.104.3</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>стратегическое планирование</keyword>
            <keyword>доступность авиаперевозки</keyword>
            <keyword>оценка качества авиатранспортной системы</keyword>
            <keyword>математическое моделирование</keyword>
            <keyword>гарантированное время путешествия</keyword>
            <keyword>требования к перспективным самолетам</keyword>
            <keyword>strategic planning</keyword>
            <keyword>air transportation accessibility</keyword>
            <keyword>quality evaluation of air transportation</keyword>
            <keyword>mathematical modelling</keyword>
            <keyword>guaranteed trip-time</keyword>
            <keyword>advanced aircraft requirements</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>ГОРБУНОВ В.П. Эволюция представлений о транс-портной доступности // Бюллетень транспортной ин-формации. – 2019. – №8. – С. 10–14.</reference>
          <reference>ДУБОВИК В.О. Методы оценки транспортной доступ-ности территории // Региональные исследования. – 2013. – №4. – С. 11–18.</reference>
          <reference>ДУТОВ А.В., КЛОЧКОВ В.В. Методы оценки влияния технологий на характеристики перспективной продук-ции и достижение целей научно-технологического раз-вития (на примере гражданского авиастроения) //Экономика науки. – 2020. – Т. 6, №1-2.</reference>
          <reference>ДУТОВ А.В., КЛОЧКОВ В.В., РОЖДЕСТВЕНСКАЯ С.М. Измерение и нормирование транспортной связанности и качества транспортного обслуживания страны и ее регионов // Россия: тенденции и перспективы развития. – 2019. – №14-2. – С. 43–48.</reference>
          <reference>ЕГОШИН С.Ф., СМИРНОВ А.В. Авиатранспортная до-ступность и транспортная дискриминация населения в субъектах Российской Федерации // Научный вестник Московского государственного технического универси-тета гражданской авиации. – 2018. – Т. 21. – №3.</reference>
          <reference>КАРПОВ А.Е., КЛОЧКОВ В.В. Моделирование и опти-мизация системы регулярных местных воздушных пере-возок с использованием скоростных винтокрылых ле-тательных аппаратов // Труды конференции «Управле-ние развитием крупномасштабных систем MLSD'2020». – 2020. – С. 1220–1231.</reference>
          <reference>КЛОЧКОВ В.В., РОЖДЕСТВЕНСКАЯ С.М., ФРИД-ЛЯНД А.А. Обоснование приоритетных направлений развития авиационной техники для местных воздушных линий // Научный вестник ГосНИИ ГА. – 2018. – №20. – С. 93–102.</reference>
          <reference>МАЛАЩУК П.А. Зарубежный опыт оценки транспорт-ной доступности // Актуальные проблемы, направления и механизмы развития производительных сил Севера-2018. – 2018. – С. 220–224.</reference>
          <reference>МАНТУРОВ Д.В., КЛОЧКОВ В.В. Методологические проблемы стратегического планирования развития рос-сийской авиационной промышленности // Труды МАИ. – 2012. – №53. – С. 17.</reference>
          <reference>РОЖДЕСТВЕНСКАЯ С.М., СЫПАЛО К.И. Обоснование целей и приоритетных направлений научно-технологического развития авиастроения // Россия: тенденции и перспективы развития. – 2018. – №13-1.</reference>
          <reference>ALEXANDRE J. et al. An innovative approach for integrat-ed airline network and aircraft family optimization // Chinese Journal of Aeronautics. – 2020. – Vol. 33, No. 2. – P. 634–663.</reference>
          <reference>BARON A. Air transport efficiency and its measures // Prace Instytutu Lotnictwa. – 2010. – No. 3(205). – P. 119–132.</reference>
          <reference>DZIKUS N.M. et al. Market-driven Derivation of Field Per-formance Requirements for Conceptual Aircraft Design // Aviation Technology, Integration, and Operations Confer-ence – 2018. – P. 3499.</reference>
          <reference>EISENHUT D. et al. Aircraft requirements for sustainable regional aviation // Aerospace. – 2021. – Vol. 8, No. 3. – P. 61.</reference>
          <reference>FREGNANI J.A.T.G., DE MATTOS B.S., HER-NANDES J.A. Multidisciplinary and Multi-Objective Optimi-zation Considering Aircraft Program Cost and Airline Net-work // Journal of Air Transportation. – 2021. – Vol. 29, No. 1. – P. 27–41.</reference>
          <reference>FREGNANI J.A., MATTOS B.S., HERNANDES J.A. An In-novative Approach for integrated Airline Network and Air-craft Family Optimization // AIAA Aviation 2019 Forum. – 2019. – P. 2865.</reference>
          <reference>GEURS K.T., VAN WEE B. Accessibility evaluation of land-use and transport strategies: review and research directions // Journal of Transport geography. – 2004. – Vol. 12, No. 2. – P. 127–140.</reference>
          <reference>GRIMME W., MAERTENS S. Flightpath 2050 revisited–An analysis of the 4-hour-goal using flight schedules and origin-destination passenger demand data // Transportation Research Procedia. – 2019. – Vol. 43. – P. 147–155.</reference>
          <reference>HASAN Y.J., SACHS F. Performance-based preliminary design and selection of aircraft configurations for unmanned cargo operations // Automated Low-Altitude Air Delivery. – Springer, Cham, 2022. – P. 107–131.</reference>
          <reference>HOELZEN J. et al. Hydrogen-powered aviation and its reli-ance on green hydrogen infrastructure–Review and re-search gaps // Int. Journal of Hydrogen Energy. – 2021.</reference>
          <reference>HUANG J. Growth, Evolution and Scaling in Transport Networks : PhD Thesis. – University of Leeds, 2015.</reference>
          <reference>ROY S. et al. Monolithic Approach for Next-Generation Air-craft Design Considering Airline Operations and Economics // Journal of Aircraft. – 2019. – Vol. 56, No. 4. – P. 1565–1576.</reference>
          <reference>SAIF M.A., ZEFREH M.M., TOROK A. Public transport accessibility: a literature review // Periodica Polytechnica Transportation Engineering. – 2019. – Vol. 47, No. 1. – P. 36–43.</reference>
          <reference>SUN X., WANDELT S., HANSEN M. Airport road access at planet scale using population grid and openstreetmap // Networks and Spatial Economics. – 2020. – Vol. 20, No. 1. – P. 273–299.</reference>
          <reference>WÖHLER S. et al. Preliminary aircraft design for a mid-range reference aircraft taking advanced technologies into account as part of the AVACON project for an entry into service in 2028. – Deutsche Gesellschaft für Luft-und Raumfahrt-Lilienthal-Oberth eV, 2019.</reference>
          <reference>YANG T., YING Y. AUC maximization in the era of big da-ta and AI: A survey // ACM Computing Surveys (CSUR). – 2022.</reference>
          <reference>YIA P., WANDELTA S., SUNA X. Flightpath 2050 door-to-door travel time goal: A comparative study on Europe and China // 8th Int. Conf. on Air Transport – INAIR 2019 GLOBAL TRENDS IN AVIATION.</reference>
          <reference>https://www.acare4europe.org/sria/flightpath-2050-goals (дата обращения: 01.09.2021)</reference>
          <reference>https://www.faa.gov/sites/faa.gov/files/npias-2023-2027-narrative.pdf (дата обращения: 15.12.2022).</reference>
          <reference>https://sacd.larc.nasa.gov//sacd/wp-content/uploads/sites/102/2021/04/2021-04-20-RAM.pdf (дата обращения: 03.11.2021).</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23151</furl>
          <file>UBS10403.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>13.01.2023.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Управление техническими системами и технологическими процессами</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>100-117</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Катаев</surname>
              <initials>Дмитрий Евгеньевич</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>dekataev@ipu.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Kataev</surname>
              <initials>Dmitry</initials>
              <orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Кутяков</surname>
              <initials>Евгений Юрьевич</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>evgeniykutyakov@gmail.com</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Kutyakov</surname>
              <initials>Evgeniy</initials>
              <orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Модальный анализ по ляпунову на основе измерений с помощью прони-анализа</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Measurement-based lyapunov modal analysis using prony analysis</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Для современных электроэнергетических систем (ЭЭС) проблема исследования их устойчивости продолжает быть особо актуальной в связи с тенденциями развития структур генерации и потребления. Модальный анализ по Ляпунову совмещает два подхода к оценке устойчивости систем и ЭЭС в частности: модальный анализ и спектральные разложения функций Ляпунова. Существующие исследования, связанные с ним, предполагают наличие линейной модели системы. В то же время существует большой интерес к методам исследования устойчивости ЭЭС, основанным на измерениях, а не моделях. Это мотивирует изучить возможности модального анализа по Ляпунову на основе измерений. Данная работа представляет пример реализации такого подхода с помощью Прони-анализа. Получены выражения для вычисления модальных вкладов по Ляпунову на основе данных, получаемых методом Прони из измерений в нелинейной системе. Представлены результаты вычислительных экспериментов, проведенных с помощью созданной программной реализации измерительной модификации модального анализа по Ляпунову. Проведено исследование переходных процессов напряжения в узлах сети тестовой модели IEEE 68. Также представлены результаты сравнения измерительной и модельной модификаций.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">Modern power grids are in need of advanced stability analysis tools due to their generation and consumption development trends. Lyapunov modal analysis combines two stability analysis approaches: modal analysis and Lyapunov functions spectral decomposition. Related currently available research requires a linear model of a studied system. Nevertheless, there is a significant interest in data-driven stability analysis methods based on measurements rather than pre-existing models. This motivates the presented study of measurement-based Lyapunov modal analysis feasibility. We derived new formulas for Lyapunov modal contributions calculation that based on data provided by Prony analysis of measurements captured in a nonlinear models or systems. We also conducted case studies using our software implementation of measurement-based Lyapunov modal analysis and node voltage transients measured in IEEE 68 power system model. The paper concludes with comparative analysis between measurement and model-based implementations.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>519.7</udk>
          <bbk>22.18</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.104.4</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>электроэнергетическая система</keyword>
            <keyword>модальный анализ</keyword>
            <keyword>Прони анализ</keyword>
            <keyword>уравнение Ляпунова</keyword>
            <keyword>спектральное разложение</keyword>
            <keyword>power system</keyword>
            <keyword>modal analysis</keyword>
            <keyword>Prony analysis</keyword>
            <keyword>Lyapunov equation</keyword>
            <keyword>spectral decomposition</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>ВОРОПАЙ Н.И., ГОЛУБ И.И., ЕФИМОВ Д.Н., ИСКА-КОВ А.Б., ЯДЫКИН И.Б. Спектральный и модальный ме-тоды в исследованиях устойчивости электроэнергетиче-ских систем и управлении ими // Автоматика и телемеха-ника. – 2020. – №10. – С. 3–34.</reference>
          <reference>КАТАЕВ Д.Е. Развитие и применение метода суб-грамианов для анализа устойчивости электроэнергетиче-ских систем: Дис. канд. техн. наук. – Москва, 2018. –127 с. – URL: https://viewer.rsl.ru/ru/rsl01009824744 (дата об-ращения: 16.03.2023).</reference>
          <reference>ЯДЫКИН И.Б. О свойствах грамианов непрерывных си-стем управления // Автоматика и телемеханика. – 2010. –№6. – С. 39–50</reference>
          <reference>ЯДЫКИН И.Б., ИСКАКОВ А.Б. Новые методы оценива-ния устойчивости и управления в сложных электроэнер-гетических системах на основе спектрального и струк-турного анализа // Труды 13-й Международной конферен-ции «Управление развитием крупномасштабных систем»(MLSD’2020, Москва). – 2020. – С. 1977–1982.</reference>
          <reference>CHAKRABORTY R., JAIN H., SEO G.-S. A review ofactive probing-based system identification techniques withapplications in power systems // Int. Journal of ElectricalPower and Energy Systems. – 2022. – Vol. 140. – URL:https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijepes.2022.108008 (дата обращения:17.03.2023).</reference>
          <reference>DELGADO FERNANDEZ O., TIISTOLA S., GUSRIALDI A.Real-Time Data-Driven Electromechanical OscillationMonitoring using Dynamic Mode Decomposition withSliding Window // IFAC-PapersOnLine. – 2022. – Vol. 55,Iss. 9. – URL: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ifacol.2022.07.028(дата обращения: 17.03.2023).</reference>
          <reference>FERNANDEZ RODRIGUEZ A., DE SANTIAGORODRIGO L., LOPEZ GUILLEN E., RODRIGUEZASCARIZ J.M., MIGUEL JIMENEZ J.M., BOQUETE L.Coding Prony’s method in MATLAB and applying it tobiomedical signal filtering // BMC Bioinformatics. – 2018. –19:451. – URL: https://doi.org/10.1186/s12859-018-2473-y(дата обращения: 06.03.2022).</reference>
          <reference>HATZIARGYRIOU N. ET AL. Definition and Classification ofPower System Stability – Revisited &amp; Extended // IEEE Trans.on Power Systems. – 2021. – Vol. 36, No. 4. – P. 3271–3281. –URL: https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9286772 (дата об-ращения: 17.03.2022).</reference>
          <reference>ISKAKOV A.B., YADYKIN I.B. Lyapunov modal analysis andparticipation factors applied to small-signal stability of powersystems // Automatica. – 2021. – Vol. 132. С. – Art. No. 109814.</reference>
          <reference>ISKAKOV A.B., YADYKIN I.B. On Spectral Decompositionof States and Gramians of Bilinear DynamicalSystems // Mathematics. – 2021. – Vol. 9(24). – URL:https://www.mdpi.com/2227-7390/9/24/3288 (дата обраще-ния: 17.03.2022).</reference>
          <reference>KATAEV D.E., KUTYAKOV E.Y. Physically meaningfulLyapunov modal contributions in linear systems // SystemsScience &amp; Control Engineering. – 2022. – Vol. 10,No. 1. – URL: https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/21642583.2022.2068165 (дата обращения:06.03.2022).</reference>
          <reference>KOSTEREV D.N., TAILOR C.W., MITTELSTADT W.A.Model validation for the August 10, 1996 WSCC systemoutage // IEEE Trans. on Power Systems. – 1999. – Vol. 14, No.3. – P. 967–979. – URL: https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/780909?arnumber=780909 (дата обращения: 06.03.2022).</reference>
          <reference>MILANO F., DORFLER F., HUG G., HILL D.J., VERBIC G.Foundations and challenges of low-inertia systems (invitedpaper) // Proc. 20 Power Systems Computation Conf. (PSCC). –Manchester, UK, June 11–15, 2018.</reference>
          <reference>PERIC V.S., BAUDETTE M., VANFRETTI L.,GJERDE J.O., LOVLUND S. Implementation andtesting of a real-time mode estimation algorithm usingambient PMU data // Clemson University PowerSystems Conference, Clemson, SC, USA, 2014. – URL:https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6808116 (дата обраще-ния: 16.03.2023).</reference>
          <reference>PERIC V.S., VANFRETTI L. Power-System Ambient-ModeEstimation Considering Spectral Load Properties // IEEE Trans.on Power Systems. – 2014. – Vol. 29, No. 3. – P. 1133–1143. –URL: https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6683082 (дата об-ращения: 16.03.2023).</reference>
          <reference>PIERRE J.W., TRUDNOWSKI D., DONNELLY M.,ZHOU N., TUFFNER F.K., DOSIEK L. Overview of SystemIdentification for Power Systems from Measured Responses //16th IFAC Symposium on System Identification, Brussels,Belgium, July 11-13, 2012. – P. 989–1000.</reference>
          <reference>SHAIR J., LI H., HU J., XIE X. Power system stabilityissues, classifications and research prospects in the contextof high-penetration of renewables and power electronics //Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews. – 2021. –Vol. 145. – URL: https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1364032121003993 (дата обращения: 17.03.2023).</reference>
          <reference>TEEUWSEN S.P., ERLICH I., FISCHER A., EL-SHARKAWI M.A. Assessment of the small signal stabilityof the European interconnected electric power system usingneural networks // Proc. of the Large Engineering SystemsConference on Power Engineering – 2001 (LESCOPE–01). Theme: Powering Beyond 2001 (Cat. No.01ex490),Halifax, NS, Canada, 2001. – P. 158–161. – URL:https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/941643 (дата обращения:16.03.2023).</reference>
          <reference>VANFRETTI L., CHOW J.H. Identification of DominantInter-Area Modes in the Eastern Interconnection fromPMU data of the FRCC 2008 Disturbance: an EigensystemRealization Algorithm Illustration // Contribution to SpecialPublication of the Task Force on Modal Identification ofElectromechanical Modes, 2012. – URL: http://kth.diva-portal.org/smash/get/diva2:482085/FULLTEXT01.pdf (датаобращения: 16.03.2023).</reference>
          <reference>ZHOU N., HUANG Z., TUFFNER F., JIN S., LIN J.,HAUER M. Oscillation detection and analysis // Rep.CIEE; Executor: CIEE. – 2010. – URL: https://uc-ciee.org/ciee-old/downloads/ODA_Final_Report.pdf (дата об-ращения: 06.03.2022).</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23152</furl>
          <file>UBS10404.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>23.03.2023.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <article>
        <pages>118-134</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Андрианов</surname>
              <initials>Андрей Алексеевич</initials>
              <orgName>Обнинский институт атомной энергетики НИЯУ МИФИ</orgName>
              <email>andreyandrianov@yandex.ru</email>
              <address>Обнинск</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Andrianov</surname>
              <initials>Andrei</initials>
              <orgName>Obninsk Institute for Nuclear Power Engineering NRNU MEPhI</orgName>
              <address>Obninsk</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Андрианова</surname>
              <initials>Ольга Николаевна</initials>
              <orgName>Обнинский институт атомной энергетики НИЯУ МИФИ</orgName>
              <email>o.n.andrianova@yandex.ru</email>
              <address>Обнинск</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Andrianova</surname>
              <initials>Olga</initials>
              <orgName>Obninsk Institute for Nuclear Power Engineering NRNU MEPhI</orgName>
              <address>Obninsk</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Ассимиляция данных в задачах моделирования нейтронно-физических процессов в объектах использования атомной энергии: текущие состояние и перспективы развития</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Data assimilation in neutronics modelling: current status and development prospects</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Приводятся результаты анализа состояния и перспектив развития процедур ассимиляции данных в задачах моделирования нейтронно-физических процессов в объектах использования атомной энергии (ОИАЭ), которые применяются с целью уточнения параметров нейтронно-физических моделей ОИАЭ по результатам реакторно-физических экспериментов, оценки и повышения точности расчетного предсказания характеристик проектируемых ОИАЭ, планирования новых информативных экспериментов, близких по своим нейтронно-физическим свойствам к проектируемым ОИАЭ. Приводится классификация используемых подходов к ассимиляции нейтронно-физических данных, отмечены области применения, достоинства и недостатки различных реализаций, выявлены основные тенденции и направления их дальнейшего развития, обозначены актуальные научные и прикладные задачи в рассматриваемой предметной области.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">The article presents an analysis of the current state and prospects for the development of data assimilation procedures in neutronics modelling. These procedures are used to refine the parameters of neutronics models based on reactor experiment results, improve the accuracy of calculations predicting the characteristics of nuclear facilities under development, and plan informative experiments that closely match the neutronics properties of the facilities being designed. The article provides a classification of the approaches used in data assimilation for neutronics modelling, discusses the areas of application, advantages, and disadvantages of various implementations, identifies the main trends and directions for further development, and considers the current scientific and applied problems in the subject area.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>621.039.51</udk>
          <bbk>31.4</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.104.5</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>ассимиляция данных</keyword>
            <keyword>машинное обучение</keyword>
            <keyword>анализ неопределенности</keyword>
            <keyword>нейтронно-физическое моделирование</keyword>
            <keyword>объекты использования атомной энергии</keyword>
            <keyword>реакторно-физические эксперименты.</keyword>
            <keyword>data assimilation</keyword>
            <keyword>machine learning</keyword>
            <keyword>uncertainty analysis</keyword>
            <keyword>neutronics modelling</keyword>
            <keyword>nuclear facilities</keyword>
            <keyword>reactor experiments</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>АНДРИАНОВ А.А., АНДРИАНОВА О.Н., ГОЛОВ-КО Ю.Е. Методика оценки интегральных эксперимен-тов для использования в задаче оценки точности нейтронно-физических расчетов // Депонированная ру-копись. – № 68-В2021. – 2021. – 58 с.</reference>
          <reference>АНДРИАНОВ А.А., АНДРИАНОВА О.Н., КОРО-ВИН Ю.А. и др. Программный комплекс оптимизации параметров нейтронно-физических моделей с учетом результатов интегральных экспериментов // Известия вузов. Ядерная энергетика. – 2023. – №2. – С. 148–161.</reference>
          <reference>ВАНЬКОВ А.А., ВОРОПАЕВ А.И., ЮРОВА Л.Н. Анализ реакторно-физического эксперимента. – М.: Атомиздат, 1977. – 88 с.</reference>
          <reference>УСАЧЕВ Л.Н., БОБКОВ Ю.Г. Теория возмущений и пла-нирование эксперимента в проблеме ядерных данных для реакторов. – М.: Атомиздат, 1980. – 88 c.</reference>
          <reference>УСЫНИН Г.Б., КАРАБАСОВ А.С., ЧИРКОВ В.А. Опти-мизационные модели реакторов на быстрых нейтронах. – М.: Атомиздат, 1981. – 232 с.</reference>
          <reference>CACUCI D.G., BUJOR M. Sensitivity and uncertainty anal-ysis, data assimilation, and predictive best-estimate model calibration // Handbook of Nuclear Engineering. Springer, Boston. – 2010. – DOI: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-0-387-98149-9_17 (дата обращения: 18.03.2023).</reference>
          <reference>DRAGT J.B. Statistical considerations on techniques for ad-justment // RCN-122. – Reactor Centrum Nederland. – 1970. – P. 85–105.</reference>
          <reference>IVANOV E., SAINT-JEAN C., SOBES V. Nuclear data as-similation, scientific basis and current status // EPJ Nuclear Sci. Technol. – 2021. – DOI: https://doi.org/10.1051/epjn/2021008 (дата обращения: 18.03.2023).</reference>
          <reference>GRECHANUK P., RISING M.E., PALMER T.S. Using ma-chine learning methods to predict bias in nuclear criticality safety // Jour. of Computational and Theoretical Transport. – 2019. – Vol. 47. – P. 552–565.</reference>
          <reference>HOEFER A., BUSS O. Assessing and improving model fit-ness in MOCABA data assimilation // Ann. Nucl. Energy. – 2021. – Vol. 162. – P. 10–21.</reference>
          <reference>HOEFER A., BUSS O., HENNEBACH M. et.al. MOCABA: A general Monte Carlo–Bayes procedure for improved pre-dictions of integral functions of nuclear data // Ann. Nucl. Energy. – 2015. – Vol. 77. – P. 514–521.</reference>
          <reference>HOEFER A., BUSS O., SCHMID M. Applications of Multi-variate Normal Bayesian Models in Nuclear Engineering // Nuclear Technology. – 2019. – Vol. 205, No. 12. – P. 1578–1587.</reference>
          <reference>KONING A.J. Bayesian Monte Carlo method for nuclear data evaluation // Nucl. Data Sheets. – 2015. – Vol. 123. – P. 207–213.</reference>
          <reference>NEWELL Q., SANDERS C. Stochastic uncertainty propaga-tion in Monte Carlo depletion calculations // Nuclear Sci-ence and Engineering. – 2015. – Vol. 179, No. 3. – P.  253–263.</reference>
          <reference>PALMIOTTI G., SALVATORES M. The role of experiments and of sensitivity analysis in simulation validation strategies with emphasis on reactor physics // Ann. Nucl. Energy. – 2013. – Vol. 52. – P. 10–21.</reference>
          <reference>ROCHMAN D., SCIOLLA C.M. Nuclear Data Uncertainty Propagation for a Typical PWR Fuel Assembly with Burnup // Nuclear Engineering and Technology. – 2014. – Vol. 46, No. 3. – P. 353–362.</reference>
          <reference>ROWLANDS J.L., MACDOUGALL L.D. The use of integral measurements to adjust cross-sections and predicted reactor properties // Proc. of the Int. Conf. on Fast Critical Experi-ments and their Analysis. – ANL-7320. – 1966.</reference>
          <reference>REARDEN B.T. Perturbation theory eigenvalue sensitivity analysis with Monte Carlo techniques // Nuclear Sci. Eng. – 2004. – Vol. 146, No. 3. – P. 367–382.</reference>
          <reference>SIEFMAN D., HURSIN M., ROCHMAN D. et.al. Stochastic vs. sensitivity-based integral parameter and nuclear data adjustments // Eur. Phys. J. Plus. – 2018. – Vol. 133, No. 12. – P. 429–438.</reference>
          <reference>http://www.inis.iaea.org (дата обращения: 18.03.2023).</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23153</furl>
          <file>UBS10405.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>13.04.2023.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
    </articles>
  </issue>
</journal>
