<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<journal>
  <operCard>
    <operator>ИПУ РАН|Губко М.В.</operator>
    <date>2023-12-15 16:28:52</date>
    <cntArticle>6</cntArticle>
  </operCard>
  <issn>1819-2440</issn>
  <eissn>1819-2467</eissn>
  <titleid>10618</titleid>
  <journalInfo lang="RUS">
    <title>Управление большими системами</title>
    <abbrTitle>УБС</abbrTitle>
    <publ>Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</publ>
    <placePubl>Москва</placePubl>
    <address>117997, г. Москва, ул. Профсоюзная, д. 65.</address>
  </journalInfo>
  <journalInfo lang="ENG">
    <title>Large-scale Systems Control</title>
    <abbrTitle>LSSC</abbrTitle>
  </journalInfo>
  <issue>
    <number>105</number>
    <dateUni>202309</dateUni>
    <pages>1–133</pages>
    <articles>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Системный анализ</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>6-29</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Промыслов</surname>
              <initials>Виталий Георгиевич</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>vp@ipu.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Promyslov</surname>
              <initials>Vitaly</initials>
              <orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Семенков</surname>
              <initials>Кирилл Валерьевич</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>semenkovk@ipu.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Semenkov</surname>
              <initials>Kirill</initials>
              <orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="3">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Жарко</surname>
              <initials>Елена Филипповна</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>zharko@ipu.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Jharko</surname>
              <initials>Elena</initials>
              <orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Оценка собственной характеристики киберфизической системы методом сетевых исчислений</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Evaluation of the intrinsic characteristics of a cyberphysical system by the method of network calculus</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Рассматриваются подходы к решению частной задачи обеспечения безопасности киберфизических систем, к которым относятся многие объекты критической информационной инфраструктуры, включая такие сферы как транспорт, связь, энергетика и промышленность, а именно, к оценке доступности как максимальной задержки передачи и обработки данных. Анализируются способы оценки собственной характеристики киберфизических систем – так называемой кривой обслуживания, которая представляет собой детерминированные ограничения, связывающие вход системы и минимальный поток на выходе системы. Оценка кривой обслуживания рассматривается в рамках метода сетевых исчислений и подходов мини- и макси-плюс алгебры, которые составляют математическую основу метода. Для оценки кривой обслуживания взят один ранее разработанный метод, использующий свойство дуальности преобразований мини- и макси-плюс алгебры, и предложен новый метод, основанный на связи двух видов кривых обслуживания – мини- и макси-кривой обслуживания. Методы рассматриваются с учетом их применения для реальных систем и существующих ограничений на возможности измерения, в частности, конечности временного интервала измерений. На основе анализа двух методов делается вывод, что каждый из них дает возможную кривую обслуживания, но они требуют дополнительных данных для того, чтобы полученная кривая соответствовала режиму максимального быстродействия системы.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">The paper analyzes the evaluation of the system's own characteristics, the so-called service curve, set in the form of deterministic constraints linking the input of the system and the minimum flow at the output of the system. The service curve estimation is considered within the framework of the Network Calculus method and mini-maxi plus algebra approaches, which form the mathematical basis of the method. To evaluate the service curve, one previously developed method related to the duality of mini and maxi plus algebra transformations is taken, and a new method based on the connection of two types of mini and maxi service curves is proposed. The methods are considered taking into account their application to real systems and existing limitations on measurement capabilities, in particular the finiteness of the definition of the observed data flows. The analysis of the both methods shows that each of the them gives an acceptable service curve, but they need improvement for the calculated service curve to correspond to the maximum system performance mode.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>519.6</udk>
          <bbk>30в6</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.105.1</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>киберфизическая система</keyword>
            <keyword>моделирование</keyword>
            <keyword>Network Calculus</keyword>
            <keyword>теория сетевых исчислений</keyword>
            <keyword>мини- и макси-плюс алгебра</keyword>
            <keyword>кривая обслуживания</keyword>
            <keyword>доступность</keyword>
            <keyword>безопасность</keyword>
            <keyword>cyberphysical system</keyword>
            <keyword>Network Calculus</keyword>
            <keyword>mini/maxi plus algebra</keyword>
            <keyword>service curve</keyword>
            <keyword>availability</keyword>
            <keyword>safety and security</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>ВИШНЕВСКИЙ В.М., ДУДИН А.Н., КЛИМЕНОК В.И. Стохастические системы с коррелированными потока-ми. Теория и применение в телекоммуникационных сетях. – М.: «ТЕХНОСФЕРА», 2018. – 564 с.</reference>
          <reference>КОВАЛЕНКО И.Н. Расчет вероятностных характери-стик систем. Задачи расчета вероятностных характе-ристик систем. Исследование систем в общем виде. Применение метода малого параметра. – М.: URSS, 2023. – 104 с. – ISBN 978-5-9710-5094-0. </reference>
          <reference>ПРОМЫСЛОВ В.Г., СЕМЕНКОВ К.В. Применение ме-тода Network Calculus для расчета временных характе-ристик систем управления с циклическим алгоритмом работы // Проблемы управления. – 2021. – №4. – С. 50–65. – URL: http://pu.mtas.ru/archive/Promyslov_pu_421.pdf. </reference>
          <reference>BAYBULATOV A. PROMYSLOV V., Industrial Control System Availability Assessment with a Metric Based on Delay and Dependency // IFAC-PapersOnLine. – 2021. – Vol. 54, Iss. 13. – P. 472–476.</reference>
          <reference>BOUILLARD A., Individual Service Curves for Bandwidth-Sharing Policies Using Network Calculus // IEEE Network-ing Letters. – 2021. – Vol. 3, No. 2. – P. 80–83. – DOI: 10.1109/LNET.2021.3067766. </reference>
          <reference>BOUILLARD A., JOUHET L., THIERRY E., “Service curves in Network Calculus: dos and don’ts”. RR-7094, IN-RIA. 2009, pp.24. inria-00431674 </reference>
          <reference>BOUILLARD A. Algorithms and efficiency of Network cal-culus. – Paris: École Normale Supérieure, 2014.</reference>
          <reference>BOYER M., DAIGMORTE H. Improved Service Curve for Element With Known Transmission Rate // IEEE Networking Letters. – 2023. – Vol. 5, No. 1. – P. 46–49. – DOI: 10.1109/LNET.2022.3150649.</reference>
          <reference>CRUZ L. A calculus for network delay. I. Network elements in isolation // IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory. – 1991. – Vol. 37, No. 1. – P. 114–131. – DOI: 10.1109/18.61109.</reference>
          <reference>CRUZ L. A calculus for network delay. II. Network analy-sis // IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory. – 1991. – Vol. 37, No. 1. – P. 132–141. – DOI: 10.1109/18.61110. </reference>
          <reference>FIDLER M. Survey of deterministic and stochastic service curve models in the network calculus // IEEE Commun. Surv. Tutorials. – 2010. – Vol. 12, No. 1. – P. 59–86. – DOI: 10.1109/SURV.2010.020110.00019. </reference>
          <reference>LE BOUDEC J-Y., THIRAN P. Network Calculus: A Theory of Deterministic Queuing Systems for the Internet. – Springer Verlag, Online Version of the Book, LNCS 2022. – 245 p. </reference>
          <reference>LIEBEHERR J. Duality of the Max-Plus and Min-Plus Net-workCalculus // Foundations and Trends in Networking. – 2017. – Vol. 11, No. 3–4. – P. 139–282. – DOI: 10.1561/1300000059. </reference>
          <reference>LIEBEHERR J., FIDLER M. AND VALAEE S. A System-Theoretic Approach to Bandwidth Estimation // IEEE/ACM Trans. on Networking. – 2010. – Vol. 18, No. 4. – P. 1040–1053. – DOI: 10.1109/TNET.2009.2035115.</reference>
          <reference>Modular Performance Analysis with Real-Time Calculus. https://www.mpa.ethz.ch (дата обращения: 12.07.2023).</reference>
          <reference>SIMON I. Recognizable sets with multiplicities in the tropical semiring // Mathematical Foundations of Computer Science. Lecture Notes in Computer Science. – 1988. – Vol. 324. – P. 107–120.</reference>
          <reference>THIELE L., CHAKRABORTY S., NAEDELE M. Real-time calculus for scheduling hard real-time systems // Proc. of the IEEE Int. Symposium on Circuits and Systems. Emerging Technologies for the 21st Century. (IEEE Cat No.00CH36353), Geneva, Switzerland, 2000. – Vol. 4. – P. 101–104. – DOI: 10.1109/ISCAS.2000.858698. </reference>
          <reference>ZHOU B., HOWENSTINE I., LIMPRAPAIPONG S., CHENG L. A Survey on Network Calculus Tools for Network Infrastructure in Real-Time Systems // IEEE Access. – 2020. – Vol. 8. – P. 223588–223605. – DOI: 10.1109/ACCESS.2020.3043600.</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23156</furl>
          <file>UBS10501.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>21.07.2023.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <article>
        <pages>30-40</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Малышев</surname>
              <initials>Сергей Вадимович</initials>
              <orgName>МГУ им. М. В. Ломоносова</orgName>
              <email>serge.malychev@mail.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Malyshev</surname>
              <initials>Sergey</initials>
              <orgName>Moscow State University</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Программная реализация численного метода лакса – фридрихса для моделирования нестационарных задач газовой динамики</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Software implementation of the lax – friedrichs numerical method for modeling nonstationary problems of gas dynamics</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Статья посвящена программной реализации численного метода Лакса –Фридрихса для моделирования нестационарных задач газовой динамики. Рассматривается задача Сода в двух измерениях в следующей постановке: имеется замкнутая ударная труба с пластинкой посередине, которая разделяет два газа с разными термодинамическими характеристиками. В начальный момент времени она моментально удаляется, газы при этом смешиваются. Появляется разрыв и возникает ударная волна. Цель работы заключается в нахождении термодинамических характеристик в произвольный момент времени и в программной реализации расчётов с помощью численного метода Лакса –Фридрихса. Задача является актуальной в силу нехватки чётких вычислительных алгоритмов в сфере газовой динамики. Точность решения зависит от количества ячеек в сетке, на которую разбивается поверхность. В результате приведён расчёт и численные значения для разных сеток, точное и численное решения сравнены в различных нормах.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">This article is devoted to the software implementation of the numerical Lax-Friedrichs method for modeling nonstationary problems of gas dynamics. The Soda problem is considered in two dimensions. We postulate it in the following way: there is a closed shock tube with a plate in the middle. The plate separates two gases with different thermodynamic characteristics. At the initial moment of time, it is instantly deleted: gases mix and produce a shock wave. The purpose of the work is to find the thermodynamic characteristics at any time and to program the implementation of calculations using the numerical Lax-Friedrichs method. This task is relevant at the moment due to the lack of clear computational algorithms in the field of gas dynamics. The solution depends on the number of cells in the grid into which the surface is divided. As a result, the calculation and numerical values for different grids are given as well as their comparison with the help of various norms is made.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>533.2</udk>
          <bbk>30.124</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.105.2</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>ударные волны</keyword>
            <keyword>задача Сода</keyword>
            <keyword>численный метод Лакса – Фридрихса</keyword>
            <keyword>shock wave</keyword>
            <keyword>Soda problem</keyword>
            <keyword>Lax-Friedrichs numerical method</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>КУРАНТ Р., ФРИДРИХС К., ЛЕВИ Г. О разностных уравнениях математической физики // Успехи матема-тических наук. – 1941. – №8. – С. 125–160.</reference>
          <reference>ЛОЙЦЯНСКИЙ Л.Г. Механика жидкости и газа: Учеб. Для вузов. – 7-е изд., испр. – М.: Дрофа, 2003.</reference>
          <reference>ОВСЯННИКОВ Л.В. Лекции по основам газовой дина-мики. – Москва – Ижевск: Институт компьютерных ис-следований, 2003.</reference>
          <reference>СТУЛОВ В.П. Лекции по газовой динамике. – М.: ФИЗ-МАТЛИТ, 2004.</reference>
          <reference>ЧЁРНЫЙ Г.Г. Газовая динамика. – М.: Наука, Гл. ред. физ.-мат. лит., 1988.</reference>
          <reference>УИЗЕМ ДЖ. Линейные и нелинейные волны. – М.: Мир, 1973.</reference>
          <reference>COURANT R., FRIEDRICHS K., LEWY H. Über die par-tiellen Differenzengleichungen der mathematischen Physik // Mathematische Annalen. – 1928. – Vol. 100, No. 1. – P. 32–74.</reference>
          <reference>LEVEQUE R.J. Numerical Methods for Conservation Laws. – Basel, Boston, Berlin: Birkhäuser, 1922. –P. 125.</reference>
          <reference>SOD G.A. A Survey of Several Finite Difference Methods for Systems of Nonlinear Hyperbolic Conservation Laws // J. Comput. Phys. – 1978. – Vol. 27. – P. 1–31.</reference>
          <reference>WEISSTEIN E.W. Courant -Friedrichs-Lewy Condition [Электронный ресурс]. – URL: https://mathworld.wolfram.com/Courant-Friedrichs-LewyCondition.html (дата обращения: 16.11.2020).</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23157</furl>
          <file>UBS10502.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>21.07.2023.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Анализ и синтез систем управления</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>41-64</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Антипов</surname>
              <initials>Алексей Семенович</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>scholess18@mail.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Antipov</surname>
              <initials>Aleksey</initials>
              <orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Ткачева</surname>
              <initials>Ольга Сергеевна</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>tkolga17@gmail.com</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Tkacheva</surname>
              <initials>Olga</initials>
              <orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Робастное управление ходовой тележкой однобалочного мостового крана при действии несогласованных возмущений и при неполных измерениях</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Robust control of the trolley of a single girder overhead crane under the action of unmatched perturbations and incomplete measurement</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Рассматривается проблема управления электромеханической системой – ходовой тележкой однобалочного мостового крана (механическая подсистема) с учетом редуцированной динамики двигателя постоянного тока (электрическая подсистема). Объект функционирует в условиях недостатка управлений, действия параметрических и внешних возмущений, неполных измерений. При этом возмущения, действующие на механическую подсистему, являются несогласованными. Для безопасного переноса груза в указанных условиях предложен ряд решений. Сформирована эталонная траектория тележки с интегралом от угловой координаты. Наличие интегральной части приводит к демпфированию колебаний груза. Показано, что эта часть также позволяет подавить несогласованные ветровые возмущения. Для отслеживания сформированной траектории разработана процедура блочного синтеза сигмовидных фиктивных управлений в механической подсистеме и истинного разрывного управления в электрической подсистеме. Гладкие и ограниченные сигмовидные функции обеспечивают подавление несогласованных возмущений. Эти функции реализуемы в исполнительном устройстве и не приводят к его сильному износу, который происходит при формировании разрывных фиктивных управлений. Для информационной поддержки закона управления разработан динамический дифференциатор с сигмовидным корректирующим воздействием, предоставляющим оценку скорости по измерению ошибки слежения с любой заданной точностью. Предложенное решение позволит отказаться от датчика скорости тележки и избежать всплесков оценочных сигналов. Представлены результаты численного моделирования замкнутых систем с разрывными и сигмовидными фиктивными управлениями. Они продемонстрировали эффективность разработанного подхода.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">We considered the problem of controlling an electromechanical system, which is a single-girder overhead crane trolley (mechanical subsystem) with the reduced dynamics of a DC motor (electrical subsystem). The plant operates under conditions of lack of controls, the action of parametric and external perturbations, and incomplete measurements. In this case, the perturbations acting on the mechanical subsystem are unmatched. For safe transfer of payload in these conditions, a number of solutions have been proposed. A reference trolley trajectory with an integral of the angular coordinate has been formed. The presence of the integral part leads to the damping of payload oscillations. It is shown that this part also makes it possible to suppress unmatched wind perturbations. To track the generated trajectory, a procedure for block synthesis of sigmoid fictitious controls in the mechanical subsystem and true discontinuous control in the electrical subsystem has been developed. Smooth and bounded sigmoid functions provide suppression of unmatched perturbations. These functions are implemented in the actuator and do not lead to its strong wear, which occurs during the formation of discontinuous fictitious controls. For information support of the control law, a dynamic differentiator with a sigmoid corrective action has been developed, which provides an estimate of the speed by measuring the tracking error with any given accuracy. The proposed solution will make it possible to abandon the trolley speed sensor and avoid jumps in evaluation signals. The results of numerical simulation of closed-loop systems with discontinuous and sigmoid fictitious controls are presented. They demonstrated the effectiveness of the developed approach.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>62 – 503.54</udk>
          <bbk>39.9</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.105.3</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>ходовая тележка мостового крана</keyword>
            <keyword>несогласованные возмущения</keyword>
            <keyword>параметрическая неопределенность</keyword>
            <keyword>робастное управление</keyword>
            <keyword>сигмовидная функция</keyword>
            <keyword>динамический дифференциатор</keyword>
            <keyword>overhead crane’s trolley</keyword>
            <keyword>unmatched perturbations</keyword>
            <keyword>parametric uncertainty</keyword>
            <keyword>robust control</keyword>
            <keyword>sigmoid function</keyword>
            <keyword>dynamic differentiator</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>АНТИПОВ А.C., КРАСНОВА C.А. Система стабилиза-ции положения тележки крана с использованием сигмо-идальной функции // Мехатроника, автоматизация, управление. – 2019. – Т. 20, №10. – С. 609–614.  </reference>
          <reference>КАБАНОВ С.А., НИКУЛИН Е.Н., ЯКУШЕВ Б.Э., ЯКУ-ШЕВА Д.Б. Оптимальное управление перемещением гру-за мостовым краном // Приборостроение. – 2011. – №5. – С. 56–65.</reference>
          <reference>КОКУНЬКО Ю.Г., КРАСНОВА С.А. Два подхода к син-тезу инвариантной системы слежения для беспилотно-го летательного аппарата // Управление большими си-стемами. – 2020. – №85. – C.113–142.</reference>
          <reference>КРАСНОВА С.А., УТКИН В.А., УТКИН А.В. Блочный подход к анализу и синтезу инвариантных нелинейных систем слежения // Автоматика и телемеханика. – 2017. – №12. – С. 26–53.</reference>
          <reference>КРУГЛОВ С.П., КОВЫРШИН С.В., АКСАМЕНТОВ Д.Н. Адаптивное управление двухмаятниковым подвесом мо-стового крана // Мехатроника, автоматизация, управле-ние. – 2022. – Т. 23, №9. – С. 451–461.</reference>
          <reference>ALGHANIM K., MOHAMMED A., ANDANI M. An input shaping control scheme with application on overhead cranes // Int. Journal of Nonlinear Sciences and Numerical Simulation. – 2019. – Vol. 20, Iss. 5. – P. 561–573.</reference>
          <reference>ANTIPOV A.S., KRASNOVA S.A. Using of Sigmoid Func-tions in the Control System of the Overhead Crane // Proc. of the 16th Int. Conf. on Stability and Oscillations of Nonlinear Control Systems (Pyatnitskiy's Conference). – Moscow: IEEE, 2022. – P. 1–4 </reference>
          <reference>ANTIPOV A.S., KRASNOVA S.A., PIVNEVA S.V. Trajec-tory Planning of Crane Trolley for Smooth Payload Trans-portation // Proc. of the 15th Int. Conf. Management of Large-Scale System Development (MLSD). – Moscow: IEEE, 2022. – P. 1–5.</reference>
          <reference>CAO X., WANG Z.,  ZHANG X. Precise Locating Control for a Polar Crane Based on Sliding Mode Active Disturb-ance Rejection Control and Quadratic Programming Algo-rithm // Machines. – 2021. – Vol. 9, No. 2. – P. 1–21. </reference>
          <reference>CRISTOFARO A., DE LUCA A. Reduced-Order Observer Design for Robot Manipulators // IEEE Control Systems Let-ters. –2022. – Vol. 7. – P. 520–525.</reference>
          <reference>HUAN X. et al. Sliding Mode Observation and Control for Overhead Cranes with Varying Rope Length //  China Auto-mation Congress (CAC–2021). – 2021. – P. 4578–4583. </reference>
          <reference>JAFARI J., GHAZAL M., NAZEMIZADEH M. A LQR Opti-mal Method to Control the Position of an Overhead Crane // Int. Journal of Robotics and Automation. – 2014. – Vol.3, No. 4. – P. 252–258.</reference>
          <reference>JOLEVSKI D., BEGO O. Model predictive control of gan-try/bridge crane with anti-sway algorithm // Journal of Me-chanical Science and Technology. – 2015. – Vol. 29. – P. 827–834.</reference>
          <reference>LA V.D., NGUYEN K.T. Combination of input shaping and radial spring-damper to reduce tridirectional vibration of crane payload // Mechanical Systems and Signal Pro-cessing. – 2019. – Vol. 116. – P. 310–321.</reference>
          <reference>MA B., FANG Y., ZHANG X. Adaptive Tracking Control for an Overhead Crane System // Proc. of the 17th IFAC World Congress. Seoul, July, 2008.  – 2008. – P. 12194–12199. </reference>
          <reference>MOHAMED K.T., ABDEL-RAZAK M.H., HARAZ E.H., ATA A.A. Fine tuning of a PID controller with inlet deriva-tive filter using Pareto solution for gantry crane systems // AEJ - Alexandria Engineering Journal. – 2021. – Vol. 61, No. 9. – P. 6659–6673.</reference>
          <reference>SHEHU M.A., AI-JUN LI, TIAN H. Modified Higher-Order Sliding Mode Observer-Based Super-Twisting Controller for Perturbed Overhead Cranes // Chinese Automation Con-gress (CAC–2019), Hangzhou, China. – 2019. – P. 255–260.</reference>
          <reference>SHI L., CUI S., LI X., ZHANG Y. Sliding Mode Control of Overhead Crane Based on High Gain Observer // IEEE 5th Advanced Information Management, Communicates, Elec-tronic and Automation Control Conference (IMCEC–2022), Chongqing, China. – 2022. – P. 1–4.</reference>
          <reference>XU R., ZHOU M. Sliding mode control with sigmoid func-tion for the motion tracking control of the piezo-actuated stages // Electron. Lett. – 2017. – Vol. 53, No. 2. – P. 75–77. </reference>
          <reference>XI Z., HESKETH T. Discrete time integral sliding mode con-trol for overhead crane with uncertainties // IET Control Theory &amp; Applications. – 2010. – Vol. 4, Iss. 10. – P. 2071–2081. </reference>
          <reference>ZHANG M., MA X., SONG R., RONG X., TIAN G., TIAN X., LI Y. Adaptive Proportional-Derivative Sliding Mode Control Law With improved Transient Performance for Underactuated Overhead Crane Systems // IEEE CAA J. Autom. Sin. – 2018. – Vol. 5, No. 3. – P. 683–690.</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23158</furl>
          <file>UBS10503.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>26.07.2023.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Сетевые модели в управлении</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>65-84</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Вытовтов</surname>
              <initials>Константин Анатольевич</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>vytovtov_konstan@mail.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Vytovtov</surname>
              <initials>Konstantin</initials>
              <orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Барабанова</surname>
              <initials>Елизавета Александровна</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>elizavetaalexb@yandex.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Barabanova</surname>
              <initials>Elizaveta</initials>
              <orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="3">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Вишневский</surname>
              <initials>Владимир Миронович</initials>
              <orgName>ФГБУН Институт проблем управления им. В.А. Трапезникова РАН</orgName>
              <email>vishn@inbox.ru</email>
              <address>Москва</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Vishnevsky</surname>
              <initials>Vladimir</initials>
              <orgName>V.A. Trapeznikov Institute of Control Sciences of RAS</orgName>
              <address>Moscow</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="4">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Волкова</surname>
              <initials>Светлана Анатольевна</initials>
              <orgName>Астраханский государственный технический университет</orgName>
              <email>svolkovav2017@gmail.com</email>
              <address>Астрахань</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Volkova</surname>
              <initials>Svetlana</initials>
              <orgName>Astrakhan State Technical University</orgName>
              <address>Astrakhan</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="5">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Вытовтов</surname>
              <initials>Георгий Константинович</initials>
              <orgName>Астраханский государственный технический университет</orgName>
              <email>georgii.vytovtov@gmail.com</email>
              <address>Астрахань</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Vytovtov</surname>
              <initials>Georgii</initials>
              <orgName>Astrakhan State Technical University</orgName>
              <address>Astrakhan</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Алгоритм построения системы уравнений колмогорова для исследования переходного режима двухфазных смо с большим числом заявок</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Algorithm for constructing a system of kolmogorov equations for studying the transition regime of two-phase queuing systems with a large number of requests</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Работа посвящена разработке алгоритма построения системы дифференциальных уравнений Колмогорова для двухфазной системы массового обслуживания с пуассоновским входным потоком, экспоненциальным распределением времени обслуживания на каждой фазе и произвольным конечным числом заявок в системе. Введены новые функции, существенно упрощающие алгоритм построения уравнений Колмогорова, а также инфинитезимальной матрицы системы. Проведен сравнительный анализ сложности ранее используемых алгоритмов и алгоритма, представленного авторами. Использование данного алгоритма позволит в дальнейшем получить аналитические и численные решения основных характеристик производительности двухфазной СМО с большим числом заявок в переходном режиме работы.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">This work is devoted to the development of the Kolmogorov differential equations system constructing algorithm for a single-line queuing system with a Poisson input and phase service. The case of two phase system and an arbitrary finite number of customers in the system is considered. The new functions that significantly simplify the Kolmogorov differential equations system constructing algorithm and the system infinitesimal matrix are introduced. A comparative analysis of the complexity of previous algorithms and the algorithm presented by the authors is carried out too. The use of this algorithm will allow in the future to obtain analytical and numerical solutions of the main performance characteristics of the M/PH/1/n QS with a large number of applications in the transient operation mode.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>519.217.13</udk>
          <bbk>30в6</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.105.4</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>двухфазная система массового обслуживания</keyword>
            <keyword>переходной режим</keyword>
            <keyword>уравнения Колмогорова</keyword>
            <keyword>сложность алгоритма</keyword>
            <keyword>a single-line queuing system</keyword>
            <keyword>phase service</keyword>
            <keyword>Kolmogorov differential equations system</keyword>
            <keyword>algorithm complexity</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>БАРАБАНОВА Е.А., ВЫТОВТОВ К.А., ПОДЛАЗОВ В.С. Двухкаскадные дуальные фотонные коммутаторы в расширенном схемном базисе // Проблемы управления. – 2021. – № 1. – С. 69–81.</reference>
          <reference>БАРАБАНОВА Е.А., ВЫТОВТОВ К.А. Аналитический метод исследования поведения системы массового об-служивания при скачкообразно-изменяющихся потоках информации // Физические основы приборостроения. – 2021. – Т. 10, №1(39). – С. 36–47.</reference>
          <reference>ВИШНЕВСКИЙ В.М., ДУДИН А.Н., КЛИМЕНОК В.И. Стохастические системы с коррелированными потока-ми. Теория и применение в телекоммуникационных се-тях. – М.: Рекламно-издательский центр «ТЕХНОСФЕ-РА». – 2018. – 564 с. </reference>
          <reference>ДУДИН С.А., ДУДИНА О.С. Модель функционирования центра информационной и технической поддержки как двухфазная система массового обслуживания // Про-блемы передачи информации. – 2013. – Т. 49, №1. – С. 66–82. – DOI:10.1134/S0032946013010067.</reference>
          <reference>КРУПКИЙ В.Н., ПЛИСКО В.Е. Теория алгоритмов. – М.: Академия, 2009. – 208 с. </reference>
          <reference>САВИНОВ Ю.Г., ЩУКИН А.Н., ПОДГОРНОВ М.Д. Ма-тематическая модель мультисервисного кол-центра с многоэтапным обслуживанием и дообслуживанием не-приоритетных заявок // Ученые записки УлГУ. Сер. Ма-тематика и информационные технологии. Ул-ГУ.Электрон. журн. – 2021. – №1. – С. 109–117.</reference>
          <reference>GRIFFITHS J.D., LEONENKO G.M., WILLIAMS J.E. The transient solution to M/Ek/1 queue // Operations Research Letters. – 2006. – Vol. 34. – P. 349–354.</reference>
          <reference>GRIFFITHS J.D., LEONENKO G.M., WILLIAMS J.E. Time-Dependent Analysis of Non-Empty M/Ek/1 Queue // Quality Technology of Quantitative Management Quantitative Man-agement. – 2008. – Vol. 5, No. 3. – P. 309–320.</reference>
          <reference>JACKSON R.R.P. Queueing Systems with Phase Type Ser-vice // Operational Research Society. – 1954. – Vol. 5, No. 4. – P. 109–120.</reference>
          <reference>KEMPA W.M., PAPROCKA I. Transient behavior of a queueing model with hyper-exponentially distributed pro-cessing times and finite buffer capacity // Sensors. – 2022. – Vol. 22(24). – P. 9909. https://doi.org/10.3390/s22249909.</reference>
          <reference>KLIMENOK V.I., VISHNEVSKY V. A dual tandem queue with multi-server stations and losses // Communications in Computer and Information Science. – 2016. – Vol. 608. – P. 316–325.</reference>
          <reference>RUBINO G. Transient analysis of Markovian queueing sys-tems: A survey with focus on closed forms and uniformiza-tion // Queueing Theory 2: Advanced Trends. – Wiley-ISTE: Hoboken, NJ, USA. – 2021. – P. 269–307.  </reference>
          <reference>SHIN YANG WOO, KIM DONG OK, MOON DUG HEE. An approximate analysis of tandem queues with general blocking nodes // Journal of the Korean Society for Industri-al and Applied Mathematics. – 2022. – Vol. 26, Iss. 1. – P. 1–22.</reference>
          <reference>VISHNEVSKY V., VYTOVTOV K., BARABANOVA E., SEMENOVA O. Analysis of a MAP/M/1/N Queue with Peri-odic and Non-Periodic Piecewise Constant Input Rate // Mathematics. – 2022. – Vol. 10(10). – 1684.</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23159</furl>
          <file>UBS10504.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>09.03.2023.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <section>
        <secTitle lang="RUS">Управление в социально-экономических системах</secTitle>
      </section>
      <article>
        <pages>85-109</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Нинидзе</surname>
              <initials>Давид Леванович</initials>
              <orgName>Южный федеральный университет</orgName>
              <email>davidnin@mail.ru</email>
              <address>г. Ростов-на-Дону</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Ninidze</surname>
              <initials>David</initials>
              <orgName>Southern Federal University</orgName>
              <address>Rostov-on-Don</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Угольницкий</surname>
              <initials>Геннадий Анатольевич</initials>
              <orgName>Южный федеральный университет</orgName>
              <email>ougoln@mail.ru</email>
              <address>г. Ростов-на-Дону</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Ougolnitsky</surname>
              <initials>Gennady</initials>
              <orgName>Southern Federal University</orgName>
              <address>Rostov-on-Don</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="3">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Усов</surname>
              <initials>Анатолий Борисович</initials>
              <orgName>Южный федеральный университет</orgName>
              <email>abusov@sfedu.ru</email>
              <address>г. Ростов-на-Дону</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Usov</surname>
              <initials>Anatoliy</initials>
              <orgName>Southern Federal University</orgName>
              <address>Rostov-on-Don</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Управление внедрением инноваций при различных информационных регламентах</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Management of innovation implementation using various information structures</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Исследуется двухуровневая система управления внедрением инноваций в организациях с учётом условия их «жизнеспособности». Основная задача математического моделирования согласования частных и общественных интересов в моделях продвижения инноваций заключается в том, чтобы определить подходящую стратегию продвижения инноваций при условии получения максимального дохода лицами, продвигающими инновации. Задача рассматривается в иерархической постановке. Имеется один субъект управления верхнего уровня (центр) и несколько субъектов нижнего уровня (агентов). За результат внедрения инноваций отвечает центр, а непосредственно их внедрением занимаются агенты. Центр управляет внедрением инноваций, используя различные информационные регламенты. Агенты продвигают инновации, на что получают средства от центра. При этом агенты несут личные расходы. Агенты имеют свой частный интерес, а именно, занимаются сторонней деятельностью, не связанной с продвижением инноваций, которая также приносит им доход. Указаны алгоритмы построения решений игр Гермейера при побуждении и принуждении. Численно решения строятся методом качественно репрезентативных сценариев имитационного моделирования. Проведены имитационные эксперименты, дан анализ полученных результатов.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">A two-level management system for the innovation implementation in organizations is studied, taking into account the conditions of their "life-ability". The main task of mathematical modeling of the coordination of private and public interests in innovation implementation models is determining the appropriate strategy for the promotion of innovations. The problem is considered in a hierarchical formulation. There is one top-level management entity (center) and several lower-level entities (agents). The center is responsible for the result of innovation implementation, and agents are directly involved in implementation. The center manages the innovation implementation using various information regulations. Agents promote innovations and they receive funds from the center. At the same time, agents bear personal expenses. Agents have their own private interest, namely, they are engaged in third-party activities, that also bring them income. These activities are not related to the innovation implementation. Algorithms for constructing solutions to Germeyer's games in motivation and compulsion are indicated. Numerical solutions are constructed using the method of qualitatively representative simulation scenarios. Simulation experiments were conducted, the analysis of the results obtained was given.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>519.83</udk>
          <bbk>22.18</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.105.5</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>игры Гермейера</keyword>
            <keyword>побуждение</keyword>
            <keyword>принуждение</keyword>
            <keyword>имитационное моделирование</keyword>
            <keyword>метод качественно репрезентативных сценариев</keyword>
            <keyword>внедрение инноваций</keyword>
            <keyword>Germeyer's games</keyword>
            <keyword>motivation</keyword>
            <keyword>compulsion</keyword>
            <keyword>simulation modeling</keyword>
            <keyword>method of qualitatively representative scenarios</keyword>
            <keyword>innovation implementation</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>АКЕРМАН Е.Н., МИХАЛЬЧУК А.А., СПИЦЫН В.В., ЧИСТЯКОВА Н.О. Оценка имитационного потенциала IT-компаний при помощи производственной функции Кобба–Дугласа // ВЕСТНИК НГУЭУ. – 2019. – №4. – С. 130–142. </reference>
          <reference>АФАНАСЬЕВ А.А. Использование производственной функции Кобба – Дугласа, построенной по панельным данным, при анализе обрабатывающих производств России // Креативная экономика. – 2022. – Т. 16, №6. – С. 2363–2380.</reference>
          <reference>ГОРЕЛИК В.А., ГОРЕЛОВ М.А., КОНОНЕНКО А.Ф. Анализ конфликтных ситуаций в системах управления. – М.: Радио и связь, 1991. – 288 с.</reference>
          <reference>КУЛИКОВ И.Н. Модели финансирования инновационных технологий// Управление экономическими системами: электронный научный журнал. – 2015. – №8. – URL: www.uecs.ru/innovacii-investicii/item/3679-2015-08-28-07-07-34.</reference>
          <reference>МАКАРОВ А.С., САЗАНОВА Д.А. Источники и модели финансирования инновационной деятельности органи-зации. – М.: Изд-во ООО «Издательский дом Финансы и Кредит», 2011. – №18 – С. 42-46.</reference>
          <reference>МУНТЬЯНОВА А.А. Моделирование инновационной со-ставляющей сбалансированной системы показателей ИТ-компании // Инженерный вестник Дона. – 2017. – №2. – URL: www.ivdon.ru/ru/magazine/archive/N2y2017/4217.</reference>
          <reference>НОВИКОВ Д.А., ИВАЩЕНКО А.А. Модели и методы организационного управления инновационным развити-ем фирмы. – М.: ЛЕНАНД, 2006. – 336 с.</reference>
          <reference>УГОЛЬНИЦКИЙ Г.А., УСОВ А.Б. Алгоритмы решения дифференциальных моделей иерархических систем управления // Автоматика и телемеханика. – 2016. – №5. – С. 148–158.</reference>
          <reference>УГОЛЬНИЦКИЙ Г.А., УСОВ А.Б. Динамические модели согласования частных и общественных интересов при продвижении инноваций // Математическая теория игр и её приложения. – 2019. – №11(1). – С. 96–114.</reference>
          <reference>УГОЛЬНИЦКИЙ Г.А., УСОВ А.Б. Равновесия в моделях иерархически организованных динамических систем с учётом требований устойчивого развития // Автомати-ка и телемеханика. – 2014. – №6. – С. 86–102.</reference>
          <reference>УГОЛЬНИЦКИЙ Г.А., УСОВ А.Б. Теоретико-игровая модель согласования интересов при инновационном раз-витии корпорации // Компьютерные исследования и мо-делирование. – 2016. – №8(4). – С. 673–684.</reference>
          <reference>УГОЛЬНИЦКИЙ Г.А. Управление устойчивым разви-тием активных систем. – Ростов-на-Дону: Изд-во ЮФУ, 2016. – С. 658–704.</reference>
          <reference>ШИШАЕВ М.Г. Комплексная системно-динамическая модель рыночной диффузии инновационного продукта // Труды института системного анализа Российской Ака-демии наук. – М.: 2009. – С. 223–244.</reference>
          <reference>BASAR T., OLSDER G.Y. Dynamic Non-Cooperative Game Theory. – SIAM, 1999. </reference>
          <reference>BASAR T., ZHU Q. Prices of Anarchy, Information, and Cooperation in Differential Games // Dynamic Games and Applications. – 2011. – No. 1(1). – P. 50–73.</reference>
          <reference>DOCKNER E., JORGENSEN S., LONG N.V., SORGER G. Differential Games in Economics and Management Science. – Cambridge University Press, 2000.</reference>
          <reference>EDISON H., BIN ALI N., TORKAR R. Towards innovation measurement in the software industry // J. of Systems and Software. – Netherlands: Elsevier, 2013.</reference>
          <reference>HOSSAIN НM., MAJUMDER A., BASAK T. An Applica-tion of Non–Linear Cobb-Douglas Production Function to Selected Manufacturing Industries in Bangladesh // Open Journal of Statistics. – 2012. – Vol. 2, No. 4. – P. 460–468.</reference>
          <reference>JUNGSU KIM, GOO HYEOK CHUNG. Implementing inno-vations within organizations: a systematic review and re-search agenda // Innovation: Organization &amp; Management. – 2017. – Vol. 19, Iss. 3 – P. 372–399.</reference>
          <reference>KLEIN K.J., BUHL CONN A., SPEER SORRA J. Imple-menting computerized technology: An organizational analy-sis // J. of Applied Psychology – USA: American Psycholog-ical Association Inc., 2001.</reference>
          <reference>OUGOLNITSKY G.A., USOV A.B. Computer Simulations as a Solution Method for Differential Games // Computer Simulations: Advances in Research and Applications / Eds.: M.D. Pfeffer, E. Bachmaier. – N.Y.: Nova Science Publish-ers, 2018. – P. 63–106.</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23160</furl>
          <file>UBS10505.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>12.04.2023.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
      <article>
        <pages>110-133</pages>
        <artType>RAR</artType>
        <authors>
          <author num="1">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Квятковская</surname>
              <initials>Ирина Юрьевна</initials>
              <orgName>Астраханский государственный технический университет</orgName>
              <email>i.kvyatkovskaya@astu.org</email>
              <address>Астрахань</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Kvyatkovskaya</surname>
              <initials>Irina</initials>
              <orgName>Astrakhan State Technical University</orgName>
              <address>Astrakhan</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="2">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname/>
              <initials>Во Тхи Хуен Чанг</initials>
              <orgName>Астраханский государственный технический университет</orgName>
              <email>vthtrang@mail.ru</email>
              <address>Астрахань</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Trang</surname>
              <initials>Vo Thi Huyen</initials>
              <orgName>Astrakhan State Technical University</orgName>
              <address>Astrakhan</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
          <author num="3">
            <individInfo lang="RUS">
              <surname>Тоан</surname>
              <initials>Чан Куок</initials>
              <orgName>Астраханский государственный технический университет</orgName>
              <email>hoaivan219@mail.ru</email>
              <address>Астрахань</address>
            </individInfo>
            <individInfo lang="ENG">
              <surname>Toan</surname>
              <initials>Tran Quoc</initials>
              <orgName>Astrakhan State Technical University</orgName>
              <address>Astrakhan</address>
            </individInfo>
          </author>
        </authors>
        <artTitles>
          <artTitle lang="RUS">Разработка рекомендательной модели поддержки принятия решения при выборе продуктов пользователем</artTitle>
          <artTitle lang="ENG">Development of a recommendation model to support decision-making when the user chooses products</artTitle>
        </artTitles>
        <abstracts>
          <abstract lang="RUS">Рекомендательные системы используются для прогнозирования предпочтений пользователей в отношении определенного продукта или услуги, а также для рекомендации пользователю подходящих продуктов или услуг. Многие методы, используемые в интеллектуальном анализе данных, связанные с классификацией или построением ассоциативных правил, применяются в рекомендательных системах. Предлагается новая рекомендательная модель, сочетающая ассоциативные правила и меры индекса статистической импликации. В предлагаемой модели меры поддержки и достоверности используются для создания ассоциативных правил, а мера индекса статистической импликации используется для фильтрации набора правил и ранжирования рекомендаций. Предложенные модель и алгоритмы использованы для построения рекомендательного результата по известному набору данных.</abstract>
          <abstract lang="ENG">Recommender systems are used to predict user preferences for a particular product or service, and to recommend suitable products or services to the user. Many of the methods used in data mining, related to classification or the construction of association rules, are used in recommender systems. This article proposes a new recommender model that combines association rules and statistical implication index measures. In the proposed model, support and confidence measures are used to create association rules, and the statistical implication index measure is used to filter the set of rules and rank recommendations. The proposed model and algorithms are used to build a recommendation result based on a known data set.</abstract>
        </abstracts>
        <text lang="RUS">NO TEXT</text>
        <codes>
          <udk>004.67</udk>
          <bbk>32.972.1</bbk>
          <doi>10.25728/ubs.2023.105.6</doi>
        </codes>
        <keywords>
          <kwdGroup lang="ANY">
            <keyword>рекомендательная система</keyword>
            <keyword>рекомендательная модель</keyword>
            <keyword>анализ статистической импликации</keyword>
            <keyword>индекс статистической импликации</keyword>
            <keyword>алгоритм Apriori</keyword>
            <keyword>ассоциативные правила</keyword>
            <keyword>recommender system</keyword>
            <keyword>recommender model</keyword>
            <keyword>statistical implication analysis</keyword>
            <keyword>statistical implication index</keyword>
            <keyword>algorithm Apriori</keyword>
            <keyword>association rules</keyword>
          </kwdGroup>
        </keywords>
        <references>
          <reference>БРАХА Ш., ЛИОР Р. Создание эффективных рекомен-дательных систем // ISBN978-1-4419-0047-0 –2012 г. Архивировано из оригинала 01.05.2014.</reference>
          <reference>БХАСКЕР Б.; СРИКУМАР К. Рекомендательные систе-мы в электронной коммерции // ЧАШКА. – ISBN978-0-07-068067-8. Архивировано из оригинала 01.09.2010.</reference>
          <reference>ФРАНЧЕСКО Р., ЛИОР Р., БРАХА Ш., КАНТОР П.Б. Справочник рекомендательных систем. – Springer. ISBN978-0-387-85819-7 – 2011.</reference>
          <reference>ШИТИКОВ В.К., МАСТИЦКИЙ С.Э. Классификация, регрессия, алгоритмы Data Mining с использованием R. – 2017. – Электронная книга. – URL: https://github.com/ranalytics/data-mining. </reference>
          <reference>ШУРШЕВ В.Ф., БУЙ Л.В. Методика выбора сканирую-щих приемников и трансиверов по основным характе-ристикам // Вестник Астраханского государственного технического университета. Серия: Управление, вычис-лительная техника и информатика. – 2013. – №2. – С. 45–51.</reference>
          <reference>ШУРШЕВ В.Ф., КОЧКИН Г.А., КОЧКИНА В.Р. Модель системы поддержки принятия решений на основе рас-суждений по прецедентам // Вестник Астраханского государственного технического университета. Серия: Управление, вычислительная техника и информатика. – 2013. – №2. – С. 175–183.</reference>
          <reference>BREESE J.S, HECKERMAN D., KADIE C.M. Anonymous web data from www.microsoft.com // Microsoft Research, Redmond WA, 98052-6399, USA, 1998. – URL: https://kdd.ics.uci.edu/databases/msweb/msweb.html.</reference>
          <reference>GRAS R. Contribution à l’étude expérimentale et à l’analyse de certaines acquisitions cognitives et de certains objectifs en didactique des mathématiques. – PhD thesis, Université de Rennes 1, 1979.</reference>
          <reference>GRAS R., KUNTZ P. An overview of the Statistical Implica-tive Analysis (SIA) development // Statistical Implicative Analysis - Studies in Computational Intelligence, Springer-Verlag. – 2008. – P. 11–40.</reference>
          <reference>GRAS R., KUNTZ P., GREFFARD N. Notion of Implicative Fields in Statistical Implicative Analysis // VIII Int. Conf. A.S.I. Analyse Statistique Implicative - Statistical Implicative Analysis Radès (Tunisie), Novembre, 2015. – P. 29–46.</reference>
          <reference>HAHSLER М. «recommenderlab: A Framework for Devel-oping and Testing Recommendation Algorithms» // The In-telligent Data Analysis Lab at SMU. – 2011. – URL: http://lyle.smu.edu/IDA/recommenderlab/.</reference>
          <reference>HIKMAWATI E., MAULIDEVI N.U., SURENDRO K. Min-imum threshold determination method based on dataset characteristics in association rule mining // J Big Data. – 2021. – Vol. 8. – P. 146. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1186/s40537-021-00538-3.</reference>
          <reference>KVYATKOVSKAYA I.Y., SHURSHEV V.F., FREN-KEL M.B. Methodology of a support of making manage-ment decisions for poorly structured problems // Communi-cations in Computer and Information Science. – 2015. – Vol. 535. – P. 278–291.</reference>
          <reference>https://archive.ics.uci.edu/ml/datasets/lenses – набор дан-ных Lenses (Lenses Data Set).</reference>
        </references>
        <files>
          <furl>http://ubs.mtas.ru/archive/search_results_new.php?publication_id=23161</furl>
          <file>UBS10506.pdf</file>
        </files>
        <dates>
          <dateReceived>29.03.2023.</dateReceived>
        </dates>
      </article>
    </articles>
  </issue>
</journal>
